<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<corpus>
	<subcorpus>
		<document name="EHRI_unit_il-002798-p_37.2.2layers.xml">
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P0">
				<sentence xml:id="P0E0">Archive of <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Benjamin Arditti</ENAMEX>: Documentation Regarding the History of <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">Bulgarian Jewry</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1850-1964</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Benjamin Arditti</ENAMEX> was born in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Vienna</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1897</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E1">He lived in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Sofia</ENAMEX> (except for <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">two years</ENAMEX> during <ENAMEX type="EVENT">World War II</ENAMEX>) from <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1916-1949</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E2">He was one of the outstanding activists in the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Zionist movement in Bulgaria</ENAMEX>: he served as a member of the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">Central Committee of the Zionist Union</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Bulgaria</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1919-1923</ENAMEX>; he held <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">five</ENAMEX> terms of office as the <ENAMEX type="TITLE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">representative</ENAMEX> to the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">World Zionist Congress</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>; he served as the <ENAMEX type="TITLE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">chairman</ENAMEX> of the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">Zionist Organization</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Sofia</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>; he was one of the founders of the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">Revisionist movement</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Bulgaria</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> and its <ENAMEX type="TITLE">chairman</ENAMEX> from <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1925-1935</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E3"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Arditti</ENAMEX> was a member of the illegal <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="NATIONAL">Committee for the Rescue of Bulgarian Jewry</ENAMEX> during <ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">World War II</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, maintaining his <ENAMEX type="CONCEPTUAL">Zionist</ENAMEX> activities and encouragement of <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">aliya to Eretz Israel</ENAMEX> after <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1944</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E4"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Arditti</ENAMEX> continued to serve as <ENAMEX type="TITLE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">representative of the Revisionists</ENAMEX> in the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">Union of Bulgarian Jews</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> during the years <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1947-1949</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E5">He made <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">aliya to Israel</ENAMEX> and joined the leadership of the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">Herut party</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">Organization of Sephardi Jews</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Israel</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1949</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E6">He also served as the <ENAMEX type="TITLE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">chairman of the Central Committee</ENAMEX> of the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">World Sephardi Federation</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> and a member of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Knesset</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P1">
				<sentence xml:id="P0E7">As early as the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1930s</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Benjamin Arditti</ENAMEX> expressed interest in the history of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Bulgaria</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>; he wrote <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">two</ENAMEX> books and many newspaper articles on the subject.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E8">He continued these activities in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Israel</ENAMEX> and concentrated on events in the history of the community during the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Holocaust</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E9">Additionally, he continued to write articles and newspaper stories regarding events in the history of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> people throughout the world, the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Zionist movement in Bulgaria</ENAMEX> and the world and the history of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Sephardi Jews</ENAMEX> and their situation in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Eretz Israel</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E10">The material in the private collection of <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Benjamin Arditti</ENAMEX> can be divided into the following classifications:</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E11">1.Personal and family documentation (correspondence, pictures and more);</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E12">2.<ENAMEX type="PERSON">Benjamin Arditti</ENAMEX>&apos;s correspondence with various institutions and public figures;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E13">3.Manuscripts and various publications (articles, essays and more, not including books) by <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Benjamin Arditti</ENAMEX>;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E14">4.Documentation regarding <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Benjamin Arditti</ENAMEX>&apos;s activities as a <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Knesset</ENAMEX> member and an activist in <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Sephardi Jewish</ENAMEX> organizations;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E15">5.Documentation regarding the history of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Bulgaria</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">until World War II</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Zionism</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Zionist movement</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Bulgaria</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> and throughout the world;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E16">6.Documentation regarding the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Bulgaria</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> during <ENAMEX type="EVENT">World War II</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E17">The material consists of the following documentation: - Internal policies of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Bulgaria</ENAMEX> during the war and <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">anti-Jewish legislation</ENAMEX>;- Implementation of the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">anti-Semitic policy</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Commissariat for Jewish Affairs activities</ENAMEX>; - Condition of the various <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> communities in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Bulgaria</ENAMEX> during the war;- Unsuccessful <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">aliya</ENAMEX> attempts to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Eretz Israel</ENAMEX> and the fate of the <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">two</ENAMEX> illegal immigrant ships,&quot;<ENAMEX type="CREATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="CREATION">Salvador</ENAMEX>&quot;and&quot;<ENAMEX subType="2" type="CREATION">Struma</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>&quot;; - The <ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Holocaust</ENAMEX> of the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Turkey</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Macedonia</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>:- Forced labor camps in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Bulgaria</ENAMEX>; - <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Rescue of the Jews of Bulgaria</ENAMEX>;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E18">7.Documentation regarding <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">aliya</ENAMEX> from <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Bulgaria</ENAMEX> to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Eretz Israel</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERIOD"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">from the late 19th century until the&quot;Great Aliya&quot;</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">1948-1949</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E19">There is also original documentation in the records group as a whole (mainly personal documentation belonging to <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Arditti</ENAMEX>, but also many documents regarding the history of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Bulgaria</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">before the 1940s</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Zionis movement</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Bulgaria</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> and the fate of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Bulgaria</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Turkey</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Macedonia</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> during the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Holocaust</ENAMEX>), photographs and copies of various documents, newspaper clippings and journals on a range of subjects.</sentence>
			</p>
		</document>
	</subcorpus>
</corpus>
