<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<corpus>
	<subcorpus>
		<document name="Wikipedia_holocaust.1.training.txt">

			<paragraph xml:id="P0">
				<sentence xml:id="P0E1">The <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Holocaust</ENAMEX> (from the <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Greek</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="EVENT">ὁλόκαυστος</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="EVENT">holókaustos</ENAMEX>: hólos," whole" and kaustós," burnt"),[3] also known as the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Shoah</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Hebrew</ENAMEX>: <ENAMEX type="EVENT">השואה</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="EVENT">HaShoah</ENAMEX>," the catastrophe"), was a genocide in which <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Adolf Hitler</ENAMEX> ' s <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> and its collaborators killed about <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">six million</ENAMEX><ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E2">[4] The victims included <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">1. 5 million</ENAMEX> children[5] and represented about <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">two - thirds of the nine million</ENAMEX><ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> who had resided in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E3">[6] Some definitions of the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Holocaust</ENAMEX> include the additional <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">five million</ENAMEX>non - <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> victims of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazi</ENAMEX> mass murders, bringing the total to about <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">11 million</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E4">Killings took place throughout <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Nazi Germany</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> - occupied territories[7] and territories held by allies of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Nazi Germany</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E5"><ENAMEX type="PERIOD">From 1941 to 1945</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> were systematically murdered in one of the deadliest genocides in history, which was part of a broader aggregate of acts of oppression and killings of various ethnic and political groups in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX> by the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Nazi regime</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E6">[8] Under the coordination of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">SS</ENAMEX>, following directions from the highest leadership of the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Nazi Party</ENAMEX>, every arm of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> ' s bureaucracy was involved in the logistics and the carrying out of the genocide.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E7">Other victims of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazi</ENAMEX> crimes included ethnic Poles, <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Soviet</ENAMEX> citizens and <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">Soviet</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="ACRONYM">POWs</ENAMEX>, other <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Slavs, Romanis, communists, homosexuals, Freemasons, Jehovah</ENAMEX> ' s Witnesses and the mentally and physically disabled.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E8">[9][10][11] A network of about <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">42, 500</ENAMEX> facilities in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> - occupied territories was used to concentrate victims for slave labor, mass murder, and other human rights abuses.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E9">[12] Over <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">200, 000</ENAMEX> people are estimated to have been <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Holocaust</ENAMEX> perpetrators.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E10">[13] The persecution and genocide were carried out in stages, culminating in what <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazis</ENAMEX> termed the" <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Final Solution to the Jewish Question</ENAMEX>" (<ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">die Endlösungder Judenfrage</ENAMEX>), an agenda to exterminate <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews in Europe</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E11">Initially the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">German government</ENAMEX> passed laws to exclude <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> from civil society, most prominently the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Nuremberg Laws of 1935</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E12"><ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazis</ENAMEX> established a network of concentration camps starting in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1933</ENAMEX> and ghettos following the outbreak of <ENAMEX type="EVENT">World War II in 1939</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E13">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1941</ENAMEX>, as <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> conquered new territory in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">eastern Europe</ENAMEX>, specialized paramilitary units called <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Einsatzgruppen</ENAMEX> murdered around <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">two million</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX>, partisans, and others often in mass shootings.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E14">By the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">end of 1942</ENAMEX>, victims were being regularly transported by freight trains to extermination camps where, if they survived the journey, most were systematically killed in gas chambers.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E15">This continued until the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">end of World War II in Europe in April – May 1945</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E16"><ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> armed resistance was limited.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E17">The most notable exception was the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Warsaw Ghetto Uprising of 1943</ENAMEX>, when <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">thousands</ENAMEX> of poorly - armed <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> fighters held the Waffen - <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">SS</ENAMEX> at bay for <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">four</ENAMEX> weeks.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E18">An estimated <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">20, 000 – 30, 000</ENAMEX><ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> partisans actively fought against the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazis</ENAMEX> and their collaborators in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Eastern Europe</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E19">[14][15] <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">French Jews</ENAMEX> took part in the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">French Resistance</ENAMEX>, which conducted a guerilla campaign against the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazis</ENAMEX> Vichy French authorities.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E20">Over <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">a hundred</ENAMEX> armed <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> uprisings took place.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E21">[16] Etymology and use of the term Main article: Names of the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Holocaust</ENAMEX> The term <ENAMEX type="EVENT">holocaust</ENAMEX> comes from the <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Greek</ENAMEX> word <ENAMEX type="EVENT">holókauston</ENAMEX>, referring to an animal sacrifice offered to a god in which the whole (olos) animal is completely burnt (kaustos).</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E22">[17] Writing in <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Latin</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Richard of Devizes</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">12th - century</ENAMEX> monk, was the <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">first</ENAMEX> to use in his <ENAMEX type="CREATION">Chronicon de rebus gestis Ricardi Primi</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1192</ENAMEX>) the term "<ENAMEX type="EVENT">holocaustum</ENAMEX>".</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E23">[18] <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Thomas Browne</ENAMEX> employed the word" <ENAMEX type="EVENT">holocaust</ENAMEX>" in his philosophical Discourse <ENAMEX type="CREATION">Urn Burial</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1658</ENAMEX>[19] and for centuries, the word was used in <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">English</ENAMEX> to denote massacres.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E24">[20] Since the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1960s</ENAMEX>, the term has come to be used by scholars and popular writers to refer specifically to the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Nazi genocide of Jews</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E25">[21] The television mini - series <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Holocaust</ENAMEX> is credited with introducing the term into common parlance after <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1978</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E26">[22] The biblical word shoah (<ENAMEX type="EVENT">שואה</ENAMEX>; also transliterated <ENAMEX type="EVENT">sho'ah</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX type="EVENT">shoa</ENAMEX>), meaning" calamity" became the standard Hebrew term for the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Holocaust</ENAMEX> as early as the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1940s</ENAMEX>, especially in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Europe and Israel</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E27">[23] <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Shoah</ENAMEX> is preferred by some <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> for several reasons including the theologically offensive nature of the word" <ENAMEX type="EVENT">holocaust</ENAMEX>" which they take to refer to the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">Greek</ENAMEX> pagan custom.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E28">[24] The <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazis</ENAMEX> used the phrase" ' <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Final Solution to the Jewish Question</ENAMEX>" and the formula" <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Final Solution</ENAMEX>" has been widely used as a term for the genocide of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E29">Distinctive features Institutional collaboration Ghettos were established in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX> in which <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> were confined before being shipped to extermination camps.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E30">Every arm of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> ' s bureaucracy was involved in the logistics that led to the genocides, turning the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Third Reich</ENAMEX> into what one <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Holocaust</ENAMEX> scholar, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Michael Berenbaum</ENAMEX>, has called" a genocidal state".</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E31">[25] Every arm of the country ' s sophisticated bureaucracy was involved in the killing process.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E32">Parish churches and the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Interior Ministry</ENAMEX> supplied birth records showing who was <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX>; the Post Office delivered the deportation and denaturalization orders; the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Finance Ministry</ENAMEX> confiscated <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">Jewish</ENAMEX> property; <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> firms fired <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> workers and disenfranchised <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> stockholders.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E33">The universities refused to admit <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX>, denied degrees to those already studying, and fired <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> academics; government transport offices arranged the trains for deportation to the camps; <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> pharmaceutical companies tested drugs on camp prisoners; companies bid for the contracts to build the crematoria; detailed lists of victims were drawn up using the Dehomag (<ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">IBM Germany</ENAMEX>) company ' s punch card machines, producing meticulous records of the killings.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E34">As prisoners entered the death camps, they were made to surrender all personal property, which was catalogued and tagged before being sent to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> to be reused or recycled.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E35"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Berenbaum</ENAMEX> writes that <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">the Final Solution of the Jewish question</ENAMEX> was" in the eyes of the perpetrators.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E36">.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E37">.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E38"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> ' s greatest achievement.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E39">"[26] Through a concealed account, the <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">German National Bank</ENAMEX> helped launder valuables stolen from the victims.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E40"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Saul Friedländer</ENAMEX> writes that:" Not one social group, not one religious community, not one scholarly institution or professional association in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> and throughout <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX> declared its solidarity with the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E41">[27] He writes that some <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Christian</ENAMEX> churches declared that converted <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> should be regarded as part of the flock, but even then only up to a point.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E42"><ENAMEX type="PERIOD">Friedländer</ENAMEX> argues that this makes the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Holocaust</ENAMEX> distinctive because <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">antisemitic policies</ENAMEX> were able to unfold without the interference of countervailing forces of the kind normally found in advanced societies such as industry, small businesses, churches, trade unions, and other vested interests and lobby groups.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E43">[27] Ideology and scale Part of a series on <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Antisemitism</ENAMEX> Yellowbadge logo.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E44">svg Part of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> history History Timeline Reference In many other genocides, pragmatic considerations such as control of territory and resources were central to the genocide policy.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E45"><ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">Israeli</ENAMEX> historian and scholar <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Yehuda Bauer</ENAMEX> argues: The basic motivation[of the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Holocaust</ENAMEX>] was purely ideological, rooted in an illusionary world of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazi</ENAMEX> imagination, where an international <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> conspiracy to control the world was opposed to a parallel <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Aryan</ENAMEX> quest.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E46">No genocide to date had been based so completely on myths, on hallucinations, on abstract, nonpragmatic ideology—which was then executed by very rational, pragmatic means.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E47">[28] <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> historian <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Eberhard Jäckel</ENAMEX> wrote in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1986</ENAMEX> that one distinctive feature of the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Holocaust</ENAMEX> was: Never before had a state with the authority of its responsible leader decided and announced that a specific human group, including its aged, its women and its children and infants, would be killed as quickly as possible, and then carried through this resolution using every possible means of state power.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E48">[29] The killings were systematically conducted in virtually all areas of <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> - occupied territory in what are now <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">35</ENAMEX> separate <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">European</ENAMEX> countries.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E49">[30] It was at its most severe in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Central and Eastern Europe</ENAMEX>, which had more than <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">seven million</ENAMEX><ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1939</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E50">About <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">five million</ENAMEX><ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> were killed there, including <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">three million</ENAMEX> in occupied <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Poland</ENAMEX> and over <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">one million</ENAMEX> in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Soviet Union</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E51"><ENAMEX type="MEASURE">Hundreds of thousands</ENAMEX> also died in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Netherlands, France, Belgium, Yugoslavia, and Greece</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E52">The <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Wannsee Protocol</ENAMEX> makes it clear the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazis</ENAMEX> intended to carry their" <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">final solution of the Jewish question</ENAMEX>" to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> and all neutral states in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX>, such as <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Ireland, Switzerland, Turkey, Sweden, Portugal, and Spain</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E53">[31] Anyone with <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">three or four</ENAMEX><ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> grandparents was to be exterminated without exception.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E54">The <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazis</ENAMEX> envisioned the extermination of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> worldwide, not only in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> proper,[32] unless their grandparents had converted before <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">18 January 1871</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E55">[33] Extermination camps Main article: Extermination camp The use of extermination camps (also called" death camps") equipped with gas chambers for the systematic mass extermination of peoples was an unprecedented feature of the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Holocaust</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E56">These were established at <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Auschwitz, Belzec, Chełmno, Jasenovac, Majdanek, Maly Trostenets, Sobibór, and Treblinka</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E57">They were built for the systematic killing of millions, primarily by gassing, but also by execution and extreme work under starvation conditions.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E58">[34] Stationary facilities built for the purpose of mass extermination resulted from earlier <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazi</ENAMEX> experimentation with poison gas during the secret <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Action T4</ENAMEX> euthanasia programme against mental patients.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E59">[35] Medical experiments Further information: <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazi</ENAMEX> human experimentation A distinctive feature of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazi</ENAMEX> genocide was the extensive use of human subjects in" medical" experiments.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E60">According to <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Raul Hilberg</ENAMEX>," <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> physicians were highly <ENAMEX type="CONCEPTUAL">Nazified</ENAMEX>, compared to other professionals, in terms of party membership.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E61">"[36] Some carried out experiments at <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Auschwitz, Dachau, Buchenwald, Ravensbrück, Sachsenhausen, and Natzweiler</ENAMEX> concentration camps.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E62">[37] The most notorious of these physicians was <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Josef Mengele</ENAMEX>, who worked in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Auschwitz</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E63">His experiments included placing subjects in pressure chambers, testing drugs on them, freezing them, attempting to change eye color by injecting chemicals into children ' s eyes, and amputations and other surgeries.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E64">[37] The full extent of his work is unknown as <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Otmar von Verschuer</ENAMEX> destroyed the truckload of records <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Mengele</ENAMEX> sent to him at the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Kaiser Wilhelm Institute</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E65">[38] Subjects who survived <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Mengele</ENAMEX> ' s experiments were almost always killed and dissected shortly afterwards.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E66"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Mengele</ENAMEX> worked extensively with <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Romani</ENAMEX> children.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E67">He would bring them sweets and toys and personally take them to the gas chamber.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E68">They would call him"<ENAMEX type="PERSON">Onkel (Uncle) Mengele</ENAMEX>".</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E69">[39] <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Vera Alexander</ENAMEX> was a <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> inmate at <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Auschwitz</ENAMEX> who looked after <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">50</ENAMEX> sets of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Romani</ENAMEX> twins: I remember one set of twins in particular: <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Guido and Ina</ENAMEX>, aged about <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">four</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E70"><ENAMEX type="PERIOD">One day</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Mengele</ENAMEX> took them away.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E71">When they returned, they were in a terrible state: they had been sewn together, back to back, like Siamese twins.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E72">Their wounds were infected and oozing pus.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E73">They screamed day and night.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E74">Then their parents—I remember the mother ' s name was <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Stella</ENAMEX>—managed to get some morphine and they killed the children in order to end their suffering.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E75">[39] Development and execution Origins <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Yehuda Bauer and Lucy Dawidowicz</ENAMEX> maintained that from the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">Middle Ages</ENAMEX> onward, <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> society and culture were suffused with <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">antisemitism</ENAMEX>, and that there was a direct ideological link from <ENAMEX type="EVENT">medieval pogroms</ENAMEX> such as the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Rhineland Massacres</ENAMEX> to the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">Nazi</ENAMEX> death camps.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E76">[40] The <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">second half of the 19th century</ENAMEX> saw the emergence in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany and Austria - Hungary</ENAMEX> of the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Völkisch movement</ENAMEX> developed by such thinkers as <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Houston Stewart Chamberlain and Paul de Lagarde</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E77">The movement presented a pseudo - scientific, biologically based racism that viewed <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> as a race locked in mortal combat with the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Aryan</ENAMEX> race for world domination.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E78">[41] <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Völkisch antisemitism</ENAMEX> drew upon stereotypes from <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Christian antisemitism</ENAMEX> but differed in that <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> were considered to be a race rather than a religion.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E79">[42] <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Friedrich Nietzsche</ENAMEX>, an opponent of <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">antisemitism and nationalism</ENAMEX>, wrote in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1886</ENAMEX>: The whole problem of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> exists only in nation states, for here their energy and higher intelligence, their accumulated capital of spirit and will, gathered from generation to generation through a long schooling in suffering, must become so preponderant as to arouse mass envy and hatred.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E80">In almost all contemporary nations, therefore—in direct proportion to the degree to which they act up nationalistically—the literal obscenity of leading the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> to slaughter as scapegoats for every conceivable public and internal misfortune is spreading.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E81"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Friedrich Nietzsche</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1886</ENAMEX> In a speech before the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Reichstag in 1895</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">völkisch leader Hermann Ahlwardt</ENAMEX> called <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX>" predators" and" cholera bacilli" who should be" exterminated" for the good of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">German</ENAMEX> people.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E82">[44] In his best - selling <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1912</ENAMEX> book <ENAMEX type="CREATION">Wenn ich der Kaiser wär</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX type="CREATION">If I were the Kaiser</ENAMEX>), <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Heinrich Class, leader of the völkisch group Alldeutscher Verband</ENAMEX>, urged that all <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">German Jews</ENAMEX> be stripped of their <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> citizenship and be reduced to Fremdenrecht (alien status).</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E83">[45] Class also urged that <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> should be excluded from all aspects of <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> life, forbidden to own land, hold public office, or participate in journalism, banking, and the liberal professions.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E84">[45] Class defined a <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jew</ENAMEX> as anyone who was a member of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> religion on the day the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">German Empire</ENAMEX> was proclaimed in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1871</ENAMEX> or anyone with at least <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">one</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> grandparent.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E85">[45] The <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">first</ENAMEX> medical experimentation on humans and ethnic cleansing by <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Germans</ENAMEX> took place in the death camps of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">German South - West Africa</ENAMEX> during the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Herero and Namaqua Genocide</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E86">It has been suggested that this was an inspiration for the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Holocaust</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E87">[46][47] During the era of the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">German Empire</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">völkisch</ENAMEX> notions and pseudo - <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">scientific racism</ENAMEX> had become commonplace and were accepted throughout <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX>,[48] with the educated professional classes of the country, in particular, adopting an ideology of human inequality.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E88">[49] Though the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">völkisch parties</ENAMEX> were defeated in the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">1912 Reichstag elections</ENAMEX>, being all but wiped out, <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">antisemitism</ENAMEX> was incorporated into the platforms of the mainstream political parties.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E89">[48] The <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">National Socialist German Workers ' Party</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Nazi Party</ENAMEX>; <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">NSDAP</ENAMEX>) was founded in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1920</ENAMEX> as an offshoot of the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">völkisch movement</ENAMEX> and adopted their <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">antisemitism</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E90">[50] In a <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1986</ENAMEX> essay, <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> historian <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Hans Mommsen</ENAMEX> wrote about the situation in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">post</ENAMEX> – <ENAMEX type="EVENT">First World War</ENAMEX><ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> that: If <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">one</ENAMEX> emphasizes the indisputably important connection in isolation, one should not then force a connection with<!--Continue here--> <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Hitler</ENAMEX> ' s <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">weltanschauung</ENAMEX>[worldview], which was in no ways original itself, in order to derive from it the existence of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Auschwitz</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E91">[.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E92">.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E93">.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E94">] Thoughts about the extermination of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> had long been current, and not only for <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Hitler</ENAMEX> and his satraps.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E95">Many of these found their way to the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">NSDAP</ENAMEX> from the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Deutschvölkisch Schutz - und Trutzbund</ENAMEX>[<ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">German Racial Union for Protection and Defiance</ENAMEX>], which itself had been called into life by the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Pan - German Union</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E96">[51] Tremendous scientific and technological changes in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX>during the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">late 19th and early 20th centuries</ENAMEX> together with the growth of the welfare state created widespread hopes that utopia was at hand and that soon all social problems could be solved.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E97">[52] At the same time a racist, <ENAMEX type="CONCEPTUAL">social Darwinist, and eugenicist</ENAMEX> world - view which declared some people to be more biologically valuable than others was common.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E98">[53] Historian <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Detlev Peukert</ENAMEX> states that the <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Shoah</ENAMEX> did not result solely from antisemitism, but was a product of the" cumulative radicalization" in which" numerous smaller currents" fed into the" broad current" that led to genocide.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E99">[54] After the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">First World War</ENAMEX>, the pre - war mood of optimism gave way to disillusionment as <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> bureaucrats found social problems to be more insoluble than previously thought, which in turn led them to place increasing emphasis on saving the biologically" fit" while the biologically" unfit" were to be written off.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E100">[55] Antisemitism in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX>: on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1 April 1933</ENAMEX><ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">SA</ENAMEX> troopers urge a national boycott of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> businesses.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E101">Here they are outside <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Israel</ENAMEX> ' s Department Store in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Berlin</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E102">The signs read:" <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Germans</ENAMEX> ! Defend yourselves ! Don ' t buy from <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E103">"(" <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Deutsche</ENAMEX>! Wehrt Euch ! Kauft nicht bei <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Juden</ENAMEX> !")[56] The store was later ransacked during <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Kristallnacht in 1938</ENAMEX>, then handed over to a non - <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> family.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E104">The political situation in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> and elsewhere in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX> after <ENAMEX type="EVENT">World War I</ENAMEX> also contributed to virulent <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">antisemitism</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E105">Many <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Germans</ENAMEX> did not accept that their country had been defeated in battle, giving rise to the Stab - in - the - back myth.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E106">The myth insinuated that it was disloyal politicians, chiefly <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Communists</ENAMEX>, who orchestrated <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> ' s surrender.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E107">Inflaming the anti - <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> sentiment espoused by the myth was the apparent overrepresentation of ethnic <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> in the leadership of <ENAMEX type="CONCEPTUAL">Communist</ENAMEX> revolutionary governments in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX>, among them <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">Russian Bolshevik leader Vladimir Lenin</ENAMEX>, and in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> itself <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Ernst Toller</ENAMEX> as head of a short lived revolutionary government in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Bavaria</ENAMEX>, contributing to the canard of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish olshevism</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E108">[57] The economic strains of the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Great Depression</ENAMEX> led many in the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> medical establishment to advocate the idea of euthanisation of the" incurable" mentally and physically disabled as a cost - saving measure to free up money to care for the curable.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E109">[58] By the time the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazis</ENAMEX> came to power in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1933</ENAMEX>, a tendency already existed in the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> social policy to save the racially" valuable" while seeking to rid society of the racially" undesirable".</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E110">[59] Although <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Hitler</ENAMEX> never wrote that he would exterminate the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX>, he was open about his hatred of them.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E111">Although the origin and first expression of <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Hitler</ENAMEX> ' s <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">anti-Semitism</ENAMEX> remain a matter of debate.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E112">[60] Hitler states in <ENAMEX type="CREATION">Mein Kampf</ENAMEX> that he first became an <ENAMEX type="CONCEPTUAL">anti-Semite</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Vienna</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E113">[61] In <ENAMEX type="CREATION">Mein Kampf</ENAMEX>, he announced his intention of removing them from <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> ' s political, intellectual, and cultural life.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E114">From the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">early 1920s</ENAMEX><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Hitler</ENAMEX> linked the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> with bacteria and that they should be dealt with in exactly the same way; in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">August 1920</ENAMEX> he said that resolving" racial tuberculosis" would be solved by the removal of the" causal agent, the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jew</ENAMEX>".</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E115">[62] In <ENAMEX type="CREATION">Mein Kampf</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Hitler</ENAMEX> wrote:" The nationalization of our masses will succeed only when, aside from all the positive struggle for the soul of our people, their international poisoners are exterminated.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E116">"[62] <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Hitler</ENAMEX> with the idea of poisoning the poisoners suggested:" If at the beginning of the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">War</ENAMEX> and during the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">War</ENAMEX><ENAMEX type="MEASURE">twelve or fifteen thousand</ENAMEX> of these <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Hebrew</ENAMEX> corrupters of the people had been held under poison gas, as happened to <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">hundreds of thousands</ENAMEX> of our very best <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> workers in the field, the sacrifice of millions at the front would not have been in vain".</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E117">[62] <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Hitler</ENAMEX> had by now viewed <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Marxism</ENAMEX> as a <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> doctrine and proclaimed he was fighting against" <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX><ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Marxism</ENAMEX>".</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E118">[63] During his time writing <ENAMEX type="CREATION">Mein Kampf</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Hitler</ENAMEX> reflected on the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish Question</ENAMEX> and concluded that he had been too soft and in the future only the most severe measures were to be taken if there was any chance of solving it.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E119"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Hitler</ENAMEX> believed the <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Jewish Question</ENAMEX> was not only a problem for the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">German</ENAMEX> people but for all peoples as" <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Juda</ENAMEX> is the world plague".</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E120">[64] <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Ian Kershaw</ENAMEX> writes that some passages in <ENAMEX type="CREATION">Mein Kampf</ENAMEX> are undeniably of an inherently genocidal nature.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E121">[62] In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1922</ENAMEX>, he allegedly told <ENAMEX type="TITLE">Major Joseph Hell</ENAMEX>, at the time a journalist: Once I really am in power, my <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">first</ENAMEX> and foremost task will be the annihilation of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E122">As soon as I have the power to do so, I will have gallows built in rows—at the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Marienplatz in Munich</ENAMEX>, for example—as many as traffic allows.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E123">Then the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> will be hanged indiscriminately, and they will remain hanging until they stink; they will hang there as long as the principles of hygiene permit.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E124">As soon as they have been untied, the next batch will be strung up, and so on down the line, until the last <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jew</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Munich</ENAMEX> has been exterminated.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E125">Other cities will follow suit, precisely in this fashion, until all <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> has been completely cleansed of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E126">[65] As early as <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1933</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Julius Streicher</ENAMEX> was calling for the extermination of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> in the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazi</ENAMEX> newspaper <ENAMEX type="MEDIA">Der Stürmer</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E127">[66] During the war, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Streicher</ENAMEX> regularly authorized articles demanding the annihilation of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> race.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E128">[67] <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Mommsen</ENAMEX> suggested there were <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">three</ENAMEX> types of <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">antisemitism</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX>: 1) the cultural <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">antisemitism</ENAMEX> found among <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">German conservatives</ENAMEX>, especially in the military officer corps as well as in the top members of the civil administration; 2) the" <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">volkisch</ENAMEX>" <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">antisemitism or racism</ENAMEX> which advocated using violence against the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX>; and 3) the religious anti - <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Judaism</ENAMEX>, particularly within the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Catholic Church</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E129">The cultural <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">antisemitism</ENAMEX> kept the ruling establishment from distancing itself or opposing the violent, racial <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">antisemitism</ENAMEX> of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazis</ENAMEX>, and religious <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">antisemitism</ENAMEX> meant that the religious establishment did not present opposition to racial persecution of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</paragraph>
		</document>
	</subcorpus>
</corpus>
