<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<corpus>
	<subcorpus>
		<document name="EHRI_unit_lt-002880-f_r_1099.en.2layers.xml">
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P0">
				<sentence xml:id="P0E0">Circulars and decrees of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazis</ENAMEX> authorities and the <ENAMEX type="TITLE">chiefs</ENAMEX> of the local municipalities, decrees, protocols of inquiries of local residents, documents concerning <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> property, information about obligatory works for the locals, information about typhus in the district; lists (with many <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> names) of: the <ENAMEX type="TITLE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">staff</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">chiefs</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">mayors</ENAMEX> and their <ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">assistants</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, men who were born in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1919-1924</ENAMEX>, war prisoners, war refugees from <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Russia</ENAMEX>, people repatriated from <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Suvalkų</ENAMEX> area and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Pakruojis</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> local rural district, local residents who have war prisoners as workers; correspondence about administration management; applications from residents concerning various matters; police precincts&apos; documentation about staff, salaries, etc.; instructions for the auxiliary police, correspondence about foreign passports, applications from residents to obtain foreign passports, documentation about registration of living places, etc.</sentence>
			</p>
		</document>
	</subcorpus>
</corpus>
