<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<corpus>
	<subcorpus>
		<document name="Wikipedia_brexit.2layers.xml">
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P0">
				<sentence xml:id="P0E0"><ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX> is the forthcoming withdrawal of the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">United Kingdom</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>)</ENAMEX> from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">EU</ENAMEX>)</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E1">In the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">June 2016 referendum</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">52%</ENAMEX> voted to leave the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, leading into a complex separation process implying political and economic changes for the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> and other countries.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E2">The timetable for withdrawal has not yet been firmly established.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P1">
				<sentence xml:id="P1E0">Withdrawal from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX> has been a right under <ENAMEX type="LEGAL"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LEGAL">Article 50 of the Treaty On European Union</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> member states</ENAMEX>  <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">since 2007</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P1E1">The details of the process for the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>&apos;s withdrawal are uncertain under <ENAMEX type="LEGAL"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">UE</ENAMEX> law – <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LEGAL">Article 50</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, which now governs the withdrawal, has never been used before.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P1E2">Unless extensions are agreed, the timing for leaving under the article is <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">two years</ENAMEX> from when <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> gives official notice, but this official notice was not given immediately following the referendum in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">June 2016</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P1E3">The assumption is that during the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">two-year</ENAMEX> window new agreements will be negotiated, but there is no requirement that there be new agreements.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P2">
				<sentence xml:id="P2E0">Withdrawal has been the goal of various individuals, advocacy groups, and political parties since the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> joined the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">European Economic Community</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">EEC</ENAMEX>)</ENAMEX>, the predecessor of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1973</ENAMEX>, though continued membership of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EEC</ENAMEX> was approved in a <ENAMEX type="EVENT">1975 referendum</ENAMEX> by <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">67%</ENAMEX> of voters.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P3">
				<sentence xml:id="P3E0">Background</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P4">
				<sentence xml:id="P4E0">The <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> was not a signatory to the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Treaty of Rome</ENAMEX> which created the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EEC</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1957</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P4E1">The country subsequently applied to join the organisation in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1963</ENAMEX> and again in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1967</ENAMEX>, but both applications were vetoed by the <ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">President of France</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Charles de Gaulle</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, ostensibly because &quot;a number of aspects of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX>&apos;s economy, from working practices to agriculture&quot; had &quot;made <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> incompatible with <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX>&quot; and that <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> harboured a &quot;deep-seated hostility&quot; to any pan-<ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">European</ENAMEX> project.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P5">
				<sentence xml:id="P5E0">Once <ENAMEX type="PERSON">de Gaulle</ENAMEX> had relinquished the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">French</ENAMEX> presidency, the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> made a <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">third</ENAMEX> application for membership, which was successful.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P5E1">Under the <ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Conservative</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">Prime Minister Edward Heath</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">European Communities Act 1972</ENAMEX> was enacted.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P5E2">On <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1 January 1973</ENAMEX> the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">United Kingdom</ENAMEX> joined the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">EEC</ENAMEX>, or &quot;Common Market</ENAMEX>&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P5E3">The opposition <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Labour Party</ENAMEX>, led by <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Harold Wilson</ENAMEX>, contested the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">October 1974 general election</ENAMEX> with a commitment to renegotiate <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX>&apos;s terms of membership of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EEC</ENAMEX> and then hold a referendum on whether to remain in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EEC</ENAMEX> on the new terms.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P6">
				<sentence xml:id="P6E0"><ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">1975</ENAMEX> referendum</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P7">
				<sentence xml:id="P7E0">Main article: <ENAMEX type="EVENT">United Kingdom <ENAMEX subType="2" type="NATIONAL">European</ENAMEX> Communities membership referendum, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">1975</ENAMEX></ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P8">
				<sentence xml:id="P8E0">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1975</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">United Kingdom</ENAMEX> held a referendum on whether the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> should remain in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EEC</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P8E1">All of the major political parties and mainstream press supported continuing membership of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EEC</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P8E2">However, there were significant splits within the ruling <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Labour party</ENAMEX>, the membership of which had voted <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">2:1</ENAMEX> in favour of withdrawal at a <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">one-day</ENAMEX> party conference on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">26 April 1975</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P8E3">Since the cabinet was split between strongly pro-<ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">European</ENAMEX> and strongly anti-<ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">European</ENAMEX> ministers, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Harold Wilson</ENAMEX> suspended the constitutional convention of <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Cabinet collective responsibility</ENAMEX> and allowed ministers to publicly campaign on either side.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P8E4"><ENAMEX type="MEASURE">Seven of the twenty-three</ENAMEX> members of the cabinet opposed <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EEC</ENAMEX> membership.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P9">
				<sentence xml:id="P9E0">On <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">5 June 1975</ENAMEX>, the electorate were asked to vote yes or no on the question: &quot;Do you think the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> should stay in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="NATIONAL">European</ENAMEX> Community (Common Market)</ENAMEX>?&quot;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P9E1">Every administrative county in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> had a majority of &quot;Yes&quot;, except the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Shetland Islands</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Outer Hebrides</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P9E2">In line with the outcome of the vote, <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">67%</ENAMEX> in favour of staying in, the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">United Kingdom</ENAMEX> remained a member of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EEC</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P10">
				<sentence xml:id="P10E0"><ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">United Kingdom European Community</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">Common Market</ENAMEX>) <ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Membership Referendum 1975</ENAMEX></ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P17">
				<sentence xml:id="P17E0">Between referendums</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P18">
				<sentence xml:id="P18E0">The opposition <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Labour Party</ENAMEX> campaigned in the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">1983 general election</ENAMEX> on a commitment to withdraw from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EEC</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P18E1">It was heavily defeated as the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Conservative</ENAMEX> government of <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Margaret Thatcher</ENAMEX> was re-elected.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P18E2">The <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Labour Party</ENAMEX> subsequently changed its policy.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P19">
				<sentence xml:id="P19E0">As a result of the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Maastricht Treaty</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EEC</ENAMEX> became the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX> on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1 November 1993</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P19E1">The new name reflected the evolution of the organisation from an economic union into a political union.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P20">
				<sentence xml:id="P20E0">The <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Referendum Party</ENAMEX> was formed in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1994</ENAMEX> by <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Sir James Goldsmith</ENAMEX><!--check Sir as title --> to contest the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">1997 general election</ENAMEX> on a platform of providing a referendum on the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>&apos;s membership of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P20E1">It fielded candidates in <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">547</ENAMEX> constituencies at that election and won <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">810,860</ENAMEX> votes, <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">2.6%</ENAMEX> of total votes cast.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P20E2">It failed to win a single parliamentary seat as its vote was spread out, losing its deposit (funded by <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Goldsmith</ENAMEX>) in <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">505</ENAMEX> constituencies.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P21">
				<sentence xml:id="P21E0">The <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">UK Independence Party</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">UKIP</ENAMEX>)</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX type="CONCEPTUAL">Eurosceptic</ENAMEX> political party, was also formed in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1993</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P21E1">It achieved <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">third</ENAMEX> place in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> during the <ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">2004</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="NATIONAL">European</ENAMEX> elections</ENAMEX> , <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">second</ENAMEX> place in the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">2009 European elections</ENAMEX>  and <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">first</ENAMEX> place in the <ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">2014</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="NATIONAL">European</ENAMEX> elections</ENAMEX>, with <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">27.5%</ENAMEX> of the total vote.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P21E2">This was the <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">first</ENAMEX> time since the <ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">1910</ENAMEX> general election</ENAMEX> that any party other than the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">Labour</ENAMEX> or <ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">Conservative</ENAMEX> parties</ENAMEX> had taken the largest share of the vote in a nationwide election.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P22">
				<sentence xml:id="P22E0">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2014</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">UKIP</ENAMEX> won <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">two</ENAMEX> by-elections, triggered when the sitting <ENAMEX type="TITLE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">Conservative</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">MPs</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> defected to <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">UKIP</ENAMEX> and then resigned.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P22E1">These were their <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">first</ENAMEX> elected <ENAMEX type="TITLE">MPs</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P22E2">At the <ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">2015</ENAMEX> general election</ENAMEX>  <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">UKIP</ENAMEX> took <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">12.6%</ENAMEX> of the total vote and held <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">one of the two</ENAMEX> seats won in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2014</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P23">
				<sentence xml:id="P23E0">The term &quot;<ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX>&quot;</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P24">
				<sentence xml:id="P24E0"><ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX> (and its early variant, <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX>), is a portmanteau of &quot;<ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX>&quot; and &quot;exit&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P24E1">It was derived by analogy from <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Grexit</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P24E2">The term <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX> may have first been used in reference to a possible <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> withdrawal from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> by <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Peter Wilding</ENAMEX> in a <ENAMEX type="MEDIA">Euractiv</ENAMEX> blog post on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">15 May 2012</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P25">
				<sentence xml:id="P25E0"><ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">2016</ENAMEX> referendum</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P26">
				<sentence xml:id="P26E0">Main article: <ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">United Kingdom</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX> membership referendum, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">2016</ENAMEX></ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P27">
				<sentence xml:id="P27E0">See also: Aftermath of the <ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">United Kingdom</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX> membership referendum, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">2016</ENAMEX></ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P28">
				<sentence xml:id="P28E0">	This section should include only a brief summary of <ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">United Kingdom</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX> membership referendum, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">2016</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P28E1">See <ENAMEX type="WEBSITE">Wikipedia</ENAMEX>:Summary style for information on how to properly incorporate it into this article&apos;s main text.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P29">
				<sentence xml:id="P29E0">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2012</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">Prime Minister</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">David Cameron</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> rejected calls for a referendum on the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>&apos;s <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> membership, but suggested the possibility of a future referendum to gauge public support.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P29E1">According to the <ENAMEX type="MEDIA">BBC</ENAMEX>, &quot;The <ENAMEX type="TITLE">prime minister</ENAMEX> acknowledged the need to ensure the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>&apos;s position within the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX> had &apos;the full-hearted support of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">British</ENAMEX> people&apos; but they needed to show &apos;tactical and strategic patience&apos;.&quot;</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P30">
				<sentence xml:id="P30E0">Under pressure from many of his <ENAMEX type="TITLE">MPs</ENAMEX> and from the rise of <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">UKIP</ENAMEX>, in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">January 2013</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Cameron</ENAMEX> announced that a <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Conservative</ENAMEX> government would hold an in–out referendum on <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> membership  <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">before the end of <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">2017</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, on a renegotiated package, if elected in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2015</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P31">
				<sentence xml:id="P31E0">The <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Conservative Party</ENAMEX> unexpectedly won the <ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">2015</ENAMEX> general election</ENAMEX> with a majority.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P31E1">Soon afterwards the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">European Union Referendum Act 2015</ENAMEX> was introduced into <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Parliament</ENAMEX> to enable the referendum.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P31E2">Despite being in favour of remaining in a reformed <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX> himself, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Cameron</ENAMEX> announced that <ENAMEX type="TITLE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">Conservative Ministers</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">MPs</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> were free to campaign in favour of remaining in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> or leaving it, according to their conscience.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P31E3">This decision came after mounting pressure for a free vote for ministers.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P31E4">In an exception to the usual rule of <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">cabinet collective responsibility</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Cameron</ENAMEX> allowed <ENAMEX type="TITLE">cabinet ministers</ENAMEX> to campaign publicly for <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> withdrawal.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P32">
				<sentence xml:id="P32E0">In a speech to the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">House of Commons</ENAMEX> on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">22 February 2016</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Cameron</ENAMEX> announced a referendum date of <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">23 June 2016</ENAMEX> and set out the legal framework for withdrawal from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX> in circumstances where there was a referendum majority vote to leave, citing <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Article <ENAMEX subType="2" type="MEASURE">50</ENAMEX> of the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="CONCEPT">Lisbon Treaty</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P32E1"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Cameron</ENAMEX> spoke of an intention to trigger the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="CONCEPT">Article 50</ENAMEX> process</ENAMEX> immediately following a leave vote and of the &quot;<ENAMEX type="PERIOD">two-year</ENAMEX> time period to negotiate the arrangements for exit.&quot;</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P33">
				<sentence xml:id="P33E0">Campaign groups</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P34">
				<sentence xml:id="P34E0">Main article: Campaigning in the <ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">United Kingdom</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX> membership referendum, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">2016</ENAMEX></ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P35">
				<sentence xml:id="P35E0">The official campaign group for leaving the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> was <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Vote Leave</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P35E1">Other major campaign groups included <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Leave</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P35E2"><ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Grassroots Out, and Better Off Out</ENAMEX>, while no-<ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> affiliated organisations also campaigned for the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">United Kingdom</ENAMEX>&apos;s withdrawal, such as the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Commonwealth Freedom of Movement Organisation</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P36">
				<sentence xml:id="P36E0">The official campaign to stay in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, chaired by <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Stuart Rose</ENAMEX>, was known as <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Britain Stronger in Europe</ENAMEX>, or informally as <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Remain</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P36E1">Other campaigns supporting remaining in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> included <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">Conservatives In</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">Labour in for Britain</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">#INtogether</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">Liberal Democrats</ENAMEX>), <ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">Greens for a Better Europe</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">Scientists for EU</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">Environmentalists For Europe</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">Universities for Europe</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">Another is Possible</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P37">
				<sentence xml:id="P37E0">Voting result</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P38">
				<sentence xml:id="P38E0">Main article: Results of the <ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">United Kingdom European Union</ENAMEX> membership referendum, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">2016</ENAMEX></ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P39">
				<sentence xml:id="P39E0">The result was announced on the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">morning of <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">24 June</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>: <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">52%</ENAMEX> voted in favour of leaving the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">48%</ENAMEX> voted in favour of remaining a member of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P40">
				<sentence xml:id="P40E0"><ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">United Kingdom</ENAMEX> European Union</ENAMEX> membership referendum, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">2016</ENAMEX></ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P53">
				<sentence xml:id="P53E0">Results by region (left) and by local council district (right)</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P54">
				<sentence xml:id="P54E0">Leave</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P55">
				<sentence xml:id="P55E0">Remain</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P56">
				<sentence xml:id="P56E0">Political effects</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P57">
				<sentence xml:id="P57E0">The political scene in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> went through substantial change and shock after the referendum.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P57E1">After the result was declared, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Cameron</ENAMEX> announced that he would resign by <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">October</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P57E2">In the event, he stood down on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">13 July</ENAMEX>, with <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Theresa May</ENAMEX> becoming <ENAMEX type="TITLE">Prime Minister</ENAMEX>.  <ENAMEX type="PERSON">George Osborne</ENAMEX> was replaced as <ENAMEX type="TITLE">Chancellor of the Exchequer</ENAMEX> by <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Philip Hammond</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Boris Johnson</ENAMEX> was appointed <ENAMEX type="TITLE">Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX type="PERSON">David Davis</ENAMEX> became <ENAMEX type="TITLE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">Secretary of State</ENAMEX> for Exiting the European Union</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P57E3"><ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Labour</ENAMEX> leader <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Jeremy Corbyn</ENAMEX> lost a vote of confidence among his parliamentary party and a leadership challenge was launched, while on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">4 July</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Nigel Farage</ENAMEX> announced his resignation as <ENAMEX type="TITLE">head of <ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">UKIP</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P58">
				<sentence xml:id="P58E0">Outside the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> many <ENAMEX type="CONCEPTUAL">Eurosceptic</ENAMEX> leaders celebrated and expected others to follow the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> example.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P58E1">However, opinion polls <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">a week after the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> vote showed strongly increased support for the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> in most of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P58E2">The right-wing <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">Dutch</ENAMEX> populist <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Geert Wilders</ENAMEX> said that the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Netherlands</ENAMEX> should follow <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX>&apos;s example and hold a referendum on whether the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Netherlands</ENAMEX> should stay in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P58E3">However, opinion polls in the fortnight following the <ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="NATIONAL">British</ENAMEX> referendum</ENAMEX> show that the immediate reaction in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Netherlands</ENAMEX> and other <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">European</ENAMEX> countries was a decline in support for <ENAMEX type="CONCEPTUAL">Eurosceptic</ENAMEX> movements.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P59">
				<sentence xml:id="P59E0">Petitions for a new referendum</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P60">
				<sentence xml:id="P60E0">Within hours of the result&apos;s announcement, a petition calling for a <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">second</ENAMEX> referendum to be held in the event that a result was secured with <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">less than <ENAMEX subType="2" type="MEASURE">60%</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> of the vote and on a turnout of <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">less than <ENAMEX subType="2" type="MEASURE">75%</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> attracted <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">tens of thousands</ENAMEX> of signatures.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P60E1">The petition had actually been started before the referendum by someone favouring an exit from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P60E2">It attracted <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">more than <ENAMEX subType="2" type="MEASURE">four million</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> signatures, meaning it was considered for debate in <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Parliament</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P61">
				<sentence xml:id="P61E0">On <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">27 June 2016</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">David Cameron</ENAMEX>&apos;s spokesperson stated that holding another vote on <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX>&apos;s membership to the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX> was &quot;not remotely on the cards.&quot;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P61E1"><ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">Home Secretary</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Theresa May</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> made the following comment when announcing her candidacy to replace <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Cameron</ENAMEX> as <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Conservative</ENAMEX> leader (and hence as <ENAMEX type="TITLE">Prime Minister</ENAMEX>) on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">30 June</ENAMEX>: &quot;The campaign was fought ...</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P61E2">and the public gave their verdict.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P61E3">There must be no attempts to remain inside the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> ...</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P61E4">and no second referendum.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P61E5">...</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P61E6"><ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX> means <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX>.&quot;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P61E7">The petition was rejected by the government on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">9 July</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P61E8">Its response said that the referendum vote &quot;must be respected&quot; and that the government &quot;must now prepare for the process to exit the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P61E9">The <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Commons Petitions Committee</ENAMEX> has scheduled a debate on the petition for <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">5 September 2016</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P62">
				<sentence xml:id="P62E0">&quot;<ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Article 50</ENAMEX>&quot; and the procedure for leaving the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P63">
				<sentence xml:id="P63E0">Main article: <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> Invocation of <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Article 50</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P64">
				<sentence xml:id="P64E0"><ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Article 50 of the Treaty on European Union</ENAMEX> provides an invocation procedure whereby a member can notify the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Council</ENAMEX> and there is a <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">two year</ENAMEX> negotiation period after which the treaties cease to apply - although a leaving agreement may be agreed by Qualified majority voting.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P65">
				<sentence xml:id="P65E0">As was the case with the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Scottish independence referendum</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">two years earlier</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">2016 referendum</ENAMEX> did not directly require the government to do anything in particular.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P65E1">It does not require the government to initiate, or even schedule, the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Article  50</ENAMEX> procedure. Although <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Cameron</ENAMEX> stated during the campaign that he would invoke <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Article  50</ENAMEX> straight away in the event of a leave victory, he refused to allow the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Civil Service</ENAMEX> to make any contingency plans, something the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Foreign Affairs Select Committee</ENAMEX> later described as &quot;an act of gross negligence.&quot;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P65E2">Following the referendum result <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Cameron</ENAMEX> announced that he would resign before the <ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">Conservative party</ENAMEX> conference in <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">October</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, and that it would be for the incoming <ENAMEX type="TITLE">Prime Minister</ENAMEX> to invoke <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Article <ENAMEX subType="2" type="MEASURE">50</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P66">
				<sentence xml:id="P66E0"> A negotiation with the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX> will need to begin under a new <ENAMEX type="TITLE">Prime Minister</ENAMEX>, and I think it is right that this new <ENAMEX type="TITLE">Prime Minister</ENAMEX> takes the decision about when to trigger <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Article 50</ENAMEX> and start the formal and legal process of leaving the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P67">
				<sentence xml:id="P67E0"> —<ENAMEX type="PERSON">David Cameron</ENAMEX>, &quot;<ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> referendum</ENAMEX> outcome: <ENAMEX type="TITLE">PM</ENAMEX> statement, <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">24 June 2016</ENAMEX>&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P67E1">gov.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P67E2"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION">uk</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P67E3">Retrieved <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">25 June 2016</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P68">
				<sentence xml:id="P68E0">There is no established, formal process for holding a <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">second</ENAMEX> referendum to &quot;confirm&quot; the decision to leave following negotiations.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P68E1"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Alan Renwick</ENAMEX> of the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Constitution Unit of <ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">University College London</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> argues that <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Article <ENAMEX subType="2" type="MEASURE">50</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> negotiations cannot be used to renegotiate the conditions of future membership and that <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Article <ENAMEX subType="2" type="MEASURE">50</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> does not provide the legal basis of withdrawing a decision to leave.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P68E2">The <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="NATIONAL">UK</ENAMEX> government</ENAMEX> has stated that they would expect a leave vote to be followed by withdrawal, not by a second vote.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P69">
				<sentence xml:id="P69E0">As long as the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">UK Government</ENAMEX> has not invoked <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Article  50</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> stays a member of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>; must continue to fulfil all <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>-related treaties, including possible future agreements; and should legally be treated as a member.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P69E1">The <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> has no framework to exclude the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>—or any member—as long as <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Article 50</ENAMEX> is not invoked, and the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> does not violate <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> laws.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P69E2">However, if the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> were to breach <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> law significantly, there are legal provisions to discharge the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> via <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Article 7</ENAMEX>, the so-called &quot;nuclear option&quot;, which allows the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> to cancel membership of a state that breaches fundamental <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> principles, a test that will be hard to pass.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P69E3"><ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Article 7</ENAMEX> does not allow forced cancellation of membership, only denial of rights such as free trade, free movement and voting rights.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P70">
				<sentence xml:id="P70E0">Various <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> leaders have said that they will not start any negotiation before the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> formally invokes <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Article 50</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P70E1"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Jean-Claude Juncker</ENAMEX> even ordered all members of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> Commision</ENAMEX> not to engage in any kind of contact with <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> parties regarding <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P70E2">Media statements of various kinds still occur.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P70E3">For example, on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">29 June</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">European Council president</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Donald Tusk</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> told the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> that they would not be allowed access to the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="NATIONAL">European</ENAMEX> Single Market</ENAMEX> unless they accept its <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">four</ENAMEX> freedoms of goods, capital, services, and people.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P70E4"><ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> Chancellor <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Angela Merkel</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> said &quot;<ENAMEX subType="2" type="CREATION">We&apos;ll ensure</ENAMEX> that negotiations don&apos;t take place according to the principle of cherry-picking ...</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P70E5">It must and will make a noticeable difference whether a country wants to be a member of the family of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX> or not.&quot;</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P71">
				<sentence xml:id="P71E0">Immediately afterwards, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Cameron</ENAMEX> declared his belief that the next <ENAMEX type="TITLE">Prime Minister</ENAMEX> should activate <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Article 50</ENAMEX> and begin negotiations with the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P71E1">During a <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">27 June 2016</ENAMEX> meeting, the Cabinet decided to establish a unit of civil servants, headed by <ENAMEX type="PERSON">senior <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Conservative</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Oliver Letwin</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, who would proceed with &quot;intensive work on the issues that will need to be worked through in order to present options and advice to a new <ENAMEX type="TITLE">Prime Minister</ENAMEX> and a new Cabinet&quot;.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P72">
				<sentence xml:id="P72E0">After a debate about the planned <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> exit on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">28 June 2016</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> Parliament</ENAMEX> passed a motion calling for the &quot;immediate&quot; triggering of <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Article 50</ENAMEX>, although there is no mechanism allowing the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> to invoke the article.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P73">
				<sentence xml:id="P73E0">Newly appointed <ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">PM</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Theresa May</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> made it clear that negotiations with the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> required a &quot;<ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>-wide approach&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P73E1">Speaking in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Scotland</ENAMEX> on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">15 July 2016</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">May</ENAMEX> offered the following comment.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P73E2">&quot;I have already said that I won&apos;t be triggering <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">articl50</ENAMEX> until I think that we have a <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> approach and objectives for negotiations – I think it is important that we establish that before we trigger <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">article 50</ENAMEX>.&quot;</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P74">
				<sentence xml:id="P74E0">Possible need for parliamentary approval before invoking <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Article 50</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P75">
				<sentence xml:id="P75E0">Lawyers disagree on whether the <ENAMEX type="TITLE">prime minister</ENAMEX> can invoke <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Article 50</ENAMEX> by royal prerogative, or whether there needs to be an explicit <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Act of Parliament</ENAMEX> to invoke it.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P76">
				<sentence xml:id="P76E0"><ENAMEX type="MEASURE">Three</ENAMEX> distinct groups of lawyers – <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">one</ENAMEX> funded by crowd sourcing – are suing the government or planning to sue it to make sure <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Article 50</ENAMEX> is not invoked without a parliamentary act.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P77">
				<sentence xml:id="P77E0"><ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Scottish Parliament</ENAMEX> objection</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P78">
				<sentence xml:id="P78E0">The <ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">First Minister of Scotland</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Nicola Sturgeon</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, stated that <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Scotland</ENAMEX> might refuse consent for legislation required to leave the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, though some lawyers argue that <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Scotland</ENAMEX> cannot block <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P79">
				<sentence xml:id="P79E0"><ENAMEX type="PERIOD">Two days</ENAMEX> after her appointment as <ENAMEX type="TITLE">PM</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Theresa May</ENAMEX> travelled to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Edinburgh</ENAMEX> to meet with <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Sturgeon</ENAMEX>, to reinforce the bond between <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Scotland</ENAMEX> and the rest of the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P79E1">After the meeting at <ENAMEX type="INSTALLATION">Bute House</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">May</ENAMEX> offered the following comment about <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Scotland</ENAMEX>&apos;s role in the negotiations about the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>&apos;s exit from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>: &quot;I&apos;m willing to listen to options and I&apos;ve been very clear with the <ENAMEX type="TITLE">first minister</ENAMEX> today that I want the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="NATIONAL">Scottish</ENAMEX> government</ENAMEX> to be fully engaged in our discussion.&quot;</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P80">
				<sentence xml:id="P80E0">Delay in invoking <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Article 50</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P81">
				<sentence xml:id="P81E0">On <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">19 July 2016</ENAMEX>, at a preliminary <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">High Court</ENAMEX> hearing of a challenge to the government&apos;s claim that it could issue the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Article 50</ENAMEX> notification without Parliamentary approval, lawyers for the government confirmed that the <ENAMEX type="TITLE">prime minister</ENAMEX> would not issue any such notification before the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">end of 2016</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P82">
				<sentence xml:id="P82E0"><ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Nicolas J. Firzli</ENAMEX> of the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">World Pensions Council</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">WPC</ENAMEX>)</ENAMEX> has argued that it could be in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX>&apos;s national interest to proceed slowly in the coming months; <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Her <ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">Majesty<!-- check Majesty if title--></ENAMEX>&apos;s Government</ENAMEX> may want to push <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Brussels</ENAMEX> to accept the principles of a free trade deal before invoking <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Article 50</ENAMEX>, hopefully gaining support from some other member states whose economy is strongly tied to the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>, thus &quot;allowing a more nimble union to focus on the free trade of goods and services without undue bureaucratic burdens, modern antitrust law and stronger external borders, leaving the rest to member states&quot;.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P83">
				<sentence xml:id="P83E0"><ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">Prime Minister</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Theresa May</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> made it clear that discussions with the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> would not start in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2016</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P83E1">&quot;I want to work with ...</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P83E2">the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European council</ENAMEX> in a constructive spirit to make this a sensible and orderly departure.&quot;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P83E3">she said.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P83E4">&quot;All of us will need time to prepare for these negotiations and the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">United Kingdom</ENAMEX> will not invoke <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">article 50</ENAMEX> until our objectives are clear.&quot;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P83E5">In a joint press conference with <ENAMEX type="PERSON">May</ENAMEX> on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">20 July</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX>&apos;s Chancellor <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Angela Merkel</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> supported the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>&apos;s position in this respect: &quot;We all have an interest in this matter being carefully prepared, positions being clearly defined and delineated.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P83E6">I think it is absolutely necessary to have a certain time to prepare for that.&quot;</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P84">
				<sentence xml:id="P84E0">Consequences of withdrawal</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P85">
				<sentence xml:id="P85E0">Relationship with remaining <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> members</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P86">
				<sentence xml:id="P86E0">Political system of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P87">
				<sentence xml:id="P87E0">As the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> electorate has voted to leave the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, its subsequent relationship with the remaining <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> members could take several forms.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P87E1">A research paper presented to the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">UK Parliament</ENAMEX> proposed a number of alternatives to membership which would continue to allow access to the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> internal market.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P87E2">These include remaining in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">European Economic Area</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">EEA</ENAMEX>)</ENAMEX> as a <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">European Free Trade Association</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">EFTA</ENAMEX>)</ENAMEX> member (alongside <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Iceland</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Liechtenstein</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Norway</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Switzerland</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>), or seeking to negotiate bilateral terms more along the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">Swiss</ENAMEX> model with a series of interdependent sectoral agreements.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P87E3"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> has not negotiated a trade agreement <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">since before 1973</ENAMEX>, and the government is looking to the private sector for assistance.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P88">
				<sentence xml:id="P88E0">Were the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> to join the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EEA</ENAMEX> as an <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EFTA</ENAMEX> member, it would have to sign up to <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> internal market legislation without being able to participate in its development or vote on its content.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P88E1">However, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> is required to conduct extensive consultations with non-<ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> members beforehand via its many committees and cooperative bodies.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P88E2">Some <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> law originates from various international bodies on which non-<ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EEA</ENAMEX> countries have a seat.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P89">
				<sentence xml:id="P89E0">The <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">EEA Agreement</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">EFTA</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> members except <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Switzerland</ENAMEX>) does not cover <ENAMEX type="LEGAL"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="CREATION">Common Agriculture and Fisheries Policies</ENAMEX>, Customs Union, Common Trade Policy, Common Foreign and Security Policy, direct and indirect taxation, and Police and Judicial Co-operation in Criminal Matters</ENAMEX>, leaving <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EFTA</ENAMEX> members free to set their own policies in these areas; however, <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EFTA</ENAMEX> countries are required to contribute to the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> Budget in exchange for access to the internal market.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P90">
				<sentence xml:id="P90E0">The <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">EEA Agreement</ENAMEX> and the agreement with <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Switzerland</ENAMEX> cover free movement of goods, and free movement of people.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P90E1">Many supporters of <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX> want to restrict freedom of movement; however, an <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">EEA Agreement</ENAMEX> would include free movement for <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">EEA</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> citizens, as passport systems allow <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EEA</ENAMEX> institutions to access markets in <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> Member States, for the most part, without having to establish subsidiaries in each <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> Member State and incur the costs of full authorisation in those jurisdiction.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P90E2">Others[who?]</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P90E3">present ideas of a <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">Swiss</ENAMEX> solution, that is tailor-made agreements between the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, but <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> representatives have claimed they would not support such a solution.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P90E4">The <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">Swiss</ENAMEX> agreements contain free movement for <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> citizens.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P90E5">(The <ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Swiss immigration referendum</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">February 2014</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> voted narrowly in favour of an end to the &apos;free movement&apos; agreement, by <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">February 2017</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P90E6">However, the bilateral treaties between <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Switzerland</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX> are all co-dependent, if one is terminated then all are terminated.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P90E7">Consequently, should <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Switzerland</ENAMEX> choose unilaterally to cancel the &apos;free movement&apos; agreement then all its agreements with the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> will lapse unless a compromise is found – as of <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">July 2016</ENAMEX>, no such compromise was in sight).</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P91">
				<sentence xml:id="P91E0">Relationship between remaining <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> members</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P92">
				<sentence xml:id="P92E0">A report by <ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Tim Oliver</ENAMEX> of the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">German Institute for International and Security Affairs</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> expanded analysis of what a <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">British</ENAMEX> withdrawal could mean for the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>: the report argues a <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> withdrawal &quot;has the potential to fundamentally change the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">European</ENAMEX> integration.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P92E1">On the one hand, a withdrawal could tip the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> towards <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">protectionism</ENAMEX>, exacerbate existing divisions, or unleash centrifugal forces leading to the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>&apos;s unravelling.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P92E2">Alternatively, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> could free itself of its most awkward member, making the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> easier to lead and more effective.&quot;</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P93">
				<sentence xml:id="P93E0">Immigration</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P94">
				<sentence xml:id="P94E0">A <ENAMEX type="TITLE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">Conservative</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">MEP</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> representing <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">South East England</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Daniel Hannan</ENAMEX>, predicted on <ENAMEX type="CREATION">BBC Newsnight</ENAMEX> that immigration from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX> would not end after <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX>: &quot;Frankly, if people watching think that they have voted and there is now going to be zero immigration from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, they are going to be disappointed.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P94E2">you will look in vain for anything that the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Leave campaign</ENAMEX> said at any point that ever suggested there would ever be any kind of border closure or drawing up of the drawbridge.&quot;</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P95">
				<sentence xml:id="P95E0">The <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> had offered <ENAMEX type="PERSON">David Cameron</ENAMEX> a so-called &quot;emergency brake&quot; which would have allowed the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> to withhold social benefits to new immigrants for the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">first four years</ENAMEX> after they arrived; this brake could have been applied for a period of <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">seven years</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P95E1">That offer was still on the table at the time of the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit referendum</ENAMEX> but expired when the vote determined that the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> would leave the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P96">
				<sentence xml:id="P96E0">In late <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">July 2016</ENAMEX>, discussions were underway that might provide the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> with an exemption from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> rules on refugees&apos; freedom of movement for up to <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">seven years</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P96E1">Senior <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">UK government</ENAMEX> sources confirmed to <ENAMEX type="MEDIA">The Observer</ENAMEX> that this was &quot;certainly one of the ideas now on the table&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P96E2">If the discussions led to an agreement, the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> – though not an <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> member – would also retain access to the single market but would be required to pay a significant annual contribution to the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P96E3">According to <ENAMEX type="MEDIA">The Daily Telegraph</ENAMEX> the news of this possibility caused a rift in the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Conservative Party</ENAMEX>: &quot; <ENAMEX type="TITLE">Tory MPs</ENAMEX> have reacted with fury ....</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P96E4">[accusing <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">European</ENAMEX> leaders of] ...</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P96E5">failing to accept the public&apos;s decision to sever ties with the <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">28</ENAMEX>-member bloc last month.&quot;</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P97">
				<sentence xml:id="P97E0">Economic effects</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P98">
				<sentence xml:id="P98E0">Prior to the referendum, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">UK treasury</ENAMEX> estimated that being in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> has a strong positive effect on trade and as a result the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>&apos;s trade would be worse off if it left the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P98E1">The <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">International Monetary Fund</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">IMF</ENAMEX>)</ENAMEX> forecasts reduced world economic growth by <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">0.1%</ENAMEX> following the referendum, and greater reductions in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> economic growth.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P99">
				<sentence xml:id="P99E0">Supporters of withdrawal from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> have argued that the cessation of net contributions to the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> would allow for some cuts to taxes and/or increases in government spending.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P99E1">However, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> would still be required to make contributions to the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> budget if it opted to remain in the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">European Free Trade</ENAMEX> Area.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P99E2">The <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Institute for Fiscal Studies</ENAMEX> notes that the majority of forecasts of the impact of <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX> on the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> economy indicate that the government would be left with less money to spend even if it no longer had to pay into the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P100">
				<sentence xml:id="P100E0">On <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">15 June 2016</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Vote Leave</ENAMEX>, the official Leave campaign, presented its roadmap to lay out what would happen if <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> left the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P100E1">The blueprint suggested that <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Parliament</ENAMEX> would pass laws: <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Finance Bill</ENAMEX> to scrap <ENAMEX type="ACRONYM">VAT</ENAMEX> on tampons and household energy bills; <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Asylum and Immigration Control Bill</ENAMEX> to end the automatic right of <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> citizens to enter <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX>; <ENAMEX type="LEGAL"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">National Health Service</ENAMEX> (Funding Target) Bill</ENAMEX> to get an extra <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">100 million</ENAMEX> pounds a week; <ENAMEX type="LEGAL"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">European Union Law (Emergency Provisions</ENAMEX>) Bill</ENAMEX>; <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Free Trade Bill</ENAMEX> to start to negotiate its own deals with non-<ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> countries; and <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">European Communities Act 1972 (Repeal) Bill</ENAMEX> to end the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Court of Justice</ENAMEX>&apos;s jurisdiction over <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> and stop making contribution to the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> budget.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P101">
				<sentence xml:id="P101E0">On <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">24 June 2016</ENAMEX>, the bond and credit rating agency of <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">Moody</ENAMEX>&apos;s</ENAMEX>, on the basis of the result of the referendum, downgraded the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>&apos;s standing as a long-term debt issuer and the country&apos;s debt rating outlook from &quot;stable&quot; to &quot;negative,&quot; while retaining the overall rating of <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">Aa1</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P101E1"><ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">Fitch Ratings</ENAMEX> degraded the credit rating from <ENAMEX type="MEASURE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">AA+</ENAMEX> to <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">AA</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> because &quot;uncertainty following the referendum outcome will induce an abrupt slowdown in short-term <ENAMEX type="ACRONYM">GDP</ENAMEX> growth...&quot;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P101E2">.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P101E3"><ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">Standard &amp; Poor&apos;s</ENAMEX> cut the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>&apos;s rating to <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">AA</ENAMEX>, with the following comment: &quot;In our opinion, this outcome is a seminal event, and will lead to a less predictable, stable, and effective policy framework in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">U.K.</ENAMEX> ...</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P101E4">The negative outlook reflects the risk to economic prospects, fiscal and external performance, and the role of sterling as a reserve currency.&quot;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P101E5">On the other hand, economic analysts have pointed out that the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>, as a fiscally and monetarily sovereign nation, retains the ability to service or retire, at any time, any part or all of the state debt that is denominated in the national currency, and, hence, there is no risk whatsoever of defaulting on that part of its debt.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P102">
				<sentence xml:id="P102E0">On <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">27 June 2016</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">Chancellor of the Exchequer</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">George Osborne</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> attempted to reassure financial markets that the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> economy was not in serious trouble.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P102E1">This came after media reports that a survey by the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Institute of Directors</ENAMEX> suggested that <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">two-thirds</ENAMEX> of businesses believed that the outcome of the referendum would produce negative results as well as the dropping value of the sterling and the <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">FTSE 100</ENAMEX>, which began on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">24 June 2016</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P102E2"><ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">British</ENAMEX> businesses had also predicted that investment cuts, hiring freezes and redundancies would be necessary to cope with the results of the referendum.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P102E3"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Osborne</ENAMEX> indicated that <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> was facing the future &quot;from a position of strength&quot; and there was no current need for an emergency Budget.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P102E4">&quot;No one should doubt our resolve to maintain the fiscal stability we have delivered for this country ....</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P102E5">And to companies, large and small, I would say this: the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">British</ENAMEX> economy is fundamentally strong, highly competitive and we are open for business.&quot;</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P103">
				<sentence xml:id="P103E0">On <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">15 July 2016</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="MEDIA">Reuters</ENAMEX> reported that the value of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> funds&apos; assets under management has dropped by more than $<ENAMEX type="MEASURE">40 billion</ENAMEX> or <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">8.2 percent</ENAMEX> &quot;in the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">three weeks</ENAMEX> since <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX>&apos;s vote to leave the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>&quot;, primarily due to the devaluation of the pound according to the <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">EPFR</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">Emerging Portfolio Fund Research</ENAMEX>)</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P103E1">While the stock market had rebounded, analysts at <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">Société Générale</ENAMEX> bank in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX> were not bullish: &quot;The conditions and consequences of <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX> remain unclear&quot; and spoke of a &quot;strong negative bias on the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> domestic economy&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P103E2">In its summary, <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">one month after <ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="MEDIA">Guardian</ENAMEX> noted that the initial effects had been less severe than predicted and there had been some sort of recovery but that initially $<ENAMEX type="MEASURE">2tn</ENAMEX> had been wiped off world stock markets.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P104">
				<sentence xml:id="P104E0">On <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">22 July 2016</ENAMEX>, a &quot;flash&quot; (provisional) estimate for <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">July</ENAMEX> from the <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Markit Purchasing Managers&apos; Index</ENAMEX> (a survey of business activity) indicated the worst economic performance since the recession of <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2009</ENAMEX>, with the important service sector being badly affected.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P104E1">The pound fell by <ENAMEX type="MEASURE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="MEASURE">one</ENAMEX> cent</ENAMEX> against the dollar on the news.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P105">
				<sentence xml:id="P105E0">On <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">29 July 2016</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="MEDIA">The Guardian</ENAMEX> reported consumer confidence and confidence of manufacturers had both fallen sharply since the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit referendum</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P106">
				<sentence xml:id="P106E0"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">The City of Berlin</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, started to actively encourage <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>-based start-ups to re-locate to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Berlin</ENAMEX> by sending invitation letters.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P107">
				<sentence xml:id="P107E0"><ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">IMF</ENAMEX> forecast revisions and relative growth prospects</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P108">
				<sentence xml:id="P108E0">In its revised growth forecasts published <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">19 July 2016</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">IMF</ENAMEX> implicitly recognised it had been excessively pessimistic regarding the economic consequences of <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX>: “After saying that leaving the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX> could trigger a <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> recession, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">International Monetary Fund</ENAMEX> now expects the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">British</ENAMEX> economy to grow by <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">1.7 per cent</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">this year</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">1.3 per cent</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">next year</ENAMEX> […] The <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> is still set to be the <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">second</ENAMEX>-fastest growing economy in the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Group of Seven</ENAMEX> industrialised nations <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">this year</ENAMEX> – behind the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">United States</ENAMEX> – and <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">third</ENAMEX>-fastest <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">next year</ENAMEX>, behind the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">US</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Canada</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>&quot;</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P109">
				<sentence xml:id="P109E0"><ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">European</ENAMEX> experts from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">World Pensions Council</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">WPC</ENAMEX>) and the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">University of Bath</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> have argued that, beyond short-lived market volatility, the long term economic prospects of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> remain high, notably in terms of country attractiveness and foreign direct investment: &quot;Country risk experts we spoke to are confident the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>&apos;s economy will remain robust in the event of an exit from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P109E1">&apos;The economic attractiveness of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> will not go down and a trade war with <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> is in no one&apos;s interest,&apos; says <ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">M</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Nicolas Firzli</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">director-general</ENAMEX> of the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">World Pensions Council</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">WPC</ENAMEX>) and advisory board member for the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="BUSINESS">World Bank Global Infrastructure</ENAMEX> Facility</ENAMEX> [...]</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P109E2"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Bruce Morley</ENAMEX>, lecturer in economics at the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">University of Bath</ENAMEX>, goes further to suggest that the long-term benefits to the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> of leaving the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Union</ENAMEX>, such as less regulation and more control over <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX>&apos;s trade policy, could outweigh the short-term uncertainty observed in the [country risk] scores.&quot;</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P110">
				<sentence xml:id="P110E0">On <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">4 August 2016</ENAMEX>, in response to signs of an historically fast economic slowdown in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Bank of England</ENAMEX> took measures including cuts to interest rates and buying debt.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P111">
				<sentence xml:id="P111E0">On <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">10 August</ENAMEX> the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Institute for Fiscal Studies</ENAMEX> published a report funded by the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Economic and Social Research Council</ENAMEX> which warned that <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> faced some very difficult choices as it couldn&apos;t retain the benefits of full <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> membership whilst restricting <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> migration.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P111E1">The <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">IFS</ENAMEX> claimed the cost of reduced economic growth would cost the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> around £<ENAMEX type="MEASURE">70Bn</ENAMEX> more than the £<ENAMEX type="MEASURE">8Bn</ENAMEX> savings in membership fees.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P111E2">It did not expect new trade deals to make up the difference.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P112">
				<sentence xml:id="P112E0">Possible change in status: <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Scotland</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Northern Ireland</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Gibraltar</ENAMEX></ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P113">
				<sentence xml:id="P113E0">Before the referendum, leading figures with a range of opinions regarding <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">Scottish</ENAMEX> independence suggested that in the event the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> as a whole voted to leave the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> but <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Scotland</ENAMEX> as a whole voted to remain, a <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">second</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">Scottish</ENAMEX> independence referendum might be precipitated.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P113E1"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Former <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Labour<name attr="value">
				</name>/ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">Scottish</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">First Minister</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Henry McLeish</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> asserted that he would support <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">Scottish</ENAMEX> independence under such circumstances.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P113E2">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2013</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Scotland</ENAMEX> exported around <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">three and a half</ENAMEX> times more to the rest of the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> than to the rest of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P113E3">The pro-union organisation <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Scotland in Union</ENAMEX> has suggested that an independent <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Scotland</ENAMEX> within the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> would face trade barriers with a post-<ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> and face additional costs for re-entry to the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P114">
				<sentence xml:id="P114E0">With the outcome of the recent <ENAMEX type="EVENT">&apos;Brexit&apos; referendum</ENAMEX> being a majority vote for <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> to leave the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX>, the question of what happens to the border between <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Northern Ireland</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Republic of Ireland</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> has been raised.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P114E1"><ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Enda Kenny</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">Taoiseach</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Ireland</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, has warned that a <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> exit from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX> could damage the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Northern Ireland</ENAMEX> peace process.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P114E2"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Northern <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Ireland</ENAMEX> Secretary <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Theresa Villiers</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> denounced the suggestion as &quot;scaremongering of the worst possible kind&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P114E3">It has been suggested by a member of <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX>&apos;s parliamentary finance committee</ENAMEX> that a &quot;bilateral solution&quot; between the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK and Ireland</ENAMEX> could be negotiated quickly after a leave vote.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P114E4">On <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">24 June 2016</ENAMEX>, following the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">UK</ENAMEX>&apos;s</ENAMEX> vote to leave the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Northern <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Ireland</ENAMEX>&apos;s Deputy First Minister <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Martin McGuinness</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> called for a referendum on <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">Irish</ENAMEX> reunification.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P115">
				<sentence xml:id="P115E0">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2015</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">Chief Minister of Gibraltar</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Fabian Picardo</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> suggested that <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Gibraltar</ENAMEX> would attempt to remain part of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> in the event the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> voted to leave, but reaffirmed that, regardless of the result, the territory would remain <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">British</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P115E1">In a letter to the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">UK Foreign Affairs Select Committee</ENAMEX>, he requested that <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Gibraltar</ENAMEX> be considered in negotiations post-<ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P115E2"><ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Spain</ENAMEX>&apos;s <ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">foreign minister</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">José García-Margallo</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> said <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Spain</ENAMEX> would seek talks on <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Gibraltar</ENAMEX> the &quot;very next day&quot; after a <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">British</ENAMEX> exit from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P116">
				<sentence xml:id="P116E0">Status of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P117">
				<sentence xml:id="P117E0">The majority of those living in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> voted for the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> to remain in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P117E1"><ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="NATIONAL">Scottish</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">First Minister</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Nicola Sturgeon</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> said she had spoken to <ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">Mayor</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Sadiq Khan</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> about the possibility of remaining in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> and said he shared that objective for <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P117E2">A petition calling on <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Khan</ENAMEX> to declare <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> independent from the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> received <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">tens of thousands</ENAMEX> of signatures.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P117E3">Supporters of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>&apos;s independence argued that <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> should become a city-state similar to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Singapore</ENAMEX>, while remaining within the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P117E4"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Khan</ENAMEX> admitted that complete independence was unrealistic, but demanded devolving more powers and autonomy for <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P118">
				<sentence xml:id="P118E0">Border with <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P119">
				<sentence xml:id="P119E0">The <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Mayor of <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Saint-Quentin</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Xavier Bertrand</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, stated in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">February 2016</ENAMEX> that &quot;If <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> leaves <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX>, right away the border will leave <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Calais</ENAMEX> and go to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Dover</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P119E1">We will not continue to guard the border for <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> if it&apos;s no longer in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX>,&quot; indicating that the juxtaposed controls would end with a leave vote.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P119E2"><ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="NATIONAL">French</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">Finance Minister</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Emmanuel Macron</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> also suggested the agreement would be &quot;threatened&quot; by a leave vote.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P119E3">These claims have been disputed, as the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Le Touquet</ENAMEX> treaty</ENAMEX> enabling juxtaposed controls was not debated from within the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, and would not be legally void upon leaving.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P119E4">After the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX> vote, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Xavier Bertrand</ENAMEX> asked <ENAMEX type="PERSON">François Hollande</ENAMEX> to renogotiate the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Touquet</ENAMEX> agreement</ENAMEX>, which can be terminated by either party with <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">two years</ENAMEX>&apos; notice.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P119E5"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Hollande</ENAMEX> rejected the suggestion, and said: &quot;Calling into question the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Touquet deal</ENAMEX> on the pretext that <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> has voted for <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX> and will have to start negotiations to leave the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Union</ENAMEX> doesn&apos;t make sense.&quot;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P119E6"><ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Bernard Cazeneuve</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">French Interior Minister</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, confirmed there would be &quot;no changes to the accord&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P119E7">He said: &quot;The border at <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Calais</ENAMEX> is closed and will remain so.&quot;</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P120">
				<sentence xml:id="P120E0">Academic funding</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P121">
				<sentence xml:id="P121E0"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> universities rely on the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> for around <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">16%</ENAMEX> of their total research funding, and are disproportionately successful at winning <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>-awarded research grants.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P121E1">This has raised questions about how such funding would be impacted by a <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">British</ENAMEX> exit.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P122">
				<sentence xml:id="P122E0"><ENAMEX type="TITLE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">St George&apos;s, University of London</ENAMEX> professor</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">UKIP</ENAMEX> campaigner <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Angus Dalgleish</ENAMEX> pointed out that <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> paid much more into the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> research budget than it received, and that existing <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">European</ENAMEX> collaborations such as <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">CERN</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">European Molecular Biology Laboratory</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">EMBL</ENAMEX>)</ENAMEX> began long before the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Lisbon Treaty</ENAMEX>, adding that leaving the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> would not damage <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX>&apos;s science.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P123">
				<sentence xml:id="P123E0"><ENAMEX type="TITLE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">London School of Economics</ENAMEX> emeritus professor</ENAMEX> (and founder of <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">UKIP</ENAMEX>) <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Alan Sked</ENAMEX> pointed out that non-<ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> countries such as <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Israel</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Switzerland</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> signed agreements with the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> in terms of the funding of collaborative research and projects, and suggested that if <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> left the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> would be able to reach a similar agreement with the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, pointing out that educated people and research bodies would easily find some financial arrangement during an at least <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2-year</ENAMEX> transition period which was related to <ENAMEX type="LEGAL"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LEGAL">Article 50 of Treaty of European Union</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">TEU</ENAMEX>)</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P123E1">The <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">UK government</ENAMEX> promised that a major type of <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> research grant, <ENAMEX type="UNKNOWN">Horizon <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">2020</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> funding, will be funded by the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> for their remaining duration after <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> exit for <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> researchers.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P124">
				<sentence xml:id="P124E0">A <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">July 2016</ENAMEX> investigation by <ENAMEX type="MEDIA">The Guardian</ENAMEX> suggested a large number of research projects in a wide range of fields had been hit after the referendum result.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P124E1">They reported that <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">European</ENAMEX> partners were reluctant to employ <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">British</ENAMEX> researchers due to uncertainties over funding.</sentence>
			</p>
		</document>
	</subcorpus>
</corpus>
