<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<corpus>
	<subcorpus>
		<document name="Wikipedia_holocaust.2.training.2layers.xml">
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P63">
				<sentence xml:id="P63E0">Legal repression and emigration</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P64">
				<sentence xml:id="P64E0">Further information: <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Anti-Jewish legislation</ENAMEX> in  <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Nazi Germany</ENAMEX>, Racial policy of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Nazi Germany</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX Type="LEGAL"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LEGAL">Nuremberg Laws</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LEGAL">Haavara Agreement</ENAMEX></ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P65">
				<sentence xml:id="P65E0">With the establishment of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Third Reich</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazi</ENAMEX> leaders proclaimed the existence of a <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Volksgemeinschaft</ENAMEX> (&quot;people&apos;s community&quot;).</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P65E1"><ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazi</ENAMEX> policies divided the population into <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">two</ENAMEX> categories, the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Volksgenossen</ENAMEX> (&quot;<ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">national comrades</ENAMEX>&quot;)</ENAMEX>, who belonged to the <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Volksgemeinschaft</ENAMEX>, and the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Gemeinschaftsfremde</ENAMEX> (&quot;community aliens&quot;), who did not.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P65E2"><ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazi</ENAMEX> policies about repression divided people into <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">three</ENAMEX> types of enemies, the &quot;racial&quot; enemies such as the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Romani</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> who were viewed as enemies because of their &quot;blood&quot;; political opponents such as <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Marxists</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">liberals</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Christians</ENAMEX> and the &quot;<ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">reactionaries</ENAMEX>&quot;</ENAMEX> who were viewed as wayward &quot;<ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">National Comrades</ENAMEX>&quot;; and moral opponents such as <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">homosexuals</ENAMEX>, the &quot;work-shy&quot; and habitual criminals, also seen as wayward &quot;<ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">National Comrades</ENAMEX>&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P65E3">The last <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">two</ENAMEX> groups were to be sent to concentration camps for &quot;re-education&quot;, with the aim of eventual absorption into the <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Volksgemeinschaft</ENAMEX>, though some of the moral opponents were to be sterilized, as they were regarded as &quot;genetically inferior&quot;.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P66">
				<sentence xml:id="P66E0"><ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> refugees being marched away by <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">British police</ENAMEX> at <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Croydon airport</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">March 1939</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P66E1">They were put on a flight to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Warsaw</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P67">
				<sentence xml:id="P67E0">&quot;Racial&quot; enemies such as the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> could, by definition, never belong to the <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Volksgemeinschaft</ENAMEX>; they were to be totally removed from society.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P67E1"><ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> historian <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Detlev Peukert</ENAMEX> wrote that the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">National Socialists</ENAMEX>&apos; &quot;goal was an utopian <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Volksgemeinschaft</ENAMEX>, totally under police surveillance, in which any attempt at nonconformist behaviour, or even any hint or intention of such behaviour, would be visited with terror&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P67E2"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Peukert</ENAMEX> quotes policy documents on the &quot;<ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Treatment of Community Aliens</ENAMEX>&quot; from <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1944</ENAMEX>, which (though never implemented) showed the full intentions of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazi</ENAMEX> social policy: &quot;persons who ...</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P67E3">show themselves [to be] unable to comply by their own efforts with the minimum requirements of the national community&quot; were to be placed under police supervision, and if this did not reform them, they were to be taken to a concentration camp.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P68">
				<sentence xml:id="P68E0">Leading up to the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">March 1933 Reichstag elections</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazis</ENAMEX> intensified their campaign of violence against the opposition.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P68E1">With the co-operation of local authorities, they set up concentration camps for extrajudicial imprisonment of their opponents.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P68E2">One of the first, at <ENAMEX type="INSTALLATION">Dachau</ENAMEX>, opened on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">9 March 1933</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P68E3">Initially the camp primarily contained <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Communists</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Social Democrats</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P68E4">Other early prisons—for example, in basements and storehouses run by the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">Sturmabteilung</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">SA</ENAMEX>)</ENAMEX> and less commonly by the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">Schutzstaffel</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">SS</ENAMEX>)</ENAMEX>—were consolidated by <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">mid-1934</ENAMEX> into purpose-built camps outside the cities, run exclusively by the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">SS</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P68E5">The initial purpose of the camps was to serve as a deterrent by terrorizing those <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Germans</ENAMEX> who did not conform to the <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Volksgemeinschaft</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P68E6">Those sent to the camps included the &quot;educable&quot;, whose wills could be broken into becoming &quot;<ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">National Comrades</ENAMEX>&quot;, and the &quot;biologically depraved&quot;, who were to be sterilized, were to be held permanently, and over time were increasingly subject to extermination through labor, i.e., being worked to death.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P69">
				<sentence xml:id="P69E0">Throughout the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1930s</ENAMEX>, the legal, economic, and social rights of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> were steadily restricted.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P69E1">The <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">Israeli</ENAMEX> historian <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Saul Friedländer</ENAMEX> writes that, for the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazis</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> drew its strength &quot;from the purity of its blood and from its rootedness in the sacred <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> earth.&quot;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P69E2">On <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1 April 1933</ENAMEX>, there occurred a boycott of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> businesses, which was the <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">first</ENAMEX> national <ENAMEX type="CONCEPTUAL">antisemitic</ENAMEX> campaign, initially planned for <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">a week</ENAMEX>, but called off after <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">one day</ENAMEX> owing to lack of popular support.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P69E3">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1933</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Law for the Restoration of the Professional Civil Service</ENAMEX> was passed which excluded all <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> and other &quot;non-<ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Aryans</ENAMEX>&quot; </ENAMEX>from the civil service.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P69E4">All persons in the civil service had to obtain an <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Ariernachweis</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Aryan</ENAMEX> certificate) in order to prove their <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Aryan</ENAMEX> ancestry.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P69E5">The <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">first</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="CONCEPTUAL">antisemitic</ENAMEX> law passed in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Third Reich</ENAMEX>; the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LEGAL">Physicians&apos; Law</ENAMEX>; and the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LEGAL">Farm Law</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, forbidding <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> from owning farms or taking part in agriculture.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P70">
				<sentence xml:id="P70E0"><ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> lawyers were disbarred, and in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Dresden</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> lawyers and judges were dragged out of their offices and courtrooms and beaten.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P70E1">At the insistence of <ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">President</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Paul von Hindenburg</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Hitler</ENAMEX> added an exemption allowing <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> civil servants who were veterans of the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">First World War</ENAMEX> or whose fathers or sons had served, to remain in office, but he revoked this exemption in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1937</ENAMEX>, after <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Hindenburg</ENAMEX>&apos;s death.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P70E2"><ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> were excluded from schools and universities (the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Law to Prevent Overcrowding in Schools</ENAMEX>), from belonging to the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Journalists&apos; Association</ENAMEX>, and from being owners or editors of newspapers.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P71">
				<sentence xml:id="P71E0"> A self-respecting nation cannot, on a scale accepted up to now, leave its higher activities in the hands of people of racially foreign origin ...</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P71E1">Allowing the presence of too high a percentage of people of foreign origin in relation to their percentage in the general population could be interpreted as an acceptance of the superiority of other races, something decidedly to be rejected.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P72">
				<sentence xml:id="P72E0">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">July 1933</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Law for the Prevention of Hereditarily Diseased Offspring</ENAMEX> calling for compulsory sterilization of the &quot;inferior&quot; was passed.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P72E1">This major eugenics policy led to <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">over 200</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">Hereditary Health Courts</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Erbgesundheitsgerichte</ENAMEX>)</ENAMEX> being set up, under whose rulings <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">over 400,000</ENAMEX> people were sterilized against their will during the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Nazi period</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P73">
				<sentence xml:id="P73E0">Racial classification chart based on the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LEGAL">Nuremberg Laws</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">1935</ENAMEX></ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P74">
				<sentence xml:id="P74E0">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1935</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Hitler</ENAMEX> introduced the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Nuremberg Laws</ENAMEX>, which prohibited &quot;<ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Aryans</ENAMEX>&quot; from having sexual relations or marriages with <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX>, although this was later extended to include &quot;<ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Gypsies</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Negroes</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> or their bastard offspring&quot; (the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Law for the Protection of German Blood and German Honor</ENAMEX>), stripped <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">German Jews</ENAMEX> of their citizenship and deprived them of all civil rights.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P74E1">At the same time the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazis</ENAMEX> used propaganda to promulgate the concept of <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Rassenschande</ENAMEX> (race defilement) to justify the need for a restrictive law.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P74E2"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Hitler</ENAMEX> described the &quot;<ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Blood Law</ENAMEX>&quot; in particular as &quot;the attempt at a legal regulation of a problem, which in the event of further failure would then have through law to be transferred to the <ENAMEX type="UNKNOWN"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="UNKNOWN">final solution</ENAMEX> of the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">National Socialist Party</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P74E3"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Hitler</ENAMEX> said that if the &quot;<ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> problem&quot; cannot be solved by these laws, it &quot;must then be handed over by law
				 to the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">National-Socialist Party</ENAMEX> for a <ENAMEX type="UNKNOWN">final solution</ENAMEX>&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P74E4">The &quot;<ENAMEX type="UNKNOWN"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="UNKNOWN">final solution</ENAMEX>&quot; (<ENAMEX subType="2" type="UNKNOWN">Endlösung</ENAMEX>)</ENAMEX> became the standard <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazi</ENAMEX> euphemism for the extermination of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P74E5">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">January 1939</ENAMEX>, he said in a public speech: &quot;If international-finance <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewry</ENAMEX> inside and outside <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX> should succeed once more in plunging the nations into yet another world war, the consequences will not be the <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Bolshevization of the earth</ENAMEX> and thereby the victory of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewry</ENAMEX>, but the annihilation (vernichtung) of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> race in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX>&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P74E6">Footage from this speech was used to conclude the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1940</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazi</ENAMEX> propaganda movie <ENAMEX type="CREATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="CREATION">The Eternal Jew</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX subType="2" type="CREATION">Der ewige Jude</ENAMEX>)</ENAMEX>, whose purpose was to provide a rationale and blueprint for eliminating the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> from <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P75">
				<sentence xml:id="P75E0"><ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Intellectuals</ENAMEX> were among the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="MEASURE">first</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> to leave.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P75E1">The philosopher <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Walter Benjamin</ENAMEX> left for <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Paris</ENAMEX> on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">18 March 1933</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P75E2">Novelist <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Lion Feuchtwanger</ENAMEX> went to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Switzerland</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P75E3">The conductor <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Bruno Walter</ENAMEX> fled after being told that the hall of the <ENAMEX type="INSTALLATION">Berlin Philharmonic</ENAMEX> would be burned down if he conducted a concert there: the <ENAMEX type="MEDIA">Frankfurter Zeitung</ENAMEX> explained on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">6 April</ENAMEX> that <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Walter</ENAMEX> and fellow conductor <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Otto Klemperer</ENAMEX> had been forced to flee because the government was unable to protect them against the mood of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">German</ENAMEX> public, which had been provoked by &quot;<ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> artistic liquidators&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P75E4"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Albert Einstein</ENAMEX> was visiting the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">US</ENAMEX> on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">30 January 1933</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P75E5">He returned to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Ostende</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Belgium</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, never to set foot in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> again, and calling events there a &quot;psychic illness of the masses&quot;; he was expelled from the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Kaiser Wilhelm Society</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Prussian Academy of Sciences</ENAMEX>, and his citizenship was rescinded.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P75E6">When <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> annexed <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Austria</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1938</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Sigmund Freud</ENAMEX> and his family fled from <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Vienna</ENAMEX> to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">England</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P75E7"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Saul Friedländer</ENAMEX> writes that when <ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Max Liebermann</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">honorary president</ENAMEX> of the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">Prussian Academy of Arts</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, resigned his position, none of his colleagues expressed sympathy, and he was still ostracized at his death <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">two years later</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P75E8">When the police arrived in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1943</ENAMEX> with a stretcher to deport his <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">85</ENAMEX>-year-old bedridden widow, she committed suicide with an overdose of barbiturates rather than be taken.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P76">
				<sentence xml:id="P76E0"><ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Kristallnacht</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">1938</ENAMEX>)</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P77">
				<sentence xml:id="P77E0">Main article: <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Kristallnacht</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P78">
				<sentence xml:id="P78E0">The synagogue of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Siegen</ENAMEX> burning on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">10 November 1938</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P79">
				<sentence xml:id="P79E0">On <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">7 November 1938</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> minor <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Herschel Grünspan</ENAMEX> assassinated <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazi German</ENAMEX> diplomat <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Ernst vom Rath</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Paris</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P79E1">The <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazis</ENAMEX> used this incident a pretext to go beyond legal repression to large-scale physical violence against <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish Germans</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P79E2">What the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazis</ENAMEX> claimed to be spontaneous &quot;public outrage&quot; was a wave of pogroms instigated by the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Nazi Party</ENAMEX> and carried out by <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">SA</ENAMEX> members and affiliates throughout <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Nazi Germany</ENAMEX>, at the time consisting of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> proper, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Austria</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Sudetenland</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P79E3">These pogroms became known as <ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Kristallnacht</ENAMEX> (&quot;<ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Crystal Night</ENAMEX>&quot; or &quot;<ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Night of Broken Glass</ENAMEX>&quot;)</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P79E4"><ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> were attacked and <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> property was vandalized.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P79E5"><ENAMEX type="MEASURE">Over 7,000</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> shops and more than <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">1,200</ENAMEX> synagogues (roughly <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">two-thirds</ENAMEX> of the synagogues in areas under <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> control) were damaged or destroyed.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P80">
				<sentence xml:id="P80E0">The death toll is assumed to be much higher than the official number of <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">91</ENAMEX> dead.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P80E1"><ENAMEX type="MEASURE">30,000</ENAMEX> were sent to concentration camps, including <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Dachau</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Sachsenhausen</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Buchenwald</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Oranienburg</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, where they were kept for <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">several weeks</ENAMEX>, and released when they could either prove that they were about to emigrate in the near future, or transferred their property to the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazis</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P80E2"><ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">German Jewry</ENAMEX> was made collectively responsible for restitution of the material damage of the pogroms, amounting to <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">several hundred thousand</ENAMEX> Reichsmarks, and furthermore had to pay an &quot;atonement tax&quot; of more than a <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">billion</ENAMEX> Reichsmarks.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P80E3">After these pogroms, <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> emigration from <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> accelerated, while public <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> life in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> ceased to exist.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P81">
				<sentence xml:id="P81E0">Resettlement and deportation</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P82">
				<sentence xml:id="P82E0">Wiki letter w.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P83">
				<sentence xml:id="P83E0">	This section is missing information about whether there were any plans for the resettlement and/or deportation of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Romani</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Slavs</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P83E1">Please expand the section to include this information.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P83E2">Further details may exist on the talk page.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P84">
				<sentence xml:id="P84E0">The <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">930</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> refugees aboard the <ENAMEX type="ARTIFACT">MS St. Louis</ENAMEX> were refused entry to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Cuba</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">United States</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Canada</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, and the ship was forced to return to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P85">
				<sentence xml:id="P85E0">Before the war, the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazis</ENAMEX> considered mass deportation of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">German</ENAMEX> (and subsequently the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">European</ENAMEX>) <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewry</ENAMEX> from <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P85E1"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Hitler</ENAMEX>&apos;s agreement to the <ENAMEX type="UNKNOWN"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">1938–39</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="UNKNOWN">Schacht Plan</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, and the continued flight of <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">thousands</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> for an extended period when the <ENAMEX type="UNKNOWN">Schacht Plan</ENAMEX> came to nothing, indicate that the preference for a concerted genocide of the type that came later did not yet exist.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P86">
				<sentence xml:id="P86E0"><ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazi</ENAMEX> bureaucrats also developed plans to deport <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Europe&apos;s Jews</ENAMEX> to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Siberia</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P86E1"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Palestine</ENAMEX> was the only location to which any <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazi</ENAMEX> relocation plan succeeded in producing significant results, via an agreement begun in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1933</ENAMEX> between the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">Zionist Federation of Germany</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">die Zionistische Vereinigung für Deutschland</ENAMEX>)</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Nazi government</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Haavara Agreement</ENAMEX>. This agreement resulted in the transfer of about <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">60,000</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">German Jews</ENAMEX> and $<ENAMEX type="MEASURE">100 million</ENAMEX> from <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Palestine</ENAMEX>, until the outbreak of <ENAMEX type="EVENT">World War II</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P87">
				<sentence xml:id="P87E0"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Hitler</ENAMEX> halted plans to reclaim former <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> colonies such as <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Tanganyika</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">South West Africa</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> for <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> resettlement, arguing that no place where &quot;so much blood of heroic <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Germans</ENAMEX> had been spilled&quot; should be made available as a residence for the &quot;worst enemies of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Germans</ENAMEX>&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P87E1">Diplomatic efforts were undertaken to convince the other colonial powers, primarily the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">United Kingdom</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, to accept expelled <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> in their colonies.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P87E2">Areas considered for possible resettlement included <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">British Palestine</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Italian</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Abyssinia</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">British Rhodesia</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">French Madagascar</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Australia</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P88">
				<sentence xml:id="P88E0">Of these areas, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Madagascar</ENAMEX> was the most seriously discussed.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P88E1"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Heydrich</ENAMEX> called the <ENAMEX type="UNKNOWN">Madagascar Plan</ENAMEX> a &quot;territorial <ENAMEX type="UNKNOWN">final solution</ENAMEX>&quot;; it was a remote location, and the island&apos;s unfavorable conditions would hasten deaths.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P88E2"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Hitler</ENAMEX> approved in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1938</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Adolf Eichmann</ENAMEX>&apos;s office carried out resettlement planning, but abandoned it once the mass killing of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> had begun in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1941</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P88E3">The end of the <ENAMEX type="UNKNOWN">Madagascar Plan</ENAMEX> was announced on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">10 February 1942</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P88E4">The <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">German Foreign Office</ENAMEX> was given the official explanation that due to the war with the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Soviet Union</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> were to be &quot;sent to the east&quot;.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P89">
				<sentence xml:id="P89E0"><ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazi</ENAMEX> resettlement schemes entailed taking measures to prepare the way eastwards.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P89E1">Ethnic <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Germans</ENAMEX> required more <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Lebensraum</ENAMEX> (&quot;living space&quot;) according to <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazi</ENAMEX> doctrine so population displacement (which included murder) and colonial settlement were intrinsically linked.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P89E2">Once the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazis</ENAMEX> embarked on their push eastwards through <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Poland</ENAMEX> and later into <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Russia</ENAMEX> with <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Operation Barbarossa</ENAMEX>, there was a radicalization in the speed and brutality of their methods.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P89E3">Winning land from the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Russian</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Slavic</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> peoples in the east it&apos;s complicated was more than just territorial aggrandizement for <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Hitler</ENAMEX>; it was part of the final reckoning with <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Jewish Bolshevism</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P90">
				<sentence xml:id="P90E0">Early measures</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P91">
				<sentence xml:id="P91E0">In <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">German-occupied Poland</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P92">
				<sentence xml:id="P92E0">Main article: The <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Holocaust in Poland</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P93">
				<sentence xml:id="P93E0">Further information: <ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Invasion of Poland</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Occupation of Poland</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">1939–45</ENAMEX>)</ENAMEX>, and History of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Poland</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P94">
				<sentence xml:id="P94E0"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Nazi Germany</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1941</ENAMEX>, including areas annexed from <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Poland</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">General Government area</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P95">
				<sentence xml:id="P95E0"><ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Germany&apos;s invasion of Poland</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">September 1939</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> increased the urgency of the &quot;<ENAMEX type="CONCEPTUAL">Jewish</ENAMEX> Question&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P95E1"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Poland</ENAMEX> was home to about <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">three million</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> (nearly <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">nine percent</ENAMEX> of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Polish</ENAMEX> population) in centuries-old communities, <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">two-thirds</ENAMEX> of whom fell under <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazi</ENAMEX> control with <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Poland</ENAMEX>&apos;s capitulation.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P96">
				<sentence xml:id="P96E0">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">September 1939</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Himmler</ENAMEX> appointed <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Reinhard Heydrich</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="TITLE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">chief</ENAMEX> of the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">Reich Main Security Office</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">Reichssicherheitshauptamt</ENAMEX> or <ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">RSHA</ENAMEX>)</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P96E1">This organization was made up of <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">seven</ENAMEX> departments, including the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">Security Service</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">SD</ENAMEX>) and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">Gestapo</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P96E2">They were to oversee the work of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">SS</ENAMEX> in occupied <ENAMEX  type="LOCATION">Poland</ENAMEX>, and carry out the policy towards the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> described in <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Heydrich</ENAMEX>&apos;s report.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P96E3">The first organized murders of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> by <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> forces occurred during <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Operation Tannenberg</ENAMEX> and through <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Selbstschutz</ENAMEX> units.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P96E4"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Heydrich</ENAMEX> (later the <ENAMEX type="TITLE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">Reichsprotektor</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Bohemia and Moravia</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>) recommended concentrating all the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Polish Jews</ENAMEX> in ghettos in major cities, where they would be put to work for the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> war industry.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P96E5">The ghettos would be in cities located on railway junctions to furnish, in <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Heydrich</ENAMEX>&apos;s words, &quot;a better possibility of control and later deportation&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P96E6">During his interrogation in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1961</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Adolf Eichmann</ENAMEX> recalled that this &quot;later deportation&quot; actually meant &quot;physical extermination.&quot;</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P97">
				<sentence xml:id="P97E0">“</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P98">
				<sentence xml:id="P98E0">I ask nothing of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> except that they should disappear.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P99">
				<sentence xml:id="P99E0">	”</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P100">
				<sentence xml:id="P100E0">— <ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Hans Frank</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">Nazi governor</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> for occupied <ENAMEX type= "LOCATION">Poland</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P101">
				<sentence xml:id="P101E0">The <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> were later herded into ghettos, mostly in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">General Government area</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">central Poland</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, where they were put to work under the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Reich Labor Office</ENAMEX> headed by <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Fritz Sauckel</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P101E1">Here <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">many thousands</ENAMEX> died from maltreatment, disease, starvation, and exhaustion, but there was still no program of systematic killing.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P101E2">There is little doubt, however, that the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazis</ENAMEX> saw forced labor as a form of extermination.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P101E3">The expression <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Vernichtung durch Arbeit</ENAMEX> (&quot;destruction through work&quot;) was frequently used.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P102">
				<sentence xml:id="P102E0">Further information: <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> ghettos in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">German-occupied Poland</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P103">
				<sentence xml:id="P103E0">Although it was clear by <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">late 1941</ENAMEX> that the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">SS</ENAMEX> hierarchy was determined to embark on a policy of killing all the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> under <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> control, there was still opposition to this policy within the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazi</ENAMEX> regime, although the motive was economic, not humanitarian.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P103E1"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Hermann Göring</ENAMEX>, who had overall control of the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> war industry, and the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">German army&apos;s Economics Department</ENAMEX>, argued that the enormous <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> labor force assembled in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">General Government area</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX type="MEASURE">more than a million</ENAMEX> able-bodied workers), was an asset too valuable to waste, particularly with <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> failing to secure rapid victory over the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Soviet Union</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P104">
				<sentence xml:id="P104E0">In other occupied countries</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P105">
				<sentence xml:id="P105E0"><ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> mass grave near <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Zolochiv</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">west Ukraine</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Nazi occupied USSR</ENAMEX>)</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P105E1">Photo was found by <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Soviets</ENAMEX> at former <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Gestapo</ENAMEX> headquarters in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Zolochiv</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P106">
				<sentence xml:id="P106E0">When <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Germany occupied Norway</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Netherlands</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Luxembourg</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Belgium</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1940</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Yugoslavia</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Greece</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1941</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="CONCEPTUAL">antisemitic</ENAMEX> measures were also introduced into these countries, although the pace and severity varied greatly from country to country according to local political circumstances.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P106E1"><ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> were removed from economic and cultural life and were subject to various restrictive laws, but physical deportation did not occur in most places before <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1942</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P106E2">The <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">Vichy regime</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">occupied France</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> actively collaborated in persecuting <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="NATIONAL">French</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P106E3"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX>&apos;s allies <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Italy</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Hungary</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Romania</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Bulgaria</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Finland</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> were pressured to introduce <ENAMEX type="CONCEPTUAL">antisemitic</ENAMEX> measures, but for the most part they did not comply until compelled to do so.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P106E4">During the course of the war some <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">900</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">300</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Roma</ENAMEX> passed through the <ENAMEX type="INSTALLATION">Banjica concentration camp</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Belgrade</ENAMEX>, intended primarily for <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Serbian communists</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">royalists</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> and others who resisted occupation.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P106E5">The <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> puppet regime in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Croatia</ENAMEX>, on the other hand, began actively persecuting <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> on its own initiative, so the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Legal Decree on the Nationalization of the Property of Jews and Jewish Companies</ENAMEX> was declared on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">10 October 1941</ENAMEX> in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Independent State of Croatia</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P107">
				<sentence xml:id="P107E0">In <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">North Africa</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P108">
				<sentence xml:id="P108E0">See also: The <ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Holocaust</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX subType="2" type="NATIONAL">Italian</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Libya</ENAMEX></ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P109">
				<sentence xml:id="P109E0">Though the vast majority of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> affected and killed during <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Holocaust</ENAMEX> were of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Ashkenazi</ENAMEX> descent, <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Sephardi</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Mizrahi Jews</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> suffered greatly as well.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P110">
				<sentence xml:id="P110E0">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1938</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="CONCEPTUAL">Fascist</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Italian regime</ENAMEX> passed <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">anti-Semitic laws</ENAMEX> which barred <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> from government jobs and government schools, and required them to stamp &quot;<ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> race&quot; into their passports.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P110E1">But these laws were not harsh enough to force <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> to leave <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Libya</ENAMEX>, because <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">25%</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Tripoli</ENAMEX>&apos;s population was <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX>, and the city had <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">over 44</ENAMEX> synagogues.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P110E2">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1942</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazis</ENAMEX> occupied <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Benghazi&apos;s</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Jewish Quarter</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> and deported <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">more than 2,000</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> to <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazi</ENAMEX> labor camps.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P110E3">By the end of <ENAMEX type="EVENT">WWII</ENAMEX>, about <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">one-fifth</ENAMEX> of those who were sent away had perished.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P110E4">Several forced labor camps for <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> were established in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Libya</ENAMEX>, the largest of which, the <ENAMEX type="INSTALLATION">Giado camp</ENAMEX>, held almost <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">2,600</ENAMEX> inmates, of whom <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">562</ENAMEX> died of weakness, hunger, and disease.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P110E5">Smaller labor camps were established in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Gharyan</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Jeren</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Tigrinna</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P111">
				<sentence xml:id="P111E0"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Tunisia</ENAMEX>, the only <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">North African</ENAMEX> country to come under direct <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazi</ENAMEX> occupation, had <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">100,000</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> when the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazis</ENAMEX> arrived in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">November 1942</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P111E1">During their <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">six months</ENAMEX> of occupation, the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazis</ENAMEX> imposed anti-<ENAMEX type="CONCEPTUAL">Semitic</ENAMEX> policies in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Tunisia</ENAMEX>, including forcing <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> to wear the <ENAMEX type="UNKNOWN">Yellow Star</ENAMEX>, fines, and property confiscation.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P111E2">Some <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">5,000</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="NATIONAL">Tunisian</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> were subjected to forced labor, and some were deported to <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">European</ENAMEX> death camps.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P111E3"><ENAMEX type="MEASURE">More than 2,500</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="NATIONAL">Tunisian</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> died in slave labor camps during the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> occupation.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P112">
				<sentence xml:id="P112E0"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION">General Government</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX type="INSTALLATION">Lublin reservation</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX type="UNKNOWN">Nisko plan</ENAMEX>)</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P113">
				<sentence xml:id="P113E0">Main articles: <ENAMEX type="UNKNOWN"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="UNKNOWN">Nisko Plan</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">General Government</ENAMEX></ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P114">
				<sentence xml:id="P114E0">On <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">28 September 1939</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> gained control over the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Lublin area</ENAMEX> through the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">German-Soviet agreement</ENAMEX> in exchange for <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Lithuania</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P114E1">According to the <ENAMEX type="UNKNOWN">Nisko Plan</ENAMEX>, they set up the <ENAMEX type="INSTALLATION">Lublin-Lipowa Reservation</ENAMEX> in the area.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P114E2">The reservation was designated by <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Adolf Eichmann</ENAMEX>, who was assigned the task of removing all <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> from <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Austria</ENAMEX>, and the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Protectorate of Bohemia and Moravia</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P114E3">They shipped the first <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Lublin</ENAMEX> on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">18 October 1939</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P114E4">The first train loads consisted of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> deported from <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Austria</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Protectorate of Bohemia and Moravia</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P114E5">By <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">30 January 1940</ENAMEX>, a total of <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">78,000</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> had been deported to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Lublin</ENAMEX> from <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Austria</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Czechoslovakia</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P114E6">On <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">12 and 13 February 1940</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Pomeranian Jews</ENAMEX> were deported to the <ENAMEX type="INSTALLATION">Lublin reservation</ENAMEX>, resulting in <ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">Pomeranian Gauleiter</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Franz Schwede-Coburg</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> to be the <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">first</ENAMEX> to declare his Gau (country subdivision) <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">judenrein</ENAMEX> (&quot;free of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX>&quot;).</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P114E7">On <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">24 March 1940</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Göring</ENAMEX> put the <ENAMEX type="UNKNOWN">Nisko Plan</ENAMEX> on hold, and abandoned it entirely by the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">end of April</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P114E8">By the time the <ENAMEX type="UNKNOWN">Nisko Plan</ENAMEX> was stopped, the total number of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> who had been transported to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Nisko</ENAMEX> had reached <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">95,000</ENAMEX>, many of whom had died from starvation.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P115">
				<sentence xml:id="P115E0">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">July 1940</ENAMEX>, due to the difficulties of supporting the increased population in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">General Government</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Hitler</ENAMEX> had the deportations temporarily halted.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P116">
				<sentence xml:id="P116E0">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">October 1940</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">Gauleiters</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Josef Bürckel</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Robert Heinrich Wagner</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> oversaw <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Operation Bürckel</ENAMEX>, the expulsion of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> into unoccupied <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX> from their Gaues and the parts of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Alsace-Lorraine</ENAMEX> that had been annexed that summer to the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Reich</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P116E1">Only those <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> in mixed marriages were not expelled.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P116E2">The <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">6,500</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> affected by <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Operation Bürckel</ENAMEX> were given at most <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">two hours</ENAMEX> warning on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">the night of 22–23 October 1940</ENAMEX>, before being rounded up.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P116E3">The <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">nine</ENAMEX> trains carrying the deported <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> crossed over into <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX> &quot;without any warning to the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">French</ENAMEX> authorities&quot;, who were not happy with receiving them.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P116E4">The deportees had not been allowed to take any of their possessions with them, these being confiscated by the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> authorities.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P116E5">The <ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">German Foreign Minister</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Joachim von Ribbentrop</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> treated the ensuing complaints by the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Vichy government</ENAMEX> over the expulsions in a &quot;most dilatory fashion&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P116E6">As a result, the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> expelled in <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Operation Bürckel</ENAMEX> were interned in harsh conditions by the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Vichy</ENAMEX> authorities at the camps in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Gurs</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Rivesaltes</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Les Milles</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> while awaiting a chance to return them to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P117">
				<sentence xml:id="P117E0">During <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1940 and 1941</ENAMEX>, the murder of large numbers of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">German-occupied Poland</ENAMEX> continued, and the deportation of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> to the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">General Government</ENAMEX> was undertaken.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P117E1">The deportation of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> from <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX>, particularly <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Berlin</ENAMEX>, was not officially completed until <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1943</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P117E2">(Many <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Berlin Jews</ENAMEX> were able to survive in hiding.)</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P117E3">By <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">December 1939</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">3.5 million</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> were crowded into the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">General Government area</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P118">
				<sentence xml:id="P118E0">Concentration and labor camps (<ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1933–1945</ENAMEX>)</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P119">
				<sentence xml:id="P119E0">Further information: <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazi</ENAMEX> concentration camps, List of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazi</ENAMEX> concentration camps, and Extermination through labor</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P120">
				<sentence xml:id="P120E0"><ENAMEX type="PERIOD">12 April 1945</ENAMEX>: <ENAMEX type="INSTALLATION">Lager Nordhausen</ENAMEX>, where <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">20,000</ENAMEX> inmates are believed to have died.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P121">
				<sentence xml:id="P121E0">The <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Third Reich</ENAMEX> first used concentration camps as places of incarceration.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P121E1">And though death rates were high—with a mortality rate of <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">50%</ENAMEX>—they were not designed to be killing centers.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P121E2"><ENAMEX type="PERIOD"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">After</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">1939</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, the camps increasingly became places where <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">POWs</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> were either killed or made to work as slave laborers, undernourished and tortured.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P121E3">By <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1942</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">six</ENAMEX> large camps were built in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Poland</ENAMEX> solely for mass killing.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P121E4">It is estimated <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Germans</ENAMEX> established <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">15,000</ENAMEX> camps and subcamps in the occupied countries, mostly in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">eastern Europe</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P121E5">New camps were founded in areas with large <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Polish intelligentsia</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">communist</ENAMEX>, or <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Roma</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Sinti populations</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, including inside <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P121E6">Prisoner transportation was often carried out under horrifying conditions in rail freight cars; many died before reaching their destination.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P122">
				<sentence xml:id="P122E0">Extermination through labor was a policy of systematic extermination—camp inmates would literally be worked to death, or worked to physical exhaustion, when they would be gassed or shot.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P122E1">Slave labour was used in war production, for example producing <ENAMEX type="ARTIFACT">V-2 rockets</ENAMEX> at <ENAMEX type="INSTALLATION">Mittelbau-Dora</ENAMEX>, and various armaments around the <ENAMEX type="INSTALLATION">Mauthausen-Gusen concentration camp</ENAMEX> complex.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P123">
				<sentence xml:id="P123E0">Some camps tattooed prisoners with an identification number on arrival.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P123E1">Those fit for work were dispatched for <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">12- to 14-hour</ENAMEX> shifts.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P123E2">Roll calls before and after could sometimes last for hours; prisoners regularly died of exposure.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P124">
				<sentence xml:id="P124E0">Ghettos (<ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1939–1945</ENAMEX>)</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P125">
				<sentence xml:id="P125E0">Main articles: Ghettos in occupied  <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1939-1944</ENAMEX> and List of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazi</ENAMEX>-era ghettos</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P126">
				<sentence xml:id="P126E0"> Main ghettos: <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Białystok</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Budapest</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Kovno</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Łódź</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Lvov</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Riga</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Vilna</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Warsaw</ENAMEX></ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P127">
				<sentence xml:id="P127E0">A starving child lying in the streets of the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Warsaw Ghetto</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P128">
				<sentence xml:id="P128E0">After invading <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Poland</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazis</ENAMEX> established ghettos in the incorporated territories and <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">General Government</ENAMEX> to confine <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P128E1">The ghettos were formed and closed off from the outside world at different times and for different reasons.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P128E2">Ghettos were intended to be temporary until the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> were deported.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P128E3">But deportation never occurred.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P128E4">Instead, the ghettos&apos; inhabitants were sent to extermination camps.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P129">
				<sentence xml:id="P129E0"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> required each ghetto to be run by a <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">Judenrat</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">Jewish council</ENAMEX>)</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P129E1">The <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">first</ENAMEX> order establishing a council is contained in a <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">29 September 1939</ENAMEX> letter from <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Heydrich</ENAMEX> to the heads of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Einsatzgruppen</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P129E2">Councils were responsible for a ghetto&apos;s day-to-day operations, including distributing food, water, heat, medical care, and shelter.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P129E3">The <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Germans</ENAMEX> also required councils to confiscate property, organize forced labor, and, finally, facilitate deportations to extermination camps.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P129E4">The councils&apos; basic strategy was one of trying to minimise losses, largely by cooperating with <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazi</ENAMEX> authorities (or their surrogates), accepting the increasingly terrible treatment, bribery, petitioning for better conditions, and clemency.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P129E5">Overall, to try and mitigate still worse cruelty and death, &quot;the councils offered words, money, labor, and finally lives.&quot;</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P130">
				<sentence xml:id="P130E0">The ultimate test of each <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Judenrat</ENAMEX> was the demand to compile lists of names of deportees to be murdered.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P130E1">Though the predominant pattern was compliance with even this final task, some council leaders insisted that not a single individual should be handed over who had not committed a capital crime.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P130E2">Leaders who refused to compile a list, such as <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Joseph Parnas</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Lviv</ENAMEX>, were shot.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P130E3">On <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">14 October 1942</ENAMEX>, the entire council of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Byaroza</ENAMEX> committed suicide rather than cooperate with the deportations.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P130E4"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Adam Czerniaków</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Warsaw</ENAMEX> killed himself on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">23 July 1942</ENAMEX> when he could take no more as the final liquidation of the ghetto got under way.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P130E5">Others, like <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Chaim Rumkowski</ENAMEX>, who became the &quot;dedicated autocrat&quot; of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Łódź</ENAMEX>, argued that their responsibility was to save the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> who could be saved, and that therefore others had to be sacrificed.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P131">
				<sentence xml:id="P131E0">The councils&apos; importance in facilitating <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX>&apos;s persecution and murder of ghetto inhabitants was not lost on the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazis</ENAMEX>: one official was emphatic that &quot;the authority of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Jewish council</ENAMEX> be upheld and strengthened under all circumstances&quot;, another that &quot;<ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> who disobey instructions of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Jewish council</ENAMEX> are to be treated as saboteurs.&quot;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P131E1">When cooperation crumbled, as happened in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Warsaw ghetto</ENAMEX> after the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Jewish Combat Organisation</ENAMEX> displaced the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">council</ENAMEX>&apos;s authority, the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Germans</ENAMEX> lost control.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P132">
				<sentence xml:id="P132E0">Emaciated corpses of children in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Warsaw Ghetto</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P133">
				<sentence xml:id="P133E0">The <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Warsaw Ghetto</ENAMEX> was the largest, with <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">380,000</ENAMEX> people; the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Łódź Ghetto</ENAMEX> was <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">second</ENAMEX>, holding <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">160,000</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P133E1">They were, in effect, immensely crowded prisons serving as instruments of &quot;slow, passive murder.&quot;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P133E2">Though the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Warsaw Ghetto</ENAMEX> contained <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">30%</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Warsaw</ENAMEX>&apos;s population, it occupied only <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">2.4%</ENAMEX> of the city&apos;s area, averaging <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">9.2</ENAMEX> people per room.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P134">
				<sentence xml:id="P134E0">Between <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1940 and 1942</ENAMEX>, starvation and disease, especially typhoid, killed <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">hundreds of thousands</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P134E1">Over <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">43,000</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Warsaw ghetto</ENAMEX> residents, or <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">one in ten</ENAMEX> of the total population, died in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1941</ENAMEX>; in <ENAMEX type="INSTALLATION">Theresienstadt</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">more than half</ENAMEX> the residents died in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1942</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P135">
				<sentence xml:id="P135E0"> The <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Germans</ENAMEX> came, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">police</ENAMEX>, and they started banging houses: &quot;Raus, raus, raus, <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Juden raus</ENAMEX>.&quot;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P135E1">...</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P135E2">[O]ne baby started to cry ...</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P135E3">The other baby started crying.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P135E4">So the mother urinated in her hand and gave the baby a drink to keep quiet ...</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P135E5">[When the police had gone], I told the mothers to come out.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P135E6">And one baby was dead ...</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P135E7">from fear, the mother [had] choked her own baby.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P136">
				<sentence xml:id="P136E0"> — <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Abraham Malik</ENAMEX>, describing his experience in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Kovno Ghetto</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P137">
				<sentence xml:id="P137E0"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Himmler</ENAMEX> ordered the start of the deportations on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">19 July 1942</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX type="PERIOD"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">three days later</ENAMEX>, on <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">22 July</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, the deportations from the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Warsaw Ghetto</ENAMEX> began; over the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="MEASURE">next 52 days</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">until 12 September</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">300,000</ENAMEX> people from <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Warsaw</ENAMEX> alone were transported in freight trains to the <ENAMEX type="INSTALLATION">Treblinka extermination camp</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P137E1">Many other ghettos were completely depopulated.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P138">
				<sentence xml:id="P138E0">Further information: <ENAMEX subType="2" type="CREATION">Timeline of Treblinka</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P139">
				<sentence xml:id="P139E0">The <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">first</ENAMEX> ghetto uprising occurred in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">September 1942</ENAMEX> in the small town of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Łachwa</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">southeast Poland</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P139E1">Although there were armed resistance attempts in the larger ghettos in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1943</ENAMEX>, such as the <ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Warsaw Ghetto Uprising</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Białystok Ghetto Uprising</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, in every case they failed against the overwhelming <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazi</ENAMEX> military force, and the remaining <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> were either killed or deported to the death camps.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P140">
				<sentence xml:id="P140E0">Pogroms (<ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1939–1942</ENAMEX>)</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P141">
				<sentence xml:id="P141E0">Main articles: Pogrom, <ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Dorohoi Pogrom</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Iaşi pogrom</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Jedwabne Massacre</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Legionnaires&apos; Rebellion</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Bucharest Pogrom</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, History of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Lviv</ENAMEX> § <ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Lviv pogroms</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Holocaust</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Odessa massacre</ENAMEX></ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P142">
				<sentence xml:id="P142E0"><ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> woman chased by men and youth armed with clubs in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Lviv</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Ukraine</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">July 1941</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P143">
				<sentence xml:id="P143E0">A number of deadly pogroms occurred during the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Second World War</ENAMEX>. The <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazis</ENAMEX> encouraged some and others were spontaneous.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P143E1">Notable are the <ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Iaşi pogrom</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Romania</ENAMEX> on <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">30 June 1941</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, in which as many as <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">14,000</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> were killed by <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">Romanian</ENAMEX> residents and <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">police</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P143E2">In the infamous series of <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Lviv pogroms</ENAMEX> committed in occupied <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Poland</ENAMEX> by <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">nationalists</ENAMEX> from the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Ukrainian People&apos;s Militia</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Lwów</ENAMEX> (now, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Ukraine</ENAMEX>), some <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">6,000</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="NATIONAL">Polish</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> were murdered in the streets between <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">30 June and 29 July 1941</ENAMEX>, on top of <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">3,000</ENAMEX> arrests and mass shootings by <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Einsatzgruppe C.</ENAMEX> Other pogroms perpetrated by the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Ukrainian militia</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">Polish</ENAMEX> provincial capitals included <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Łuck</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Tarnopol</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P143E3">During the <ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Jedwabne pogrom</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">July 1941</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, in the presence of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Nazi Ordnungspolizei</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">300</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> were burned to death in a locked barn by local <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Poles</ENAMEX>, which was preceded by <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">German</ENAMEX> execution of <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">40</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> men at the same location.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P144">
				<sentence xml:id="P144E0">Death squads (<ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1941–1943</ENAMEX>)</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P145">
				<sentence xml:id="P145E0">Main articles: <ENAMEX type="EVENT">The <ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Holocaust in Ukraine</ENAMEX>, The <ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Holocaust in Lithuania</ENAMEX>, The <ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Holocaust in Latvia</ENAMEX>, The <ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Holocaust in Estonia</ENAMEX>, The <ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Holocaust in Belarus</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">The Holocaust in Russia</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Einsatzgruppen</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Mass graves in the Soviet Union</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="EVENT">War crimes of the Wehrmacht</ENAMEX>, and Collaboration with the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Axis Powers</ENAMEX> during <ENAMEX type="EVENT">World War II</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P146">
				<sentence xml:id="P146E0">See also: <ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Babi Yar</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Rumbula massacre</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Kamianets-Podilskyi Massacre</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">Ponary massacre</ENAMEX></ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P147">
				<sentence xml:id="P147E0"><ENAMEX type="EVENT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX>&apos;s <ENAMEX subType="2" type="EVENT">invasion of the Soviet Union</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">June 1941</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> opened a new phase in the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Holocaust</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P147E1">Even before the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">invasion of the Soviet Union</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> troops had been indoctrinated with <ENAMEX type="CONCEPTUAL"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="CONCEPTUAL">anti-Bolshevik</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="CONCEPTUAL">anti-Semitic</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="CONCEPTUAL">anti-Slavic</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> ideology via movies, radio, lectures, books and leaflets.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P147E2">Following the invasion, <ENAMEX type="TITLE">Wehrmacht officers</ENAMEX> told their soldiers to target people who were described as &quot;<ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish Bolshevik</ENAMEX> subhumans&quot;, the &quot;<ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Mongol</ENAMEX> hordes&quot;, the &quot;<ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Asiatic</ENAMEX> flood&quot; and the &quot;red beast&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P147E3"><ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazi</ENAMEX> propaganda portrayed the war against the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Soviet Union</ENAMEX> as both an ideological war between <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="CONCEPT">German National Socialism</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="CONCEPT">Jewish Bolshevism</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> and a racial war between the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Germans</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Bolsheviks</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Romani</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Slavic Untermenschen</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> (&quot;sub-humans&quot;).</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P147E4"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Hitler</ENAMEX> on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">30 March 1941</ENAMEX> described the war with the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Soviet Union</ENAMEX> as a &quot;war of annihilation&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P147E5">The pace of extermination intensified after the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Nazis</ENAMEX> occupied <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Lithuania</ENAMEX>, where close to <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">80%</ENAMEX> of the country&apos;s <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">220,000</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> were exterminated before year&apos;s end.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P147E6">The <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Soviet territories</ENAMEX> occupied by <ENAMEX type="PERIOD"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">early</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">1942</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, including all of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Belarus</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Estonia</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Latvia</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Lithuania</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Ukraine</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Moldova</ENAMEX> and most <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Russian territory</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">west of the line Leningrad–Moscow–Rostov</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, were inhabited at the start of the war by about <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">three million</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P148">
				<sentence xml:id="P148E0">Executions of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> by <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTIUTION">German army mobile killing units</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Einsatzgruppen</ENAMEX>)</ENAMEX> near <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Ivanhorod</ENAMEX>, now <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Ukraine</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P148E1">The photo was mailed from the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Eastern Front</ENAMEX> to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> and intercepted by a member of the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Polish resistance</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P149">
				<sentence xml:id="P149E0">Due to shortage of manpower, an order of <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">February 1943</ENAMEX> forbid anyone to characterize the peoples of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Eastern Europe</ENAMEX> as &quot;beasts,&quot; &quot;subhumans&quot; or other derogatory descriptions in order to gain their support in &quot;the struggle against <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Bolshevism</ENAMEX>.&quot;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P149E1">Local populations in some <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">occupied Soviet territories</ENAMEX> actively participated in the killings of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> and others.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P149E2">But it was ultimately the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Germans</ENAMEX> who organized and channelled these local efforts.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P149E3">Many of the collaborators who participated in the killings of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> enlisted in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Waffen-SS</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P149E4">In <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Lithuania</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Latvia</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">western Ukraine</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> locals were deeply involved in the murder of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> from the very beginning of the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">German occupation</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P149E5">The <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Latvian Arajs Kommando</ENAMEX> is an example of an auxiliary unit involved in these killings.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P149E6">Some of these <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="NATIONAL">Latvian</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="NATIONAL">Lithuanian</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> units left their own countries to murder <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Belarus</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P149E7">In the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">south</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Ukrainians</ENAMEX> killed about <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">24,000</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> and some went to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Poland</ENAMEX> to serve as concentration and death-camp guards.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P149E8"><ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">Ustaše militia</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Croatia</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> also persecuted and murdered <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX>, among others.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P150">
				<sentence xml:id="P150E0">Many of the mass killings were carried out in public, a change from previous practice.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P150E1"><ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> witnesses to these killings emphasized the locals&apos; participation.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P151">
				<sentence xml:id="P151E0">The mass killings of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> in the occupied <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Soviet territories</ENAMEX> was assigned to <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">SS</ENAMEX> formations called <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Einsatzgruppen</ENAMEX> (&quot;task groups&quot;), which were under <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Heydrich</ENAMEX>&apos;s overall command.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P151E1">These had been used to a limited extent in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Poland</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1939</ENAMEX>, but were organized in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Soviet territories</ENAMEX> on a much larger scale.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P151E2"><ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Einsatzgruppe A</ENAMEX> was assigned to the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Baltic area</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">Einsatzgruppe B</ENAMEX> to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Belarus</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">Einsatzgruppe C</ENAMEX> to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">north and central Ukraine</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">Einsatzgruppe D</ENAMEX> to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Moldova</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">south Ukraine</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Crimea</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, and, during <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1942</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">north Caucasus</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P151E3">The <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Einsatzgruppen</ENAMEX>&apos;s commanders were ordinary citizens: the great majority were professionals, most were intellectuals, and they brought to bear all their skills and training in becoming efficient killers.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P152">
				<sentence xml:id="P152E0">According to <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Otto Ohlendorf</ENAMEX> at his trial, &quot;the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Einsatzgruppen</ENAMEX> had the mission to protect the rear of the troops by killing the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Gypsies</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Communist</ENAMEX> functionaries, active <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Communists</ENAMEX>, and all persons who would endanger the security.&quot;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P152E1">In 
					practice, their victims were nearly all defenseless <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> civilians (not a single <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Einsatzgruppe</ENAMEX> member was killed in action during these operations).</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P152E2">By <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">December 1941</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">four</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Einsatzgruppen</ENAMEX> had killed, respectively, <ENAMEX type="MEASURE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="MEASURE">125,000</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="MEASURE">45,000</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="MEASURE">75,000</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="MEASURE">55,000</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> people—a total of <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">300,000</ENAMEX> people—mainly by shooting or with hand grenades at mass-killing sites outside the major towns.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P153">
				<sentence xml:id="P153E0">The <ENAMEX type="INSTALLATION">United States Holocaust Memorial Museum</ENAMEX> provides the account of <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">one</ENAMEX> survivor of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Einsatzgruppen</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Piryatin</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Ukraine</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, where the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Germans</ENAMEX> killed <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">1,600</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">6 April 1942</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERIOD">the second day of Passover</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>:</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P154">
				<sentence xml:id="P154E0"> I saw them do the killing.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P154E1">At <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">5:00 pm</ENAMEX> they gave the command, &quot;Fill in the pits.&quot;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P154E2">Screams and groans were coming from the pits.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P154E3">Suddenly I saw my neighbor <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Ruderman</ENAMEX> rise from under the soil ...</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P154E4">His eyes were bloody and he was screaming: &quot;Finish me off!&quot;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P154E5">...</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P154E6">A murdered woman lay at my feet.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P154E7">A boy of <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">five</ENAMEX> years crawled out from under her body and began to scream desperately.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P154E8">&quot;Mommy!&quot;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P154E9">That was all I saw, since I fell unconscious.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P155">
				<sentence xml:id="P155E0">The most notorious massacre of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Soviet Union</ENAMEX> was at a ravine called <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Babi Yar</ENAMEX> outside <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Kiev</ENAMEX>, where <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">33,771</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> were killed in a single operation on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">29–3 September 1941</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P155E1">The decision to kill all the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Kiev</ENAMEX> was made by the military governor <ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">Major-General</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Friedrich Eberhardt</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">Police Commander</ENAMEX> for <ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">Army Group South SS</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">Obergruppenführer</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Friedrich Jeckeln</ENAMEX>, and the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">Einsatzgruppe C</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">Commander</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Otto Rasch</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P155E2">A mixture of <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">SS</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">SD</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">Security Police</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, assisted by <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Ukrainian police</ENAMEX>, carried out the killings.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P155E3">Although they did not participate in the killings, men of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">6th Army</ENAMEX> played a key role in rounding up the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Kiev</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> and transporting them to be shot at <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Babi Yar</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P156">
				<sentence xml:id="P156E0">On <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">29 September</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Kiev&apos;s Jews</ENAMEX> gathered by the cemetery as ordered, expecting to be loaded onto trains.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P156E1">The crowd was large enough that most of the men, women, and children could not have known what was happening until it was too late; by the time they heard the machine gun fire, there was no chance to escape.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P156E2">All were driven down a corridor of soldiers, in groups of <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">ten</ENAMEX>, and shot.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P157">
				<sentence xml:id="P157E0"> one after the other, they had to remove their luggage, then their coats, shoes, and outer garments and also underwear ...</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P157E1">Once undressed, they were led into the ravine which was about <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">150 meters</ENAMEX> long and <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">30 meters</ENAMEX> wide and a good <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">15 meters</ENAMEX> deep ...</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P157E2">When they reached the bottom of the ravine they were seized by members of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Schutzpolizei</ENAMEX> and made to lie down on top of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> who had already been shot ...</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P157E3">The corpses were literally in layers.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P157E4">A police marksman came along and shot each <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jew</ENAMEX> in the neck with a submachine gun ...</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P157E5">I saw these marksmen stand on layers of corpses and shoot one after the other ...</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P157E6">The marksman would walk across the bodies of the executed <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> to the next <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jew</ENAMEX>, who had meanwhile lain down, and shoot him.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P158">
				<sentence xml:id="P158E0">From left to right; <ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Heinrich Himmler</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Reinhard Heydrich</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Karl Wolff</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> (second from the right) at the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Obersalzberg</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">May 1939</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P158E1"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Wolff</ENAMEX> wrote in his diary that <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Himmler</ENAMEX> had vomited after witnessing the mass shooting of <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">100</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P159">
				<sentence xml:id="P159E0">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">August 1941</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Himmler</ENAMEX> travelled to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Minsk</ENAMEX>, where he personally witnessed <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">100</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> being shot in a ditch outside the town.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P159E1"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Karl Wolff</ENAMEX> described the event in his diary: &quot;<ENAMEX type="PERSON">Himmler</ENAMEX>&apos;s face was green.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P159E2">He took out his handkerchief and wiped his cheek where a piece of brain had squirted up onto it.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P159E3">Then he vomited.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P159E4">After recovering his composure, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Himmler</ENAMEX> lectured the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">SS</ENAMEX> men on the need to follow the &quot;highest moral law of the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Party</ENAMEX>&quot; in carrying out their tasks.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P160">
				<sentence xml:id="P160E0"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> usually justified the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Einsatzgruppen</ENAMEX>&apos;s massacres on the grounds of <ENAMEX type="CONCEPTUAL"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="CONCEPTUAL">anti-Bolshevik</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="CONCEPTUAL">anti-partisan</ENAMEX> or <ENAMEX subType="2" type="CONCEPTUAL">anti-bandit</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> operations, but the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> historian <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Andreas Hillgruber</ENAMEX> wrote that this was merely an excuse for the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">German Army</ENAMEX>&apos;s considerable involvement in the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Holocaust in Russia</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P160E1">He wrote in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1989</ENAMEX> that the terms &quot;war crimes&quot; and &quot;crimes against humanity&quot; were indeed correct labels for what happened.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P160E2"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Hillgruber</ENAMEX> maintained that the slaughter of about <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">2.2 million</ENAMEX> defenseless men, women, and children based on a <ENAMEX type="CONCEPTUAL">racist</ENAMEX> ideology cannot possibly be justified for any reason, and that those <ENAMEX type="TITLE">German generals</ENAMEX> who claimed that the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Einsatzgruppen</ENAMEX> were a necessary anti-partisan response were lying.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P161">
				<sentence xml:id="P161E0"><ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Army</ENAMEX> co-operation with the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">SS</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="CONCEPTUAL"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="CONCEPTUAL">anti-Bolshevik</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="CONCEPTUAL">anti-partisan</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="CONCEPTUAL">anti-Jewish</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> operations was close and intensive.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P161E1">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">mid-1941</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">SS Cavalry Brigade</ENAMEX>, commanded by <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Hermann Fegelein</ENAMEX>, killed <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">699</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Red Army</ENAMEX> soldiers, <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">1,100</ENAMEX> partisans, and <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">14,178</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> during the course of &quot;anti-partisan&quot; operations in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Pripyat Marshes</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P161E2">Before the operation, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Fegelein</ENAMEX> had been ordered to shoot all adult <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> and herd the women and children into the marshes.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P161E3">After the operation, <ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">General</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Max von Schenckendorff</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, who commanded the rear areas of <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Army Group Center</ENAMEX>, ordered that all <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Wehrmacht</ENAMEX> security divisions should emulate <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Fegelein</ENAMEX>&apos;s example when on <ENAMEX type="CONCEPTUAL">anti-partisan</ENAMEX> duty, and organized a joint <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">SS</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX subType="2" type="INSTITUTION">Wehrmacht</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> seminar on how best to kill <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P161E4">The seminar ended with the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">7th Company</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">Police Battalion 322</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> shooting <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">32</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> before the assembled <ENAMEX type="TITLE">officers</ENAMEX> at a village called <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Knjashizy</ENAMEX> as an example of how to &quot;screen&quot; the population for <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">partisans</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P162">
				<sentence xml:id="P162E0">As the war diary of the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Battalion 322</ENAMEX> read:</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P163">
				<sentence xml:id="P163E0"> The action, first scheduled as a training exercise, was carried out under real-life conditions (ernstfallmässig) in the village itself.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P163E1">Strangers, especially partisans could not be found.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P164">
				<sentence xml:id="P164E0"><ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">German police</ENAMEX> shooting women and children from the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Mizocz Ghetto</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">14 October 1942</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P165">
				<sentence xml:id="P165E0">Based on what they had learned during the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Mogilev</ENAMEX> seminar, <ENAMEX type="TITLE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="MEASURE">one</ENAMEX><ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">Wehrmacht officer</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> told his men: &quot;Where the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">partisan</ENAMEX> is, there is the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jew</ENAMEX> and where the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jew</ENAMEX> is, there is the partisan&quot;.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P166">
				<sentence xml:id="P166E0"><ENAMEX type="PERSON"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">Head of the OKW</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">Field-Marshal</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON">Wilhelm Keitel</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, in an order on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">12 September 1941</ENAMEX>, declared:</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P167">
				<sentence xml:id="P167E0"> The struggle against <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Bolshevism</ENAMEX> demands ruthless and energetic, rigorous action above all against the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX>, the main carriers of <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Bolshevism</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P168">
				<sentence xml:id="P168E0">In Order No. 24 <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">24 November 1941</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="TITLE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="TITLE">commander</ENAMEX> of the <ENAMEX subType="2" type="ORGANISATION">707th</ENAMEX></ENAMEX> division declared:</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P169">
				<sentence xml:id="P169E0"> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX subType="2" type="PERSON_TYPE">Gypsies</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>:...As already has been ordered, the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> have to vanish from the flat country and the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Gypsies</ENAMEX> have to be annihilated too.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P169E1">The carrying out of larger <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jewish</ENAMEX> actions is not the task of the divisional units.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P169E2">They are carried out by civilian or police authorities, if necessary ordered by the commandant of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">White Ruthenia</ENAMEX>, if he has special units at his disposal, or for security reasons and in the case of collective punishments.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P169E3">When smaller or larger groups of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> are met in the flat country, they can be liquidated by divisional units or be massed in the ghettos near bigger villages designated for that purpose, where they can be handed over to the civilian authority or the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">SD</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P170">
				<sentence xml:id="P170E0"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Jürgen Förster</ENAMEX>, a leading expert on the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Wehrmacht</ENAMEX>&apos;s war crimes, argued that the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Wehrmacht</ENAMEX> played a key role in the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Holocaust</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P170E1">He said it is wrong to describe the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Shoah</ENAMEX> as solely the work of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">SS</ENAMEX> with the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Wehrmacht</ENAMEX> as a passive and disapproving bystander.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P171">
				<sentence xml:id="P171E0">The mass murder of <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">2,749</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> on the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION"><ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">beach near the city of Liepāja</ENAMEX>, in <ENAMEX subType="2" type="LOCATION">Latvia</ENAMEX></ENAMEX>, on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">15–17 December 1941</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P172">
				<sentence xml:id="P172E0">New methods of mass murder</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P173">
