File	O
1	B-MEASURE
.	O
Policy	O
guidelines	O
for	O
"	O
cultural	O
"	O
events	O
.	O
Reports	O
on	O
cultural	O
activities	O
(	O
most	O
of	O
the	O
documents	O
in	O
German	B-NATIONAL
)	O
.	B-MEASURE
2	B-MEASURE
.	B-MEASURE
09	B-MEASURE
.	O
1942	B-PERIOD
-	B-PERIOD
1	PERIOD
.	PERIOD
04	PERIOD
.	PERIOD
1944	PERIOD
.	O
219	B-MEASURE
pages	O
.	O
File	O
2	B-MEASURE
.	O
Article	O
by	O
Bykovich	B-PERSON
in	O
"	O
Commonwealth	B-CREATION
in	B-CREATION
-	CREATION
arms	O
"	O
newspaper	O
for	O
volunteers	O
(	O
No	O
.	O
2	B-MEASURE
from	O
11	B-MEASURE
.	B-MEASURE
12	B-MEASURE
.	O
1944	B-PERIOD
)	O
entitled	O
"	O
The	O
Destruction	O
of	O
the	O
center	O
of	O
the	O
bandit	O
movement	O
in	O
Crimea	B-LOCATION
.	O
Release	O
of	O
the	O
civilian	O
population	O
from	O
prison	O
.	O
"	O
International	O
information	O
for	O
February	B-PERIOD
1944	B-PERIOD
(	O
in	O
German	B-NATIONAL
)	O
.	O
1944	O
.	B-MEASURE
108	B-MEASURE
pages	O
.	O
File	O
3	B-MEASURE
.	O
Reports	O
of	O
an	O
international	O
character	O
(	O
in	O
German	B-NATIONAL
)	O
.	O
1944	B-PERIOD
.	O
File	O
4	B-MEASURE
.	O
Short	O
essay	O
about	O
Soviet	O
Russia	B-LOCATION
(	O
in	O
German	B-NATIONAL
)	O
.	O
1944	O
.	B-MEASURE
134	B-MEASURE
pages	O
.	O
File	O
5	B-MEASURE
.	O
Reviews	O
and	O
articles	O
for	O
newspapers	O
published	O
during	O
the	O
German	B-NATIONAL
occupation	O
.	B-MEASURE
155	B-MEASURE
pages	O
.	O
File	O
6	B-MEASURE
.	O
I	O
.	O
F	B-PERSON
.	B-PERSON
Lyubitsky	B-PERSON
book	O
"	O
Some	O
of	O
the	O
old	O
memories	O
.	O
"	O
Volume	O
1	B-MEASURE
.	O
1942	O
.	B-MEASURE
142	B-MEASURE
pages	O
.	O
File	O
7	B-MEASURE
.	O
I	O
.	O
F	B-PERSON
.	B-PERSON
Lyubitsky	B-PERSON
book	O
"	O
Some	O
of	O
the	O
old	O
memories	O
.	O
"	O
Volume	O
2	B-MEASURE
.	O
1942	B-PERIOD
.	B-MEASURE
139	B-MEASURE
pages	O
.	O
