The	O
history	O
of	O
the	O
Archive	O
can	O
be	O
divided	O
into	O
four	O
periods	O
:	O
the	O
first	O
,	O
from	O
1919	B-PERIOD
-	O
1940	B-PERIOD
,	O
during	O
the	O
time	O
of	O
Lithuanian	B-NATIONAL
independence	O
following	O
World	B-EVENT
War	B-EVENT
I	O
;	O
the	O
second	O
,	O
from	O
1941	B-PERIOD
-	O
1944	B-PERIOD
,	O
during	O
the	O
time	O
of	O
the	O
Nazi	B-NATIONAL
occupation	O
of	O
Lithuania	B-LOCATION
;	O
the	O
third	O
from	O
1944	B-PERIOD
-	B-PERIOD
1991	B-PERIOD
,	O
under	O
the	O
Soviet	B-NATIONAL
regime	O
;	O
and	O
the	O
fourth	O
and	O
current	O
period	O
,	O
during	O
the	O
time	O
of	O
independence	O
from	O
1991	B-PERIOD
to	O
the	O
present	O
.	O
The	O
first	O
period	O
was	O
the	O
time	O
of	O
the	O
foundation	O
and	O
establishment	O
of	O
the	O
government	O
institutions	O
and	O
the	O
formulation	O
of	O
work	O
procedures	O
.	O
During	O
this	O
period	O
of	O
time	O
,	O
the	O
Constitution	O
was	O
accepted	O
,	O
as	O
well	O
as	O
additional	O
legislation	O
to	O
regulate	O
life	O
in	O
the	O
renewed	O
country	O
and	O
preserve	O
the	O
national	O
heritage	O
.	O
Thus	O
,	O
the	O
Central	B-ORGANISATION
National	B-ORGANISATION
Archives	ORGANISATION
were	O
set	O
up	O
in	O
Kaunas	B-LOCATION
,	O
the	O
capital	O
of	O
Lithuania	B-LOCATION
at	O
that	O
time	O
.	O
In	O
1921	B-PERIOD
,	O
a	O
peace	O
treaty	O
was	O
signed	O
between	O
Soviet	B-LOCATION
Russia	B-LOCATION
and	O
Lithuania	B-LOCATION
facilitating	O
the	O
return	O
to	O
Kaunas	B-LOCATION
of	O
many	O
documents	O
that	O
had	O
been	O
taken	O
to	O
Russia	B-LOCATION
during	O
the	O
Czarist	B-CONCEPTUAL
regime	O
.	O
During	O
the	O
second	O
period	O
under	O
the	O
Nazi	B-CONCEPTUAL
rule	O
,	O
the	O
Archive	O
continued	O
to	O
be	O
active	O
,	O
albeit	O
under	O
certain	O
restrictions	O
.	O
The	O
Archive	O
was	O
subject	O
to	O
Reichskommissariat	B-PERSON
Ostland	B-PERSON
,	O
and	O
was	O
only	O
open	O
to	O
visitors	O
of	O
German	B-NATIONAL
origin	O
.	O
In	O
actuality	O
,	O
the	O
ongoing	O
responsibility	O
for	O
the	O
Archives	O
was	O
under	O
the	O
control	O
of	O
the	O
Office	B-ORGANISATION
for	B-ORGANISATION
Internal	B-ORGANISATION
Affairs	B-ORGANISATION
,	O
which	O
was	O
located	O
in	O
Kaunas	B-LOCATION
.	O
The	O
third	O
period	O
has	O
been	O
divided	O
in	O
two	O
.	O
In	O
1940	B-PERIOD
,	O
following	O
the	O
invasion	O
by	O
the	O
Soviet	B-LOCATION
Union	B-LOCATION
,	O
the	O
Archives	B-ORGANISATION
administration	O
was	O
transferred	O
to	O
Vilnius	B-LOCATION
.	O
From	O
an	O
organizational	O
point	O
of	O
view	O
,	O
the	O
Archives	O
were	O
now	O
under	O
the	O
supervision	O
of	O
the	O
NKVD	B-ORGANISATION
.	O
The	O
confidential	O
documents	O
were	O
transferred	O
to	O
the	O
Soviet	B-LOCATION
Union	B-LOCATION
and	O
afterwards	O
were	O
only	O
partially	O
returned	O
.	O
Even	O
after	O
World	B-EVENT
War	B-EVENT
II	EVENT
,	O
the	O
Archives	O
remained	O
under	O
the	O
supervision	O
of	O
the	O
NKVD	B-ORGANISATION
;	O
in	O
1960	B-PERIOD
,	O
the	O
Archives	O
was	O
transferred	O
to	O
the	O
supervision	O
of	O
the	O
National	B-ORGANISATION
Council	B-ORGANISATION
of	ORGANISATION
Soviet	ORGANISATION
Union	ORGANISATION
Archives	ORGANISATION
.	O
The	O
current	O
period	O
began	O
with	O
the	O
enactment	O
of	O
the	O
Archives	O
Law	O
.	O
The	O
name	O
of	O
the	O
main	O
Archives	O
was	O
changed	O
to	O
the	O
Lithuanian	B-ORGANISATION
Central	B-ORGANISATION
State	ORGANISATION
Archives	ORGANISATION
,	O
and	O
the	O
Archives	O
were	O
transferred	O
to	O
the	O
supervision	O
of	O
the	O
Central	B-ORGANISATION
Archives	B-ORGANISATION
administration	O
which	O
is	O
subject	O
to	O
the	O
Lithuanian	B-ORGANISATION
Council	B-ORGANISATION
of	ORGANISATION
Ministers	ORGANISATION
.	O
The	O
Archives	B-BUSINESS
deal	O
with	O
archival	O
documentation	O
created	O
between	O
1918	B-PERIOD
and	O
1990	B-PERIOD
,	O
as	O
well	O
as	O
documents	O
,	O
films	O
,	O
photographs	O
and	O
recordings	O
that	O
are	O
a	O
part	O
of	O
the	O
Lithuanian	B-NATIONAL
cultural	O
data	O
base	O
.	O
The	O
activities	O
of	O
the	O
Archives	O
have	O
been	O
arranged	O
in	O
accordance	O
with	O
the	O
Lithuanian	B-NATIONAL
Constitution	B-NATIONAL
,	O
European	B-ORGANISATION
Union	B-ORGANISATION
legislation	O
,	O
and	O
additional	O
laws	O
that	O
regulate	O
the	O
activities	O
of	O
the	O
Archives	B-BUSINESS
as	O
a	O
public	O
government	O
office	O
.	O
The	O
Archives	B-BUSINESS
preserves	O
records	O
of	O
state	O
,	O
local	O
government	O
,	O
enterprises	O
,	O
religious	O
communities	O
,	O
popular	O
organizations	O
,	O
other	O
non	O
-	O
state	O
institutions	O
and	O
individuals	O
,	O
dating	O
from	O
1918	B-PERIOD
until	O
1990	B-PERIOD
.	O
The	O
division	O
of	O
Sound	O
and	O
Image	O
is	O
the	O
main	O
repository	O
of	O
audiovisual	O
heritage	O
in	O
Lithuania	B-LOCATION
.	O
It	O
preserves	O
moving	O
pictures	O
since	O
1919	B-PERIOD
,	O
photo	O
negatives	O
and	O
positives	O
since	O
1850	B-PERIOD
'	O
s	O
,	O
sound	O
recordings	O
since	O
1950	B-PERIOD
'	O
s	O
,	O
videotapes	O
since	O
1988	B-PERIOD
until	O
the	O
present	O
day	O
.	O
Archives	O
’	O
holdings	O
comprise	O
of	O
approximately	O
31	B-MEASURE
000	B-MEASURE
linear	O
meters	O
of	O
records	O
.	O
"	O
The	O
archive	O
contains	O
177	O
collections	O
from	O
the	O
Nazi	B-PERSON
occupation	O
period	O
(	O
a	O
total	O
of	O
72	B-MEASURE
189	B-MEASURE
items	O
i	O
.	O
e	O
.	O
files	O
)	O
.	O
They	O
are	O
collections	O
of	O
the	O
documents	O
of	O
the	O
civil	O
government	O
,	O
offices	O
,	O
military	O
offices	O
and	O
police	O
stations	O
and	O
their	O
branches	O
,	O
industrial	O
,	O
transport	O
and	O
other	O
companies	O
and	O
offices	O
of	O
the	O
Nazi	B-PERSON
period	O
.	O
"	O
Approximately	O
390	B-MEASURE
,	B-MEASURE
000	B-MEASURE
photographic	O
documents	O
(	O
middle	O
of	O
the	O
19th	B-MEASURE
c	MEASURE
.	O
–	O
until	O
nowadays	O
)	O
:	O
photographs	O
,	O
negatives	O
,	O
photographic	O
glass	O
plates	O
,	O
albums	O
,	O
vignettes	O
,	O
slides	O
,	O
digital	O
pictures	O
;	O
works	O
of	O
A	O
.	O
Strauss	B-PERSON
,	O
J	B-PERSON
.	PERSON
Čechavičius	PERSON
,	O
A	B-PERSON
.	PERSON
Fleury	PERSON
,	O
V	B-PERSON
.	PERSON
Zatorskis	PERSON
;	O
photographic	O
documents	O
by	O
J	B-PERSON
.	B-PERSON
Bulhakas	B-PERSON
,	O
M	B-PERSON
.	B-PERSON
Smečechauskas	B-PERSON
,	O
J	O
.	B-PERSON
Karazija	B-PERSON
,	O
J	B-PERSON
.	PERSON
Miežlaiškis	PERSON
,	O
B	B-BUSINESS
.	B-BUSINESS
Buračas	B-BUSINESS
,	O
A	O
.	O
Varnas	B-PERSON
,	O
A	B-PERSON
.	PERSON
Mickus	PERSON
,	O
V	B-PERSON
.	PERSON
Janiselis	PERSON
.	O
The	O
Soviet	B-NATIONAL
period	O
is	O
reflected	O
in	O
thephotographic	O
material	O
of	O
the	O
Lithuanian	B-MEDIA
News	B-MEDIA
Agency	MEDIA
ELTA	MEDIA
and	O
editorial	O
offices	O
of	O
newspapers	O
;	O
numerous	O
collections	O
of	O
documentary	O
photography	O
works	O
of	O
J	B-BUSINESS
.	B-BUSINESS
Juknevičius	BUSINESS
,	O
V	B-PERSON
.	PERSON
Kapočius	PERSON
,	O
A	B-PERSON
.	PERSON
Žižiūnas	PERSON
.	O
Modern	O
-	O
day	O
documentary	O
photographs	O
are	O
also	O
being	O
accumulated	O
.	O
Approximately	O
20	B-MEASURE
,	B-MEASURE
000	B-MEASURE
audio	O
documents	O
:	O
sound	O
recordings	O
on	O
gramophone	O
records	O
,	O
magnetic	O
tape	O
,	O
audio	O
cassettes	O
,	O
CDs	O
.	O
The	O
oldest	O
sound	O
record	O
is	O
a	O
series	O
of	O
songs	O
performed	O
by	O
Lithuanian	B-NATIONAL
male	O
quartet	O
from	O
Riga	B-LOCATION
and	O
recorded	O
in	O
Riga	B-LOCATION
in	O
1907	B-PERIOD
.	O
There	O
are	O
also	O
voice	O
recordings	O
of	O
the	O
presidents	O
of	O
Lithuania	B-LOCATION
A	O
.	O
Smetona	B-PERSON
and	O
K	B-PERSON
.	B-PERSON
Grinius	B-PERSON
,	O
audio	O
recordings	O
testifying	O
the	O
events	O
of	O
1940	B-PERIOD
in	O
Lithuania	B-LOCATION
;	O
a	O
collection	O
of	O
recordings	O
of	O
Kaunas	B-PERSON
Radiophone	B-PERSON
(	O
Radio	O
of	O
the	O
Reich	O
)	O
programmes	O
relating	O
to	O
the	O
war	O
period	O
;	O
public	O
speeches	O
of	O
Lithuanian	B-NATIONAL
functionaries	O
of	O
the	O
Soviet	B-NATIONAL
period	O
;	O
recordings	O
of	O
conventions	O
of	O
various	O
organizations	O
and	O
official	O
celebrations	O
of	O
state	O
holidays	O
;	O
recordings	O
of	O
Vilnius	B-BUSINESS
Recording	B-BUSINESS
Studio	BUSINESS
;	O
voice	O
recordings	O
of	O
representatives	O
of	O
Lithuanian	B-NATIONAL
Reform	O
Movement	O
Sąjūdis	B-PERSON
,	O
scientists	O
,	O
artists	O
,	O
politicians	O
,	O
Lithuanian	B-NATIONAL
expatriates	O
,	O
former	O
political	O
prisoners	O
and	O
deportees	O
;	O
recordings	O
of	O
the	O
programmes	O
of	O
Lithuanian	B-NATIONAL
radio	O
service	O
in	O
the	O
USA	B-LOCATION
and	O
Australia	B-LOCATION
;	O
recordings	O
the	O
Voice	B-ORGANISATION
of	B-ORGANISATION
America	ORGANISATION
Lithuanian	ORGANISATION
Radio	ORGANISATION
Service	ORGANISATION
of	O
1951	B-PERIOD
–	O
1995	B-PERIOD
;	O
Over	O
3	B-MEASURE
,	B-MEASURE
000	B-MEASURE
video	O
documents	O
.	O
Accumulation	O
of	O
video	O
recordings	O
started	O
in	O
1988	B-PERIOD
.	O
They	O
were	O
mostly	O
video	O
clips	O
filmed	O
by	O
cameramen	O
of	O
the	O
Archives	O
.	O
They	O
testify	O
to	O
the	O
activities	O
of	O
the	O
National	B-ORGANISATION
Liberation	B-ORGANISATION
Movement	ORGANISATION
Sąjūdis	ORGANISATION
,	O
the	O
restoration	O
of	O
independence	O
of	O
Lithuania	B-LOCATION
,	O
the	O
events	O
of	O
January	B-PERIOD
1991	B-PERIOD
.	O
There	O
are	O
also	O
video	O
recordings	O
of	O
reminiscences	O
of	O
the	O
former	O
deportees	O
,	O
political	O
prisoners	O
,	O
partisans	O
submitted	O
to	O
the	O
Archives	O
by	O
the	O
Lithuanian	B-BUSINESS
National	B-BUSINESS
Foundation	BUSINESS
,	BUSINESS
Inc	BUSINESS
;	O
Approximately	O
9	B-MEASURE
,	B-MEASURE
000	B-MEASURE
cinematographic	O
documents	O
(	O
1910s	O
–	B-MEASURE
to	O
date	O
)	O
.	O
Copies	O
of	O
the	O
films	O
made	O
by	O
the	O
Lumieres	B-PERSON
in	O
1895	O
–	O
the	O
earliest	O
films	O
ever	O
made	O
–	O
are	O
preserved	O
in	O
the	O
Archives	O
.	O
There	O
is	O
also	O
a	O
collection	O
of	O
the	O
Lithuanian	B-NATIONAL
newsreels	O
from	O
1918	B-PERIOD
–	B-PERIOD
1940	B-PERIOD
and	O
the	O
works	O
of	O
the	O
first	O
Lithuanian	B-NATIONAL
cameramen	O
–	O
K	B-PERSON
.	B-PERSON
Lukšys	B-PERSON
,	O
J	B-PERSON
.	PERSON
Milius	PERSON
,	O
brothers	O
Motūza	B-BUSINESS
-	B-BUSINESS
Beleckas	BUSINESS
,	O
S	B-PERSON
.	B-PERSON
Vainalavičius	B-PERSON
,	O
S	B-PERSON
.	B-PERSON
Uzdonas	B-PERSON
and	O
J	B-PERSON
.	PERSON
Miežlaiškis	PERSON
;	O
cinematographic	O
material	O
relating	O
to	O
the	O
World	B-EVENT
War	B-EVENT
II	EVENT
period	O
;	O
documentaries	O
made	O
in	O
the	O
Lithuanian	B-CONCEPT
Film	B-CONCEPT
Studios	CONCEPT
and	CONCEPT
Lithuanian	CONCEPT
Television	CONCEPT
in	O
1946	B-PERIOD
–	B-PERIOD
1990	B-PERIOD
;	O
the	O
first	O
Lithuanian	B-NATIONAL
feature	O
films	O
"	O
Blue	B-CREATION
Horizon	B-CREATION
"	O
(	O
Žydrasis	B-PERSON
horizontas	O
)	O
,	O
"	O
The	B-CREATION
Bridge	B-CREATION
"	O
(	O
Tiltas	B-PERSON
)	O
,	O
"	O
Ignotas	B-CREATION
Returned	B-CREATION
Home	CREATION
"	O
(	O
Ignotas	B-PERSON
grįžo	O
namo	O
)	O
,	O
"	O
The	B-CREATION
Turkeys	B-CREATION
"	O
(	O
Kalakutai	B-ARTIFACT
)	O
,	O
and	O
others	O
.	O
Galina	B-PERSON
Žirikova	B-PERSON
,	O
Lietuvos	B-PERSON
centrinio	B-PERSON
valstybės	O
archyvo	O
fondai	O
:	O
holokausto	O
Lietuvoje	B-PERSON
tyrimo	O
šaltinis	O
(	O
The	O
Collections	O
of	O
the	O
State	O
Archive	O
of	O
Lithuania	B-LOCATION
:	O
a	O
Source	O
of	O
Research	O
on	O
the	O
Holocaust	B-BUSINESS
in	O
Lithuania	B-LOCATION
)	O
,	O
Vilnius	B-LOCATION
,	O
Valstybinis	B-PERSON
Vilniaus	B-PERSON
Gaono	PERSON
žydų	O
muziejus	O
,	O
2011	B-PERIOD
.	O
Monday	B-PERIOD
–	O
Thursday	B-PERIOD
09	PERIOD
:	PERIOD
00	PERIOD
–	PERIOD
17	PERIOD
:	O
00	B-PERIOD
Friday	B-PERIOD
09	B-ARTIFACT
:	ARTIFACT
00	ARTIFACT
–	ARTIFACT
15	ARTIFACT
:	ARTIFACT
45	ARTIFACT
Lunch	ARTIFACT
Break	O
:	O
12	B-IDENTIFIER
:	IDENTIFIER
00	IDENTIFIER
–	IDENTIFIER
12	IDENTIFIER
:	IDENTIFIER
45	IDENTIFIER
