The	O
files	O
concern	O
anti	O
-	O
semitic	O
posters	O
from	O
April	B-PERIOD
1942	B-PERIOD
(	O
"	O
Jews	B-PERSON
are	O
your	O
deadly	O
enemy	O
"	O
)	O
;	O
confiscation	O
of	O
Jewish	B-NATIONAL
property	O
and	O
adaptation	O
for	O
such	O
property	O
for	O
public	O
use	O
(	O
for	O
example	O
:	O
the	O
synagogue	O
was	O
adapted	O
for	O
police	O
purposes	O
)	O
;	O
the	O
report	O
of	O
the	O
chief	O
of	O
the	O
county	O
concerning	O
registration	O
by	O
doctors	O
Aryan	B-NATIONAL
origins	O
all	O
cases	O
of	O
deaths	O
of	O
Jews	B-LOCATION
in	O
August	B-PERIOD
1942	B-PERIOD
;	O
the	O
main	O
instructions	O
for	O
how	O
settlements	O
in	O
the	O
county	O
were	O
to	O
deal	O
with	O
Jews	B-PERSON
,	O
how	O
they	O
were	O
to	O
forced	O
Jews	B-PERSON
to	O
work	O
,	O
how	O
they	O
were	O
to	O
confiscate	O
and	O
register	O
private	O
property	O
of	O
Jews	B-BUSINESS
from	O
September	B-PERIOD
1941	B-PERIOD
.	O
Entry	O
written	O
by	O
Neringa	B-PERSON
based	O
on	O
survey	O
.	O
Entry	O
updated	O
by	O
Neringa	B-PERSON
on	O
19	B-PERIOD
March	B-PERIOD
2015	B-PERIOD
.	O
