<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<corpus>
	<subcorpus>
		<document name="EHRI_unit_il-002798-o_32-61.en">
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P0">
				<sentence xml:id="P0E0">Documentation of the murder of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews of Crimea</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1941-1942</ENAMEX> Excerpts of documents of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Soviet Extraordinary State Commission (ChGK) in the Crimean occupied territory</ENAMEX>, including information regarding the murder of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Yevpatoria, Zuya, Kheyrus and Biyuk-Onlar</ENAMEX>, names of those who perished, <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">January-March 1942</ENAMEX>; notice from the <ENAMEX type="TITLE">mayor of Simferopol</ENAMEX> regarding housing for <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">15 March 1942</ENAMEX>; Ausweis (identity card) of <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Foma Paskitovski</ENAMEX>, from <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Kerch</ENAMEX>; copy of a photograph of a cell in the <ENAMEX type="INSTALLATION">Kerch jail</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">December 1941</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
		</document>
	</subcorpus>
</corpus>
