<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<corpus>
	<subcorpus>
		<document name="Wikipedia_worldWarZ">
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P0">
				<sentence xml:id="P0E0"><ENAMEX type="CREATION">World War Z: An Oral History of the Zombie War (2006)</ENAMEX> is an apocalyptic horror novel by <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Max Brooks</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E1">The novel is a collection of individual accounts narrated by an agent of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">United Nations Postwar Commission</ENAMEX>, following the devastating global conflict against the zombie plague.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E2">Other passages record a decade-long desperate struggle, as experienced by people of various nationalities.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E3">The personal accounts also describe the resulting social, political, religious, and environmental changes.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P1">
				<sentence xml:id="P1E0"><ENAMEX type="CREATION">World War Z</ENAMEX> is a follow-up to <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Brooks</ENAMEX>&apos; &quot;survival manual&quot; <ENAMEX type="CREATION">The Zombie Survival Guide (2003)</ENAMEX>, but its tone is much more serious.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P1E1">It was inspired by <ENAMEX type="CREATION">The Good War: An Oral History of World War Two (1984)</ENAMEX> by <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Studs Terkel</ENAMEX>, and by the zombie films of <ENAMEX type="PERSON">George A. Romero</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P1E2"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Brooks</ENAMEX> used <ENAMEX type="CREATION">World War Z</ENAMEX> to comment on government ineptitude and <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">American isolationism</ENAMEX>, while also examining <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">survivalism</ENAMEX> and uncertainty.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P1E3">The novel was a commercial hit and was praised by most critics.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P2">
				<sentence xml:id="P2E0">Its audiobook version, performed by a full cast including <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Alan Alda, Mark Hamill, and John Turturro</ENAMEX>, won an <ENAMEX type="AWARD">Audie Award</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2007</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P2E1">A film inspired by the novel, directed by <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Marc Forster and starring Brad Pitt</ENAMEX>, was released in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2013</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P3">
				<sentence xml:id="P3E0">The story is told in the form of a series of interviews conducted by the narrator, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Max Brooks</ENAMEX>, an agent of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">United Nations Postwar Commission</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P3E1">Although the exact origin of the plague is unknown, a young boy from a village in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">China</ENAMEX> is identified as the plague&apos;s official patient zero.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P3E2">The boy&apos;s case marks the point where the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Chinese government</ENAMEX> begins to take measures to cover up the disease, including generating a crisis with <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Taiwan</ENAMEX> to mask their activities.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P3E3">Nevertheless, the plague still manages to spread to various nations by human trafficking, refugees and the black market organ trade.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P3E4">Initially, these nations were able to cover up their smaller outbreaks, until a much larger outbreak in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">South Africa</ENAMEX> brings the plague to public attention.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P4">
				<sentence xml:id="P4E0">As the infection spreads, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Israel</ENAMEX> abandons the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Palestinian territories</ENAMEX> and initiates a nationwide quarantine, closing its borders to everyone except uninfected <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Jews and Palestinians</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P4E1">Its military then puts down an ultra-Orthodox uprising, which is later referred to as an <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">Israeli</ENAMEX> civil war.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P4E2">The <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">United States</ENAMEX> does little to prepare because it is overconfident in its ability to suppress any threat.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P4E3">Although special forces teams contain initial outbreaks, a widespread effort never starts: the nation is deprived of political will by &quot;brushfire wars&quot;, and a widely distributed and marketed placebo vaccine creates a false sense of security.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P5">
				<sentence xml:id="P5E0">As many more areas around the globe fall to infection, a period known as the &quot;<ENAMEX type="EVENT">Great Panic</ENAMEX>&quot; begins.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P5E1"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Pakistan and Iran</ENAMEX> destroy each other in a nuclear war, after the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Iranian government</ENAMEX> attempts to stem the flow of refugees fleeing through <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Pakistan</ENAMEX> into <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Iran</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P5E2">After zombies overrun <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">New York City</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">U.S. military</ENAMEX> sets up a high-profile defense in the nearby <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">city of Yonkers</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P5E3">The &quot;<ENAMEX type="EVENT">Battle of Yonkers</ENAMEX>&quot; is a disaster; modern weapons and tactics prove ineffective against zombies, as the enemy has no self-preservation instincts and can only be stopped if shot through the head.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P5E4">The unprepared and demoralized soldiers are routed on live television.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P5E5">Other countries suffer similarly disastrous defeats, and human civilization teeters on the brink of destruction.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P6">
				<sentence xml:id="P6E0">In <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">South Africa</ENAMEX>, the government adopts a contingency plan drafted by <ENAMEX type="PERSON">apartheid-era intelligence consultant Paul Redeker</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P6E1">It calls for the establishment of small sanctuaries, leaving large groups of survivors abandoned in special zones in order to distract the undead and allowing those within the main safe zone time to regroup and recuperate.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P6E2">Governments worldwide assume similar plans or relocate the populace to safer foreign territory, such as the attempted complete evacuation of the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Japanese archipelago</ENAMEX> to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Kamchatka</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P6E3">Because zombies freeze solid in severe cold, many civilians in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">North America</ENAMEX> flee to the wildernesses of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">northern Canada</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Arctic</ENAMEX>, where <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">eleven million</ENAMEX> people die of starvation and hypothermia.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P6E4">It is implied that some turn to <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">cannibalism</ENAMEX> to survive; further interviews from other sources imply that <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">cannibalism</ENAMEX> occurred in areas of the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">United States</ENAMEX> where food shortages occurred.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P6E5">The <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">three</ENAMEX> remaining astronauts in the <ENAMEX type="INSTALLATION">International Space Station</ENAMEX> survive the war by salvaging supplies from the abandoned <ENAMEX type="INSTALLATION">Chinese space station</ENAMEX> and maintain some military and civilian satellites using an orbital fuel station.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P6E6">A surviving member of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">ISS</ENAMEX> crew describes &quot;mega&quot; swarms of zombies on the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">American Great Plains and Central Asia</ENAMEX>, and how the crisis affected <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Earth</ENAMEX>&apos;s atmosphere.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P7">
				<sentence xml:id="P7E0">The <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> eventually establishes safe zones west of the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Rocky Mountains</ENAMEX> and spends much of the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">next decade</ENAMEX> eradicating zombies in that region.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P7E1">All aspects of civilian life are devoted to supporting the war effort against the pandemic.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P7E2">Much of it resembles total war strategies: rationing of fuel and food, cultivation of private gardens, and civilian neighborhood patrols.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P7E3">The <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">U.S. government</ENAMEX> also initiates a &quot;<ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Re-education Act</ENAMEX>&quot; to train the civilian population for the war effort and restore order; the people with skills such as carpentry and construction find themselves more valuable than people with managerial skills.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P8">
				<sentence xml:id="P8E0"><ENAMEX type="PERIOD">Seven years after the outbreak</ENAMEX> began, a conference is held off the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">coast of Honolulu</ENAMEX>, aboard the <ENAMEX type="INSTALLATION">USS Saratoga</ENAMEX>, where most of the world&apos;s leaders argue that they can outlast the zombie plague if they stay in their safe zones.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P8E1">The <ENAMEX type="TITLE">U.S. President</ENAMEX>, however, argues for going on the offensive.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P8E2">Determined to lead by example, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">U.S. military</ENAMEX> reinvents itself to meet the specific strategic requirements of fighting the undead: using semi-automatic, high-power rifles and volley firing, focusing on head shots and slow, steady rates of fire (a tactic &quot;re-invented&quot; by the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Indian Army</ENAMEX> during the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Great Panic</ENAMEX>); and devising a multipurpose hand tool, the &quot;<ENAMEX type="ARTIFACT">Lobotomizer</ENAMEX>&quot; or &quot;<ENAMEX type="ARTIFACT">Lobo</ENAMEX>&quot; (described as a combination of a shovel and a battle axe), for close-quarters combat.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P8E3">The military, backed by a resurgent <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">American</ENAMEX> wartime economy, began the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">three-year</ENAMEX>-long process of retaking the contiguous <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">United States</ENAMEX> from both the undead as well as groups of hostile human survivors.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P8E4">Prewar military tactics and equipment are mentioned as being employed to deal with sometimes well-armed and organized human criminal or rebel opposition.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P9">
				<sentence xml:id="P9E0"><ENAMEX type="PERIOD">Ten years after the official end of the zombie war</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">millions</ENAMEX> of zombies are still active, mainly on the ocean floor or on snow line islands.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P9E1">A democratic <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Cuba</ENAMEX> has become the world&apos;s most thriving economy.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P9E2">Following a civil war that saw use of nuclear weapons, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">China</ENAMEX> has become a democracy and is now known as the &quot;<ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Chinese Federation</ENAMEX>&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P9E3"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Tibet</ENAMEX> is freed from <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">Chinese</ENAMEX> rule and hosts <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Lhasa</ENAMEX>, the world&apos;s most populated city.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P9E4">Following a religious revolution and the revival of <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Russian orthodoxy</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Russia</ENAMEX> is now an expansionist theocracy known as the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Holy Russian Empire</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P9E5">Owing to the fact that many young <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">Russians</ENAMEX> either became zombies, were infected with HIV, or died due to drugs, the government has initiated a &quot;breeding&quot; program, with the remaining fertile women implied to be coercively impregnated to raise the birthrate.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P9E6"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION">North Korea</ENAMEX> is completely empty, with the entire population presumed to have disappeared into underground bunkers.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P10">
				<sentence xml:id="P10E0">The situation in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">British Isles</ENAMEX> is not entirely clear in the novel, although <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Ireland</ENAMEX> may have escaped the worst of the outbreak.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P10E1">Members of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">British Royal Family</ENAMEX> had fled to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Ireland</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Isle of Man</ENAMEX>, following the military retreat to the <ENAMEX type="INSTALLATION">Antonine Wall</ENAMEX>, and now exports oil from a reserve under <ENAMEX type="INSTALLATION">Windsor Castle</ENAMEX> where the <ENAMEX type="TITLE">Queen</ENAMEX> held out for the war&apos;s duration, refusing to flee with her relatives.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P10E2"><ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">The Papacy</ENAMEX> established a wartime refuge in the <ENAMEX type="INSTALLATION">Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Armagh</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P10E3"> In <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="INSTALLATION">Palace of Versailles</ENAMEX> was the site of a massacre and has been burned to the ground; military losses were particularly high while clearing <ENAMEX type="INSTALLATION">the catacombs</ENAMEX> underneath <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Paris</ENAMEX> because <ENAMEX type="INSTALLATION">the catacombs</ENAMEX> housed nearly a quarter of a <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">million</ENAMEX> refugees during the early stages of the war, all of whom became zombies.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P10E4"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Iceland</ENAMEX> has been completely depopulated and remains the world&apos;s most heavily infested country.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P11">
				<sentence xml:id="P11E0">The <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Israelis and Palestinians</ENAMEX> have made peace, and the former occupied territories have been renamed &quot;<ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Unified Palestine</ENAMEX>&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P11E1"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Mexico</ENAMEX> is now known as &quot;<ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Aztlán</ENAMEX>&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P11E2">Several countries are described as having revised borders due to the &quot;dumping&quot; of convicts into infected zones; these convicts rose to command &quot;powerful fiefdoms&quot; that later became independent states.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P11E3">A so-called &quot;Pacific Continent&quot; appears to encompass previously uninhabited islands as well as ships rendered immobile due to lack of fuel.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P11E4">For unknown reasons, the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Saudi Royal Family</ENAMEX> destroyed the oil fields in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Saudi Arabia</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P12">
				<sentence xml:id="P12E0">The <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">United Nations</ENAMEX> fields a large military force to eliminate the remaining zombies from overrun areas, defeat hordes that surface from the ocean floor, and kill frozen zombies before they unfreeze.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P12E1">It is stated that previously eradicated diseases have made a comeback and that global life expectancy is greatly reduced as the world starts over from where it began.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P13">
				<sentence xml:id="P13E0"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Brooks</ENAMEX> designed <ENAMEX type="CREATION">World War Z</ENAMEX> to follow the &quot;laws&quot; set up in his earlier work, <ENAMEX type="CREATION">The Zombie Survival Guide (2003)</ENAMEX>, and explained that the guide may exist in the novel&apos;s fictional universe.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P13E1"> The zombies of <ENAMEX type="CREATION">The Zombie Survival Guide</ENAMEX> are human bodies reanimated by an incurable virus (Solanum), devoid of intelligence, desirous solely of consuming living flesh, and cannot be killed unless the brain is destroyed.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P13E2">Decomposition will eventually set in, but this process takes longer than for an uninfected body and can be slowed by effects such as freezing.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P13E3">Although zombies do not tire and are as strong as the humans they infect, they are slow-moving and incapable of planning or cooperation in their attacks.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P13E4">Zombies usually reveal their presence by moaning.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P14">
				<sentence xml:id="P14E0"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Max Brooks</ENAMEX> (right) with <ENAMEX type="PERSON">George Romero</ENAMEX> at the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">SDCC</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2007</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P15">
				<sentence xml:id="P15E0"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Brooks</ENAMEX> discussed the cultural influences on the novel.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P15E1">He claimed inspiration from &quot;<ENAMEX type="CREATION">The Good War: An Oral History of World War Two&quot; (1984)</ENAMEX> by <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Studs Terkel</ENAMEX>, stating: &quot;[<ENAMEX type="PERSON">Terkel</ENAMEX>&apos;s book is] an oral history of <ENAMEX type="EVENT">World War II</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P15E2">I read it when I was a teenager and it&apos;s sat with me ever since.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P15E3">When I sat down to write <ENAMEX type="CREATION">World War Z: An Oral History of the Zombie War</ENAMEX>, I wanted it to be in the vein of an oral history.&quot;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P15E4"> <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Brooks</ENAMEX> also cited renowned zombie <ENAMEX type="PERSON">film director George A. Romero</ENAMEX> as an influence and criticized <ENAMEX type="CREATION">The Return of the Living Dead</ENAMEX> films: &quot;They cheapen zombies, make them silly and campy.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P15E5">They&apos;ve done for <ENAMEX type="CREATION">the living dead</ENAMEX> what the old <ENAMEX type="CREATION">Batman</ENAMEX> TV show did for <ENAMEX type="CREATION">The Dark Knight</ENAMEX>.&quot;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P15E6"> <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Brooks</ENAMEX> acknowledged making several references to popular culture in the novel, including one to alien robot franchise Transformers, but declined to identify the others so that readers could discover them independently.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P16">
				<sentence xml:id="P16E0"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Brooks</ENAMEX> conducted copious research while writing <ENAMEX type="CREATION">World War Z</ENAMEX>. The technology, politics, economics, culture, and military tactics were based on a variety of reference books and consultations with expert sources.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P16E1"> <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Brooks</ENAMEX> also cites the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">U.S. Army</ENAMEX> as a reference on firearm statistics.</sentence>
			</p>
		</document>
	</subcorpus>
</corpus>
