<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<corpus>
	<subcorpus>
		<document name="Wikipedia_brexit.1">
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P0">
				<sentence xml:id="P0E0">The <ENAMEX type="EVENT">United Kingdom European Union membership referendum</ENAMEX>, known within the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">United Kingdom</ENAMEX> as the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">EU referendum</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit referendum</ENAMEX>, was a non-binding referendum that took place on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">Thursday 23 June 2016</ENAMEX> in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK and Gibraltar</ENAMEX> to gauge support for the country&apos;s continued membership in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E1">The referendum resulted in an overall vote to leave the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, by <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">51.9%</ENAMEX> on a national turnout of <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">72%</ENAMEX> making it the highest ever for a <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>-wide referendum and also the highest turnout for any national vote since the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1992</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="EVENT">UK General Election</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E2"> The result was split between the constituent countries of the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">United Kingdom</ENAMEX>, with a majority in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">England and Wales</ENAMEX> voting to leave, and a majority in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Scotland and Northern Ireland</ENAMEX>, as well as <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Gibraltar</ENAMEX>, voting to remain.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E3">To start the process to leave the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, which is expected to take several years, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">British government</ENAMEX> will have to invoke <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Article 50 of the Treaty on European Union</ENAMEX>, but it has not yet done so.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P1">
				<sentence xml:id="P1E0">Membership of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> and its predecessors had long been a topic of debate in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">United Kingdom</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P1E1">The country joined the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Economic Community (EEC, or &quot;Common Market&quot;)</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1973</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P1E2">A referendum on continued <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EEC</ENAMEX> membership was held in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1975</ENAMEX>, and it was approved by <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">67%</ENAMEX> of voters.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P1E3"> In accordance with a <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Conservative Party</ENAMEX> manifesto commitment, the legal basis for a referendum was established by the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">UK Parliament</ENAMEX> through the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">European Union Referendum Act 2015</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P2">
				<sentence xml:id="P2E0"><ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Britain Stronger in Europe</ENAMEX> was the official group campaigning for the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> to remain in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, and Vote Leave the official group campaigning for it to leave.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P2E1">Other campaign groups, political parties, businesses, trade unions, newspapers and prominent individuals were also involved, and each side had supporters from across the political spectrum.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P3">
				<sentence xml:id="P3E0">Those who favoured a <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">British</ENAMEX> withdrawal from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX> – commonly referred to as a <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX> (a portmanteau of &quot;<ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">British</ENAMEX>&quot; and &quot;exit&quot;) – argued that the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> has a democratic deficit and that being a member undermined national sovereignty, while those who favoured membership argued that in a world with many supranational organisations any loss of sovereignty was compensated by the benefits of <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> membership.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P3E1">Those who wanted to leave the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> argued that it would allow the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> to better control immigration, thus reducing pressure on public services, housing and jobs; save <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">billions</ENAMEX> of pounds in <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> membership fees; allow the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> to make its own trade deals; and free the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> from <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> regulations and bureaucracy that they saw as needless and costly.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P3E2">Those who wanted to remain argued that leaving the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> would risk the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>&apos;s prosperity; diminish its influence over world affairs; jeopardise national security by reducing access to common <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">European</ENAMEX> criminal databases; and result in trade barriers between the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P3E3">In particular, they argued that it would lead to job losses, delays in investment into the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> and risks to business.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P4">
				<sentence xml:id="P4E0">Financial markets reacted negatively to the outcome.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P4E1"> Investors in worldwide stock markets lost more than the equivalent of <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">2 trillion</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">United States</ENAMEX> dollars on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">24 June 2016</ENAMEX>, making it the worst single-day loss in history, in absolute terms.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P4E2"> The market losses amounted to <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">3 trillion</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">US</ENAMEX> dollars by <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">27 June</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P4E3"> The value of the pound sterling against the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">US</ENAMEX> dollar fell to a <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">31</ENAMEX>-year low.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P4E4"> The <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>&apos;s and the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>&apos;s sovereign debt credit rating was also lowered by Standard &amp; Poor&apos;s.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P4E5"> By <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">29 June</ENAMEX>, the markets had returned to growth and the value of the pound had begun to rise.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P5">
				<sentence xml:id="P5E0">Immediately following the result, the <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Prime Minister David Cameron</ENAMEX> announced he would resign, having campaigned unsuccessfully for a &quot;remain&quot; vote on behalf of <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Britain Stronger in Europe</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">HM Government</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P5E1">He was succeeded by <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Theresa May</ENAMEX> on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">13 July</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P5E2">The opposition <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Labour Party</ENAMEX> also faces a leadership challenge as a result of the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">EU referendum</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P5E3"> In response to the result, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Scottish Government</ENAMEX> announced that it would plan for a possible second referendum on independence from the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">United Kingdom</ENAMEX>, and announced that it would like &quot;discussions with the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> institutions and other member states to explore all the possible options to protect <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Scotland</ENAMEX>&apos;s place in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P5E4"> Meanwhile, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Nigel Farage</ENAMEX>, leader of the anti-<ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">UKIP</ENAMEX> stood down after his party&apos;s long-term ambition had been accomplished.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P6">
				<sentence xml:id="P6E0">History</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P7">
				<sentence xml:id="P7E0">See also: <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">European Communities Act 1972</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>) and <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">European Union Act 2011</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P8">
				<sentence xml:id="P8E0">The <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Economic Community (EEC)</ENAMEX> was formed in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1957</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P8E1"> The <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">United Kingdom (UK)</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">first</ENAMEX> applied to join in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1961</ENAMEX>, but this was vetoed by <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P8E2"> A later application was successful and the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> joined in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1973</ENAMEX>; a referendum <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">two years later</ENAMEX> on continuing membership resulted in <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">67%</ENAMEX> approval.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P8E3"> Political integration gained greater focus when the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Maastricht Treaty</ENAMEX> established the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>) in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1993</ENAMEX>, which incorporated (and after the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Treaty of Lisbon</ENAMEX>, succeeded) the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EEC</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P9">
				<sentence xml:id="P9E0">In his <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2015</ENAMEX> election campaign, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">David Cameron</ENAMEX> promised to renegotiate the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> membership and later hold a referendum.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P10">
				<sentence xml:id="P10E0">In the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">European Parliament election</ENAMEX>in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2014</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">UK Independence Party (UKIP)</ENAMEX> secured a (narrow) plurality of the popular vote leaving the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Conservative Party</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">third</ENAMEX> place (<ENAMEX type="MEASURE">first</ENAMEX> time a party other than the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Conservatives</ENAMEX> or <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Labour</ENAMEX> had topped a nationwide poll in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">108 years</ENAMEX>).</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P10E1">Given the electoral system for the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Parliament</ENAMEX> uses a Proportional Representation, <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">UKIP</ENAMEX> also gained the most <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">British</ENAMEX> seats in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Parliament</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P11">
				<sentence xml:id="P11E0">While attending the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">May 2012 NATO summit meeting</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">British Prime Minister David Cameron, William Hague and Ed Llewellyn</ENAMEX> discussed the idea of using a <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">European Union referendum</ENAMEX> as a concession to energise the <ENAMEX type="CONCEPTUAL">Eurosceptic</ENAMEX> wing of the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Conservative Party</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P11E1"> In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">January 2013</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Cameron</ENAMEX> promised that, should his <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Conservative Party</ENAMEX> win a parliamentary majority at the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">2015 general election</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">UK Government</ENAMEX> would negotiate more favourable arrangements for continuing <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">British</ENAMEX> membership of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, before holding a referendum on whether the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> should remain in or leave the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P11E2"> In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">May 2013</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Conservative Party</ENAMEX> published a draft <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">EU Referendum Bill</ENAMEX> and outlined their plans for renegotiation and then an In-Out vote if returned to office in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2015</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P11E3"> The <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">draft Bill</ENAMEX> stated that the referendum must be held no later than <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">31 December 2017</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P12">
				<sentence xml:id="P12E0">The draft legislation was taken forward as a <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Private Member&apos;s Bill</ENAMEX> by <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Conservative MP James Wharton</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P12E1"> The bill&apos;s<ENAMEX type="MEASURE">First</ENAMEX> Reading in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">House of Commons</ENAMEX> took place on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">19 June 2013</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P12E2"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Cameron</ENAMEX> was said by a spokesperson to be &quot;very pleased&quot; and would ensure the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Bill</ENAMEX> was given &quot;the full support of the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Conservative Party</ENAMEX>&quot;.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P13">
				<sentence xml:id="P13E0">Regarding the ability of the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Bill</ENAMEX> to bind the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">UK Governement</ENAMEX> in the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2015-20</ENAMEX> Parliament to holding such a referendum, a parliamentary research paper noted that:</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P14">
				<sentence xml:id="P14E0">The <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Bill</ENAMEX> simply provides for a referendum on continued <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> membership by the end of <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">December 2017</ENAMEX> and does not otherwise specify the timing, other than requiring the <ENAMEX type="TITLE">Secretary of State</ENAMEX> to bring forward orders by the end of <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2016</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P14E1">[...]</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P14E2">If no party obtained a majority at the [next general election due in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2015</ENAMEX>], there might be some uncertainty about the passage of the orders in the next Parliament.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P15">
				<sentence xml:id="P15E0">The <ENAMEX type= "LEGAL">Bill</ENAMEX> received its <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">Second</ENAMEX> Reading on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">5 July 2013</ENAMEX>, passing by <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">304</ENAMEX> votes to none after almost all <ENAMEX type="TITLE">Labour MPs</ENAMEX> and all <ENAMEX type="TITLE">Liberal Democrat MPs</ENAMEX> abstained, cleared the Commons in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">November 2013</ENAMEX>, and was then introduced to the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">House of Lords</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">December 2013</ENAMEX>, where members voted to block the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">bill</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P16">
				<sentence xml:id="P16E0"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Conservative MP Bob Neill</ENAMEX> then introduced an Alternative <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Referendum Bill</ENAMEX> to the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Commons</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P16E1"> After a debate on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">17 October 2014</ENAMEX>, it passed to the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Public Bills Committee</ENAMEX>, but because the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">Commons</ENAMEX> failed to pass a money resolution, the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Bill</ENAMEX> was unable to progress further before the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Dissolution of Parliament on 27 March 2015</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P17">
				<sentence xml:id="P17E0">Under <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Ed Miliband</ENAMEX>&apos;s leadership <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">between 2010 and 2015</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Labour Party</ENAMEX> ruled out an In-Out referendum unless and until a further transfer of powers from the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> to the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> were proposed.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P17E1"> In their manifesto for the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">2015 general election</ENAMEX> the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Liberal Democrats</ENAMEX> pledged to hold an In-Out referendum only in the event of there being a change in the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">EU treaties</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P17E2"> <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">The UK Independence Party (UKIP), the British National Party (BNP), the Green Party, the Democratic Unionist Party and the Respect Party</ENAMEX> all supported the principle of a referendum.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P18">
				<sentence xml:id="P18E0">When the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Conservative Party</ENAMEX> won the majority of seats in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">House of Commons</ENAMEX> in the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">May 2015 general election</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Cameron</ENAMEX> reiterated his party&apos;s manifesto commitment to hold an In-Out referendum on <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> membership of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> by the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">end of 2017</ENAMEX>, but only after &quot;negotiating a new settlement for <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>&quot;.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P19">
				<sentence xml:id="P19E0">Renegotiation before the referendum</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P20">
				<sentence xml:id="P20E0">Main article: <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> renegotiation of <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> membership, <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2016</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P21">
				<sentence xml:id="P21E0">In early <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2014</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Prime Minister David Cameron</ENAMEX> outlined the changes he aimed to bring about in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> and in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>&apos;s relationship with it.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P21E1"> These were: additional immigration controls, especially for new <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> members; tougher immigration rules for present <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> citizens; new powers for national parliaments collectively to veto proposed <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> laws; new free trade agreements and a reduction in bureaucracy for businesses; a lessening of the influence of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Court of Human Rights</ENAMEX> on <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> police and courts; more power for individual member states and less for the central <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>; and abandoning the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> notion of &quot;ever closer union&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P21E2"> He intended to bring these about during a series of negotiations with other <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> leaders  and then, if re-elected, to announce a referendum.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P22">
				<sentence xml:id="P22E0">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">November</ENAMEX> that year, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Cameron</ENAMEX> gave an update on the negotiations and further details of his aims.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P22E1"> The key demands made of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> were: on economic governance, to recognise officially that <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Eurozone</ENAMEX> laws would not necessarily apply to non-<ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Eurozone</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> members and the latter would not have to bail out troubled <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Eurozone</ENAMEX> economies; on competitiveness, to expand the single market and to set a target for the reduction of bureaucracy for businesses; on sovereignty, for the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> to be legally exempted from &quot;ever closer union&quot; and for national parliaments to be able collectively to veto proposed <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> laws; and, on immigration, for <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> citizens going to the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> for work to be unable to claim social housing or in-work benefits until they had worked there for <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">four years</ENAMEX> and for them to be unable to send child benefit payments overseas.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P23">
				<sentence xml:id="P23E0">The outcome of the renegotiations was announced in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">February 2016</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P23E1"> The renegotiated terms were in addition to the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">United Kingdom</ENAMEX>&apos;s existing opt-outs in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> rebate.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P23E2">There was no fundamental change to the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>–<ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> relationship.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P23E3">[citation needed] Some limits to in-work benefits for <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> immigrants were agreed, but these would apply on a sliding scale for <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">four years</ENAMEX> and be for new immigrants only; before they could be applied, a country would have to get permission from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Council</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P23E4"> Child benefit payments could still be made overseas, but these would be linked to the cost of living in the other country.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P23E5"> On sovereignty, the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> was reassured that it would not be required to participate in &quot;ever closer union&quot;; these reassurances were &quot;in line with existing <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> law&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P23E6"> <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Cameron</ENAMEX>&apos;s demand to allow national parliaments to veto proposed <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> laws was modified to allow national parliaments collectively to object to proposed <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> laws, in which case the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Council</ENAMEX> would reconsider the proposal before itself deciding what to do.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P23E7"> On economic governance, anti-discrimination regulations for non-<ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Eurozone</ENAMEX> members would be reinforced, but they would be unable to veto any legislation.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P23E8"> The final <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">two</ENAMEX> areas covered were proposals to &quot;exclude from the scope of free movement rights, <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">third</ENAMEX> country nationals who had no prior lawful residence in a Member State before marrying a Union citizen&quot; and to make it easier for member states to deport <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> nationals for public policy or public security reasons.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P23E9"> The extent to which the various parts of the agreement would be legally binding is complex; no part of the agreement itself changed <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> law, but some parts could be enforceable in international law.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P24">
				<sentence xml:id="P24E0">According to reliable sources, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> had offered <ENAMEX type="PERSON">David Cameron</ENAMEX> a so-called &quot;emergency brake&quot; which would have allowed the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> to withhold social benefits to new immigrants for the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">first four years</ENAMEX> after they arrived; this brake could have been applied for a period of <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">seven years</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P24E1">That offer was still on the table at the time of the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit referendum</ENAMEX> but expired when the vote determined that the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> would leave the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P24E2"> <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Cameron</ENAMEX> claimed &quot;he could have avoided <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX> had <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">European</ENAMEX> leaders let him control migration&quot;, according to the <ENAMEX type="MEDIA">Financial Times</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P24E3"> However, that offer had not been made by the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, as confirmed by <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Angela Merkel</ENAMEX> to the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">German Parliament</ENAMEX>: “If you wish to have free access to the single market then you have to accept the fundamental <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">European</ENAMEX> rights as well as obligations that come from it.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P24E4">This is as true for <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Great Britain</ENAMEX> as for anybody else.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P25">
				<sentence xml:id="P25E0">Legislation</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P26">
				<sentence xml:id="P26E0">To enable the referendum to take place across the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">United Kingdom</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Gibraltar</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">two</ENAMEX> pieces of legislation were enacted.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P26E1">The <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">first</ENAMEX> of these, the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">European Union Referendum Act 2015</ENAMEX>, was passed by the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Parliament of the United Kingdom</ENAMEX> and received the <ENAMEX type= "LEGAL">Royal Assent</ENAMEX> on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">17 December 2015</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P26E2">The <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">second</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">European Union (Referendum) Act 2016</ENAMEX>, was passed by the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Gibraltar Parliament </ENAMEX>  to allow the referendum to take place in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Gibraltar</ENAMEX> and received the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Royal Assent</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">on 28 January 2016</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P27">
				<sentence xml:id="P27E0">The planned referendum was included in the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Queen &apos;s Speech on 27 May 2015</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P27E1"> It was suggested at the time that <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Cameron</ENAMEX> was planning to hold the referendum in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">October 2016</ENAMEX>, but the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">European Union Referendum Act 2015</ENAMEX>, which authorised it, went before the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">House of Commons</ENAMEX> the following day, just <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">three weeks after the election</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P27E2"> On the bill&apos;s <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">second</ENAMEX> reading on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">9 June</ENAMEX>, members of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">House of Commons</ENAMEX> voted by <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">544</ENAMEX> to <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">53</ENAMEX> in favour of it, endorsing the principle of holding a referendum, with only the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Scottish National Party</ENAMEX> voting against.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P27E3"> In contrast to the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Labour Party</ENAMEX>&apos;s position prior to the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2015 general election</ENAMEX> under <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Miliband</ENAMEX>, acting <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Labour</ENAMEX> leader <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Harriet Harman</ENAMEX> committed her party to supporting plans for an <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> referendum by <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2017</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P28">
				<sentence xml:id="P28E0">Administration</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P29">
				<sentence xml:id="P29E0">Date</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P30">
				<sentence xml:id="P30E0">Prior to being officially announced, it was widely speculated that a <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">June</ENAMEX> date for the referendum was a serious possibility.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P30E1">The <ENAMEX type="TITLE">First Ministers of Northern Ireland, Scotland, and Wales</ENAMEX> co-signed a letter to <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Cameron</ENAMEX> asking him not to hold the referendum in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">June</ENAMEX>, as devolved elections were scheduled to take place the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">previous month</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P30E2">These elections had been postponed for <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">a year</ENAMEX> to avoid a clash with the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2015 General Election</ENAMEX>, after <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Westminster</ENAMEX> had implemented the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Fixed Term parliament Act</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P30E3"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Cameron</ENAMEX> refused this request, saying people were able to make up their own minds in multiple elections spaced a short time from each other.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P31">
				<sentence xml:id="P31E0">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">February 2016</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Cameron</ENAMEX> announced that the Government was to recommend that the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> should remain in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> and that the referendum would be held on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">23 June</ENAMEX>, marking the official launch of the campaign.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P31E1">He also announced that Parliament would enact secondary legislation relating to the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">European Union Referendum Act 2015</ENAMEX> on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">22 February</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P31E2">With the official launch, ministers of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">UK Government</ENAMEX> were then free to campaign on either side of the argument in a rare exception to Cabinet collective responsibility.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P32">
				<sentence xml:id="P32E0">Eligibility to vote</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P33">
				<sentence xml:id="P33E0">The <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">European Union Referendum Act 2015</ENAMEX> dictated that only <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">British, Irish</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Commonwealth</ENAMEX> citizens over <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">18</ENAMEX> who were resident in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK or Gibraltar</ENAMEX> would be able to vote in the referendum.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P33E1"> <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">British</ENAMEX> citizens who had been registered to vote in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> within the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">last 15 years</ENAMEX> would also be eligible to vote.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P34">
				<sentence xml:id="P34E0">The deadline to register to vote was initially midnight on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">7 June 2016</ENAMEX> but this was extended by <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">48 hours</ENAMEX> because of technical problems with the official registration website on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">7 June</ENAMEX> caused by unusually high web traffic.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P34E1">Some supporters of the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Leave campaign</ENAMEX>, including the <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Conservative MP Sir Gerald Howarth</ENAMEX>, criticised the government&apos;s decision to extend the deadline, alleging it gave Remain an advantage because many late registrants were young people who were considered to be more likely to vote for Remain.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P34E2"> Almost <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">46.5 million</ENAMEX> people were eligible to vote.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P35">
				<sentence xml:id="P35E0">There was protest by some residents of the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Crown dependencies</ENAMEX> of the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Isle of Man, Jersey and Guernsey</ENAMEX> that they should have the opportunity to vote in the referendum, as (although not part of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, unlike <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Gibraltar</ENAMEX>) <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> membership also affected them.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P36">
				<sentence xml:id="P36E0">Procedure for a withdrawal</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P37">
				<sentence xml:id="P37E0">There is no precedent for a sovereign member state leaving the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX> or any of its predecessor organisations.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P37E1">However, <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">three</ENAMEX> territories of <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> member states have withdrawn: <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Algeria</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1962</ENAMEX>, independence from <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX>), <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Greenland</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1985</ENAMEX>) and <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Saint Barthélemy</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2012</ENAMEX>), the latter <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">two</ENAMEX> becoming <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Overseas Countries and Territories</ENAMEX> of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P38">
				<sentence xml:id="P38E0"><ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Article 49A</ENAMEX> of the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Treaty of Lisbon</ENAMEX>, which came into force on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1 December 2009</ENAMEX>, introduced for the <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">first</ENAMEX> time a procedure for a member state to withdraw voluntarily from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P39">
				<sentence xml:id="P39E0">Any Member State may decide to withdraw from the Union in accordance with its own constitutional requirements.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P40">
				<sentence xml:id="P40E0">A Member State which decides to withdraw shall notify the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Council</ENAMEX> of its intention.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P40E1">In the light of the guidelines provided by the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Council</ENAMEX>, the Union shall negotiate and conclude an agreement with that State, setting out the arrangements for its withdrawal, taking account of the framework for its future relationship with the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Union</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P40E2">That agreement shall be negotiated in accordance with <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Article 218 (3) of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P40E3">It shall be concluded on behalf of the Union by the Council, acting by a qualified majority, after obtaining the consent of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Parliament</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P41">
				<sentence xml:id="P41E0">The Treaties shall cease to apply to the State in question from the date of entry into force of the withdrawal agreement or, failing that, <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">two years</ENAMEX> after the notification referred to in paragraph 2, unless the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Council</ENAMEX>, in agreement with the Member State concerned, unanimously decides to extend this period.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P42">
				<sentence xml:id="P42E0">Coverage of the issue in <ENAMEX type="MEDIA">The Guardian</ENAMEX> includes an explanation as to <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Article 50</ENAMEX> and how it would be invoked.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P42E1">&quot;...</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P42E2">there seems to be no immediate legal means out of the stalemate.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P42E3">It is entirely up to the departing member state to trigger <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">article 50</ENAMEX>, by issuing formal notification of intention to leave: no one, in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Brussels, Berlin or Paris</ENAMEX>, can force it to.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P42E4">But equally, there is nothing in <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">article 50</ENAMEX> that obliges the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> to start talks – including the informal talks the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX> leaders want – before formal notification has been made. &quot;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P42E5">There is no mechanism to compel a state to withdraw from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX>,&quot; said <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Kenneth Armstrong</ENAMEX>, professor of European law at <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Cambridge University</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P42E6">... &quot;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P42E7">The notification of <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">article 50</ENAMEX> is a formal act and has to be done by the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">British government</ENAMEX> to the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European council</ENAMEX>,&quot; an <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> official told <ENAMEX type="MEDIA">Reuters</ENAMEX>.&quot;</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P43">
				<sentence xml:id="P43E0">Remaining members of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> consequently would need to undertake negotiations to manage change over the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>&apos;s budgets, voting allocations and policies brought about by the withdrawal of any member state.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P44">
				<sentence xml:id="P44E0">Some constitutional experts have argued that, under the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Scotland Act 1998</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Scottish Parliament</ENAMEX> has to consent to measures that eliminate <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> law&apos;s application in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Scotland</ENAMEX>, which gives the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Scottish Parliament</ENAMEX> an effective veto over <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>withdrawal from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, unless the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Scotland Act 1998</ENAMEX> is amended by the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">UK Parliament</ENAMEX> to reduce the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Scottish Parliament</ENAMEX>&apos;s current powers.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P44E1"> After the Leave result was announced, on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">26 June 2016</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">First Minister Nicola Sturgeon</ENAMEX> said she would &quot;of course&quot; ask the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Scottish Parliament</ENAMEX> to withhold consent and thus block the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> from leaving the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P44E2"> However, this interpretation of the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">1998 Act</ENAMEX> is disputed.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P44E3">For example, <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Section 28 (7) of the Act</ENAMEX> states that it &quot;does not affect the power of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Parliament of the United Kingdom</ENAMEX> to make laws for <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Scotland</ENAMEX>.&quot;</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P45">
				<sentence xml:id="P45E0">Referendum wording</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P46">
				<sentence xml:id="P46E0">Sample referendum ballot paper</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P47">
				<sentence xml:id="P47E0">Research by the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Electoral Commission</ENAMEX> confirmed that its recommended question &quot;was clear and straightforward for voters, and was the most neutral wording from the range of options ...</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P47E1">considered and tested&quot;, citing responses to its consultation by a diverse range of consultees.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P47E2"> The proposed question was accepted by the government in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">September 2015</ENAMEX>, shortly before the bill&apos;s <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">third</ENAMEX> reading.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P47E3"> The first ballot papers were issued to postal voters in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">May 2016</ENAMEX>, and the referendum question that appeared on them, as required under both pieces of legislation, was: &quot;Should the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">United Kingdom</ENAMEX> remain a member of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX> or leave the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX>?&quot;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P47E4"> The response was to be marked with a single (X): &quot;Remain a member of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX>&quot; or &quot;Leave the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX>&quot;.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P48">
				<sentence xml:id="P48E0">Campaign</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P49">
				<sentence xml:id="P49E0">Main article: Campaigning in the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">United Kingdom European Union membership referendum, 2016</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P50">
				<sentence xml:id="P50E0"><ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Britain Stronger in Europe</ENAMEX> campaigners, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">June 2016</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P51">
				<sentence xml:id="P51E0">Referendum posters for both the Leave and Remain campaigns in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Pimlico</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P52">
				<sentence xml:id="P52E0">As of <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">October 2015</ENAMEX>, there was a cross-party, formal group campaigning for <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> to remain a member, called <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Britain Stronger in Europe</ENAMEX>, while there were <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">two</ENAMEX> groups promoting exit which sought to be the official Leave campaign: Leave.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P52E1"><ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> (supported by most of <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">UKIP</ENAMEX>, including <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Nigel Farage</ENAMEX>), and <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Vote Leave</ENAMEX> (supported by <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Conservative Party Eurosceptics</ENAMEX>).</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P52E2"> The <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Electoral Commission</ENAMEX> announced on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">13 April 2016</ENAMEX> that <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Vote Leave</ENAMEX> was the official leave campaign.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P52E3">This gave it the right to spend up to <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">£7m,</ENAMEX> a free mailshot, TV broadcasts and <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">£600,000</ENAMEX> in public funds.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P52E4"> Leave.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P52E5"><ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> also had an umbrella group offshoot, the cross-party Grassroots Out.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P52E6"> The <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">UK government</ENAMEX>&apos;s official position was to support the remain option.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P52E7">A Government-backed campaign was launched in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">April</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P52E8"> On <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">16 June</ENAMEX> all official national campaigning was suspended until <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">19 June</ENAMEX> after the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">killing of MP Jo Cox</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P53">
				<sentence xml:id="P53E0"><ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">HM Government</ENAMEX> distributed a leaflet to every household in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">England</ENAMEX> in the week commencing on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">11 April</ENAMEX>, and in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland</ENAMEX> on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">5 May</ENAMEX> (after devolved elections).</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P53E1">It gave details on why the government&apos;s position was that the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> should remain in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P53E2">The rationale was that internal polls showed that <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">85%</ENAMEX> of the population wanted more information from the Government.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P53E3"> It was criticised by those wanting to leave as being an unfair advantage, inaccurate and a waste of money costing <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">£9.3 million</ENAMEX> for the campaign.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P54">
				<sentence xml:id="P54E0">In the week beginning on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">16 May</ENAMEX> the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Electoral Commission</ENAMEX> sent a voting guide regarding the referendum to every household within the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK and Gibraltar</ENAMEX> to raise awareness of the upcoming referendum.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P54E1">The <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">eight-page</ENAMEX> guide contained details on how to vote, as well as a sample of the actual ballot paper, and a whole page each was given to the campaign groups <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Britain Stronger in Europe</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Vote Leave</ENAMEX> to present their case.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P55">
				<sentence xml:id="P55E0">Responses to the referendum campaign</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P56">
				<sentence xml:id="P56E0">Party policies</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P57">
				<sentence xml:id="P57E0">The table lists only those political parties with elected representation in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Westminster</ENAMEX>, the devolved and the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">European</ENAMEX> parliaments.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P76">
				<sentence xml:id="P76E0">Among minor parties, <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Britain First, the British National Party (BNP), Éirígí, Respect Party, Trade Unionist and Socialist Coalition (TUSC), SDP, Liberal Party, and Independence from Europe</ENAMEX> supported leaving the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P76E1">The <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Scottish Socialist Party (SSP)</ENAMEX> supported remaining in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P76E2"> The <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Women&apos;s Equality Party (WE)</ENAMEX> had no official position on the issue.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P77">
				<sentence xml:id="P77E0">All parties represented in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Gibraltar Parliament</ENAMEX> supported Remain: the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Gibraltar Social Democrats (GSD), the Gibraltar Socialist Labour Party (GSLP), and the Liberal Party of Gibraltar</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P78">
				<sentence xml:id="P78E0">No party had decreed that its members should all follow the party line, resulting in public differences of view: <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Conservative Party</ENAMEX> MPs in particular, and <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Labour</ENAMEX> MPs to a lesser extent, taking different sides.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P78E1">Most parties had splits in their members and supporters, with <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Labour</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Conservative</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Liberal Democrat</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">UKIP</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Green</ENAMEX> supporters all taking different sides.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P79">
				<sentence xml:id="P79E0">Cabinet ministers</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P80">
				<sentence xml:id="P80E0">For the positions of <ENAMEX type="TITLE">backbench MPs</ENAMEX> and other politicians, see Endorsements in the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">United Kingdom European Union membership referendum 2016</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P81">
				<sentence xml:id="P81E0"><ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">The Cabinet of the United Kingdom</ENAMEX> is a body responsible for making decisions on policy and organising governmental departments; it is chaired by the <ENAMEX type="TITLE">Prime Minister</ENAMEX> and contains most of the government&apos;s ministerial heads.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P81E1"> Following the announcement of the referendum in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">February, 23</ENAMEX> of the <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">30</ENAMEX> Cabinet ministers (including attendees) supported the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> staying in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P81E2"> <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Iain Duncan Smith</ENAMEX>, in favour of leaving, resigned on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">19 March</ENAMEX> and was replaced by <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Stephen Crabb</ENAMEX> who was in favour of remaining.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P81E3"> <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Crabb</ENAMEX> was already a cabinet member, as the <ENAMEX type="TITLE">Secretary of State</ENAMEX> for <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Wales</ENAMEX>, and his replacement, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Alun Cairns</ENAMEX>, was in favour of remaining, bringing the total number of pro-remain Cabinet members to <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">25</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P82">
				<sentence xml:id="P82E0">Business</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P83">
				<sentence xml:id="P83E0">See also: Opinion polling for the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">United Kingdom European Union membership referendum</ENAMEX> § Business leaders</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P84">
				<sentence xml:id="P84E0">Various <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> multinationals have stated that they would not like the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> to leave the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> because of the uncertainty it would cause, such as <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">Shell</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">BT</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">Vodafone</ENAMEX>, with some assessing the pros and cons of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> exiting.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P84E1"> The banking sector was one of the most vocal advocating to stay in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, with the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">British Bankers&apos; Association</ENAMEX> saying: &quot;Businesses don&apos;t like that kind of uncertainty&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P84E2"> <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">RBS</ENAMEX> has warned of potential damage to the economy.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P84E3"> Furthermore, <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">HSBC</ENAMEX> and foreign-based banks <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">JP Morgan</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">Deutsche Bank</ENAMEX> claim a <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX> might result in the banks&apos; changing domicile.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P84E4"> According to <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">Goldman Sachs</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">City of London</ENAMEX>&apos;s policy chief, all such factors could impact on the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">City of London</ENAMEX>&apos;s present status as a <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">European</ENAMEX> and global market leader in financial services.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P84E5"> In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">February 2016</ENAMEX>, leaders of <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">36</ENAMEX> of the <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">FTSE 100</ENAMEX> companies, including <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">Shell, BAE Systems, BT and Rio Tinto</ENAMEX>, officially supported staying in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P84E6"> Moreover, <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">60%</ENAMEX> of the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Institute of Directorsand</ENAMEX> the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">EEF</ENAMEX> memberships supported staying.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P85">
				<sentence xml:id="P85E0">Many <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>-based businesses, including <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">Sainsbury</ENAMEX>&apos;s, remained steadfastly neutral, concerned that taking sides in the divisive issue could lead to a backlash from customers.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P86">
				<sentence xml:id="P86E0"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Richard Branson</ENAMEX> stated that he was &quot;very fearful&quot; of the consequences of a <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> exit from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P86E1"> <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Alan Sugar</ENAMEX> expressed similar concern.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P87">
				<sentence xml:id="P87E0">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">June 2016</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">James Dyson</ENAMEX>, founder of the <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">Dyson company</ENAMEX>, argued that the introduction of tariffs would be less damaging for <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">British</ENAMEX> exporters than the appreciation of the pound against the Euro, arguing that, as <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> ran a <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">100 billion</ENAMEX> pound trade deficit with the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, tariffs could represent a significant revenue source for the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Treasury</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P87E1"> Pointing out that languages, plugs and laws differ between <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> member states, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Dyson</ENAMEX> said that the <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">28</ENAMEX>-country bloc was not a single market, and argued the fastest growing markets were outside the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P87E2"> Engineering company <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">Rolls-Royce</ENAMEX> wrote to employees to say that it did not want the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> to leave the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P88">
				<sentence xml:id="P88E0">Surveys of large <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> businesses showed a strong majority favour the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> remaining in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P88E1"> Small and medium-sized <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> businesses are more evenly split.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P88E2"> Polls of foreign businesses found that around <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">half</ENAMEX> would be less likely to do business in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>, while <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">1%</ENAMEX> would increase their investment in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P88E3"> <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">Two</ENAMEX> large car manufacturers – <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">Ford and BMW</ENAMEX> – warned in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2013</ENAMEX> against <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX>, suggesting it would be &quot;devastating&quot; for the economy.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P88E4"> Conversely, in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2015</ENAMEX>, some other manufacturing executives told <ENAMEX type="MEDIA">Reuters</ENAMEX> that they would not shut their plants if the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> left the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, although future investment might be put at risk.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P88E5"> The <ENAMEX type="TITLE">CEO of Vauxhall</ENAMEX> stated that a <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX> would not materially affect its business.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P88E6"> Foreign-based <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Toyota CEO Akio Toyoda</ENAMEX> confirmed that, whether or not <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> left the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">Toyota</ENAMEX> would carry on manufacturing cars in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> as they had done before.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P89">
				<sentence xml:id="P89E0">Exchange rates and stock markets</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P90">
				<sentence xml:id="P90E0">In the week following conclusion of the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>&apos;s renegotiation (and especially after <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Boris Johnson</ENAMEX> announced that he would support the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> leaving), the pound fell to a <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">seven-year</ENAMEX> low against the dollar and economists at <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">HSBC</ENAMEX> warned that it could drop even more.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P90E1"> At the same time, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Daragh Maher, head of HSBC</ENAMEX>, suggested that if Sterling dropped in value so would the Euro.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P90E2">He said &quot;If we have increased <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX> risk, we will have a negative risk for the euro.&quot;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P90E3"><ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">European</ENAMEX> banking analysts also cited <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX> concerns as the reason for the Euro&apos;s decline.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P90E4"> Immediately after a poll in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">June 2016</ENAMEX> showed that the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Leave campaign</ENAMEX> was <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">10</ENAMEX> points ahead, the pound dropped by a further <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">one per cent</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P90E5"> In the same month, it was announced that the value of goods exported from the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">April</ENAMEX> had shown a month-on-month increase of <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">11.2%</ENAMEX>, &quot;the biggest rise since records started in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1998</ENAMEX>&quot;.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P91">
				<sentence xml:id="P91E0">Uncertainty over the referendum result, together with several other factors – <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">US</ENAMEX> interest rates rising, low commodity prices, low <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Eurozone</ENAMEX> growth and concerns over emerging markets such as <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">China</ENAMEX> – contributed to a high level of stock market volatility in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">January and February 2016</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P91E1"> During this period, the <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">FTSE 100</ENAMEX> rose or fell by more than <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">1.5%</ENAMEX> on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">16 days</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P91E2"> On <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">14 June</ENAMEX>, polls showing that a <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX> was more likely led to the <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">FTSE 100</ENAMEX> falling by <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">2%,</ENAMEX> lost <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">£98 billion</ENAMEX> in value.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P91E3"> After further polls suggested a move back towards <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Remain</ENAMEX>, the pound and the <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">FTSE</ENAMEX> recovered.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P92">
				<sentence xml:id="P92E0">On the day of the referendum, Sterling hit a <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2016</ENAMEX> high and the <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">FTSE 100</ENAMEX> climbed to a <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2016</ENAMEX> high of <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">$1.5018</ENAMEX> as a new poll suggested a win for the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Remain campaign</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P92E1"> Initial results suggested a vote for &apos;remain&apos; and the value of the pound held its value.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P92E2">However, when the result for <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Sunderland</ENAMEX> was announced, it indicated an unexpected swing to &apos;leave&apos;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P92E3">Subsequent results appeared to confirm this swing and sterling fell in value to <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">$1.3777</ENAMEX>, its lowest level <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">since 1985</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P92E4">However, the following <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">Monday</ENAMEX> when the markets opened, Sterling fell to a new low of <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">$1.32</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P93">
				<sentence xml:id="P93E0">When the <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">London Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> opened on the morning of <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">24 June</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">FTSE 100</ENAMEX> fell from <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">6338.10</ENAMEX> to <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">5806.13</ENAMEX> in the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">first ten minutes</ENAMEX> of trading.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P93E1">It recovered to <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">6091.27</ENAMEX> after a further <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">90</ENAMEX> minutes before further recovering to <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">6162</ENAMEX>.<ENAMEX type="MEASURE">97</ENAMEX> by the end of the day&apos;s trading.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P93E2">When the markets reopened the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">Following Monday</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">FTSE 100</ENAMEX> showed a steady decline losing over <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">2%</ENAMEX> by <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">mid-afternoon</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P93E3"> Upon opening later on the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">Friday after the referendum</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">US Dow Jones</ENAMEX> Industrial Average dropped nearly <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">450</ENAMEX> points or about <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">2½%</ENAMEX> in less than <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">half an hour</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P93E4">The <ENAMEX type="MEDIA">Associated Press</ENAMEX> called the sudden worldwide stock market decline a stock market crash.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P94">
				<sentence xml:id="P94E0">By <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">mid afternoon on 27 June 2016</ENAMEX>, the sterling was at a <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">31</ENAMEX>-year low, having fallen <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">11%</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">two</ENAMEX> trading days and the <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">FTSE 100</ENAMEX> had surrendered <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">£85 billion</ENAMEX>, though by <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">29 June</ENAMEX> it had recovered all its losses since the markets closed on polling day.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P95">
				<sentence xml:id="P95E0"><ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">European</ENAMEX> responses</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P96">
				<sentence xml:id="P96E0"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Czech prime minister Bohuslav Sobotka</ENAMEX> suggested that the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Czech Republic</ENAMEX> would start discussions on leaving the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> if the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> voted for an <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> exit.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P96E1"> <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Former Czech President Václav Klaus</ENAMEX> said that <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX>&apos;s departure from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> would be a bigger non-event than the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">dissolution of Czechoslovakia</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P97">
				<sentence xml:id="P97E0"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Marine Le Pen</ENAMEX>, the leader of the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">French Front national</ENAMEX>, described the possibility of a <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX> as &quot;like the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">fall of the Berlin Wall</ENAMEX>&quot; and commented that &quot;<ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX> would be marvellous – extraordinary – for all <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">European</ENAMEX> peoples who long for freedom&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P97E1"> A poll in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX> showed that <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">59%</ENAMEX> of the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">French</ENAMEX> people were in favour of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> remaining in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P98">
				<sentence xml:id="P98E0"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Polish President Andrzej Duda</ENAMEX> lent his support for the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> remaining within the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P98E1"> <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Moldovan Prime Minister Pavel Filip</ENAMEX> asked all citizens of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Moldova</ENAMEX> living in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> to speak to their <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">British</ENAMEX> friends and convince them to vote for the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> to remain in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P99">
				<sentence xml:id="P99E0"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Spanish foreign minister José García-Margallo</ENAMEX> said <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Spain</ENAMEX> would demand control of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Gibraltar</ENAMEX> the &quot;very next day&quot; after a <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">British</ENAMEX> withdrawal from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P99E1"> <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Margallo</ENAMEX> also threatened to close the border with <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Gibraltar</ENAMEX> if <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> left the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P100">
				<sentence xml:id="P100E0">The <ENAMEX type="PERSON">right-wing Dutch populist Geert Wilders</ENAMEX> said that the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Netherlands</ENAMEX> should follow <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">Britain</ENAMEX>&apos;s example: &quot;Like in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">1940s</ENAMEX>, once again <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> could help liberate <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX> from another totalitarian monster, this time called ‘<ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Brussels</ENAMEX>’.&quot;</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P101">
				<sentence xml:id="P101E0"><ENAMEX type="PERIOD">11 June 2016</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Swedish foreign minister Margot Wallstrom</ENAMEX> said that if <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> left the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, other countries would have referendums whether to leave the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, and that if <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> stayed in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, other countries would negotiate, ask and demand to have special treatment.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P102">
				<sentence xml:id="P102E0">Non-<ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">European</ENAMEX> responses</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P103">
				<sentence xml:id="P103E0"><ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">International Monetary Fund</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P104">
				<sentence xml:id="P104E0">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">February 2016</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Christine Lagarde, the managing director of the International Monetary Fund</ENAMEX>, warned that the uncertainty over the outcome of the referendum would be bad &quot;in and of itself&quot; for the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">British</ENAMEX> economy.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P104E1"> In response, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Leave campaigner Priti Patel</ENAMEX> said a previous warning from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">IMF</ENAMEX> regarding the coalition government&apos;s deficit plan for the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> was proven incorrect and that the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">IMF</ENAMEX> &quot;were wrong then and are wrong now&quot;.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P105">
				<sentence xml:id="P105E0"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION">United States</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P106">
				<sentence xml:id="P106E0">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">October 2015</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">United States Trade Representative Michael Froman</ENAMEX> declared that the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">United States</ENAMEX> was not keen on pursuing a separate free trade agreement (<ENAMEX type="ACRONYM">FTA</ENAMEX>) with <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> if it were to leave the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, thus undermining, according to <ENAMEX type="MEDIA">The Guardian</ENAMEX>, a key economic argument of proponents of those who say <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> would prosper on its own and be able to secure bilateral <ENAMEX type="ACRONYM">FTA</ENAMEX>s with trading partners.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P106E1"> Also in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">October 2015</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="PERSON">United States Ambassador to the United Kingdom Matthew Barzun</ENAMEX> said that <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> participation in <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">NATO</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> made each group &quot;better and stronger&quot; and that, while the decision to remain or leave is a choice for the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">British</ENAMEX> people, it was in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">US</ENAMEX> interest that it remain.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P106E2"> In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">April 2016</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type= "MEASURE">eight</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type= "TITLE">former US Secretaries of the Treasury</ENAMEX>, who served both <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Democratic and Republican</ENAMEX> presidents, urged <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> to remain in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P107">
				<sentence xml:id="P107E0">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">July 2015</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">President Barack Obama</ENAMEX> confirmed the long-standing <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">US</ENAMEX> preference for the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> to remain in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P107E1"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Obama</ENAMEX> said: &quot;Having the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> gives us much greater confidence about the strength of the transatlantic union, and is part of the cornerstone of the institutions built after <ENAMEX type="EVENT">World War II</ENAMEX> that has made the world safer and more prosperous.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P107E2">We want to make sure that the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">United Kingdom</ENAMEX> continues to have that influence.&quot;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P107E3"> <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Obama</ENAMEX>&apos;s intervention was criticised by <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Republican Senator Ted Cruz</ENAMEX> as &quot;a slap in the face of <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">British</ENAMEX> self-determination as the president, typically, elevated an international organisation over the rights of a sovereign people&quot;and stated that &quot;<ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> will be at the front of the line for a free trade deal with <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">America</ENAMEX>&quot;, were a <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX> to occur.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P108">
				<sentence xml:id="P108E0">Prior to the vote, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Republican presidential candidate Donald Trump</ENAMEX> anticipated that <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> would leave based on their concerns over migration, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Democratic presidential candidate Hillary Clinton</ENAMEX> hoped that <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> would remain in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> to strengthen transatlantic co-operation.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P109">
				<sentence xml:id="P109E0">Other states</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P110">
				<sentence xml:id="P110E0">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">October 2015</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Chinese President Xi Jinping</ENAMEX> declared his support for <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> remaining in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, saying &quot;<ENAMEX type="LOCATION">China</ENAMEX> hopes to see a prosperous <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX> and a united <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, and hopes <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX>, as an important member of the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">EU</ENAMEX>, can play an even more positive and constructive role in promoting the deepening development of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">China</ENAMEX>-<ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> ties&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P110E1"> <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">Chinese</ENAMEX> diplomats have stated &quot;off the record&quot; that the People&apos;s Republic sees the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> as a counterbalance to <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">American</ENAMEX> economic power, and that an <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> without <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> would mean a stronger <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">United States</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P111">
				<sentence xml:id="P111E0">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">February 2016</ENAMEX>, the finance ministers from the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">G20</ENAMEX> major economies warned that leaving the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> would lead to &quot;a shock&quot; in the global economy.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P112">
				<sentence xml:id="P112E0">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">May 2016</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Australian Prime Minister Malcolm Turnbull</ENAMEX> said that <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Australia</ENAMEX> would prefer the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> to remain in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, but that it was a matter for the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">British</ENAMEX> people, and &quot;whatever judgment they make, the relations between <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain and Australia</ENAMEX> will be very, very close&quot;.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P113">
				<sentence xml:id="P113E0"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Indonesian president Joko Widodo</ENAMEX> stated during a <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">European</ENAMEX> trip that he was not in favour of <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P114">
				<sentence xml:id="P114E0"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Sri Lankan Prime Minister Ranil Wickremesinghe</ENAMEX> issued a statement of reasons why he was &quot;very concerned&quot; at the possibility of <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P115">
				<sentence xml:id="P115E0"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Russian President Vladimir Putin</ENAMEX> said: &quot;I want to say it is none of our business, it is the business of the people of the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>.&quot;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P115E1"> <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Maria Zakharova, the official Russian foreign ministry spokesperson</ENAMEX>, said: &quot;<ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Russia</ENAMEX> has nothing to do with <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P115E2">We are not involved in this process in any way.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P115E3">We don’t have any interest in it.&quot;</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P116">
				<sentence xml:id="P116E0">Economists</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P117">
				<sentence xml:id="P117E0">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">November 2015</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Governor of the Bank of England Mark Carney</ENAMEX> said that the <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">Bank of England</ENAMEX> would do what was necessary to help the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> economy if the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">British</ENAMEX> people voted to leave the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P117E1"> In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">March 2016</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Carney</ENAMEX> told MPs that an <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> exit was the &quot;biggest domestic risk&quot; to the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> economy, but that remaining a member also carried risks, related to the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Monetary Union</ENAMEX>, of which the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> is not a member.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P117E2"> In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">May 2016</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Carney</ENAMEX> said that a &quot;technical recession&quot; was one of the possible risks of the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> leaving the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P117E3"> However, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Iain Duncan Smith</ENAMEX> said <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Carney</ENAMEX>&apos;s comment should be taken with &quot;a pinch of salt&quot;, saying &quot;all forecasts in the end are wrong&quot;.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P118">
				<sentence xml:id="P118E0">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">December 2015</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="BUSINESS">Bank of England</ENAMEX> published a report about the impact of immigration on wages.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P118E1">The report concluded that immigration put downward pressure on workers&apos; wages, particularly low-skilled workers: a <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">10 percent</ENAMEX> point rise in the proportion of migrants working in low-skilled services drove down the average wages of low-skilled workers by about <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">2 percent</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P119">
				<sentence xml:id="P119E0">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">March 2016</ENAMEX>,<ENAMEX type="PERSON">Nobel prize-winning economist Joseph Stiglitz</ENAMEX> argued that he might reconsider his support for the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> remaining in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> if the proposed <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Transatlantic Trade and Investment Partnership (TTIP)</ENAMEX> were to be agreed to.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P119E1"> <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Stiglitz</ENAMEX> warned that under the investor-state dispute settlement provision in current drafts of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">TTIP</ENAMEX>, governments risked being sued for loss of profits resulting from new regulations, including health and safety regulations to limit the use of asbestos or tobacco.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P120">
				<sentence xml:id="P120E0">The <ENAMEX type="PERSON">German economist Clemens Fuest</ENAMEX> wrote that at present there is a liberal, free trade bloc in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> comprising the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK, the Netherlands, the Czech Republic, Sweden, Denmark, Ireland, Slovakia, Finland, Estonia, Latvia, and  Lithuania</ENAMEX> which control <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">32%</ENAMEX> of the votes in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Council</ENAMEX> and stands in opposition to the dirigiste, protectionist policies favoured by <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX> and its allies.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P120E1"> <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> with its &quot;social market&quot; economy stands midway between the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">French</ENAMEX> dirigiste economic model and the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">British</ENAMEX> free market economic model.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P120E2">From the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">German</ENAMEX> viewpoint, the existence of the liberal bloc allows <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> to play-off free market <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> against dirigiste <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX>, and that if <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> were to leave, the liberal bloc would be severely weakened, thereby allowing the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">French</ENAMEX> to take the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> into a much more dirigiste direction that would be unattractive from the standpoint of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Berlin</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P121">
				<sentence xml:id="P121E0">Institute for Fiscal Studies</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P122">
				<sentence xml:id="P122E0">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">May 2016</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Institute for Fiscal Studies</ENAMEX> said that an <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> exit could mean <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">two more years</ENAMEX> of austerity cuts as the government would have to make up for an estimated loss of <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">£20 billion to £40 billion</ENAMEX> of tax revenue.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P122E1">The <ENAMEX type="PERSON">head of the IFS, Paul Johnson</ENAMEX> said that the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> &quot;could perfectly reasonably decide that we are willing to pay a bit of a price for leaving the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> and regaining some sovereignty and control over immigration and so on.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P122E2">That there would be some price though, I think is now almost beyond doubt.&quot;</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P123">
				<sentence xml:id="P123E0">Centre for Economics and Business Research</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P124">
				<sentence xml:id="P124E0">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">June 2016</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Centre for Economics and Business Research</ENAMEX> warned that <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">800,000</ENAMEX> jobs could be lost if <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> adopted the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">World Trade Organisation (WTO)</ENAMEX> rules for trade with <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX>, which prominent Brexiteers <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Boris Johnson, Michael Gove and Nigel Farage</ENAMEX> said <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> could trade under, if it could not agree a new trade deal with the rest of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P124E1"><ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">WTO</ENAMEX> rules allow tariffs of <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">10 per cent</ENAMEX> on cars, <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">75 per cent</ENAMEX> on tobacco and cigars, <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">22 per cent</ENAMEX> on fruit and <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">12 per cent</ENAMEX> on clothes.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P125">
				<sentence xml:id="P125E0">Law and economics experts</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P126">
				<sentence xml:id="P126E0">A study by <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Oxford Economics</ENAMEX> for the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Law Society of England and Wales</ENAMEX> has suggested that <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX> would have a particularly large negative impact on the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> financial services industry and the law firms that support it, which could cost the law sector as much as <ENUMEX type="MEASURE">£1.7bn</ENUMEX> per annum by <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2030</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P126E1"> The <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Law Society</ENAMEX>&apos;s own report into the possible effects of <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX> notes that leaving the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> would be likely to reduce the role played by the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> as a centre for resolving disputes between foreign firms, whilst a potential loss of &quot;passporting&quot; rights would require financial services firms to transfer departments responsible for regulatory oversight overseas.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P127">
				<sentence xml:id="P127E0"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">World Pensions Forum director M. Nicolas Firzi</ENAMEX> has argued that the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX> debate should be viewed within the broader context of economic analysis of <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">EU law</ENAMEX> and regulation in relation to <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">English</ENAMEX> common law, arguing: &quot;Every year, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">British Parliament</ENAMEX> is forced to pass <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">tens</ENAMEX> of new statutes reflecting the latest <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> directives coming from <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Brussels</ENAMEX> – a highly undemocratic process known as &apos;transposition&apos;...</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P127E1">Slowly but surely, these new laws dictated by <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> commissars are conquering <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">English</ENAMEX> common law, imposing upon <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> businesses and citizens an ever-growing collection of fastidious regulations in every field&quot;.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P128">
				<sentence xml:id="P128E0">A poll of lawyers conducted by a legal recruiter in late <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">May 2016</ENAMEX> suggested <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">57%</ENAMEX> of lawyers wanted to remain in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P129">
				<sentence xml:id="P129E0"><ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">NHS</ENAMEX> officials</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P130">
				<sentence xml:id="P130E0"><ENAMEX type="PERSON">Simon Stevens, head of NHS England</ENAMEX>, warned in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">May 2016</ENAMEX> that a recession following a <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX> would be &quot;very dangerous&quot; for the health service, saying that &quot;when the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">British</ENAMEX> economy sneezes, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">NHS</ENAMEX> catches a cold.&quot;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P130E1"> <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">Three-quarters</ENAMEX> of a sample of <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">NHS</ENAMEX> leaders agreed that leaving the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> would have a negative effect on the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">NHS</ENAMEX> as a whole.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P130E2">In particular, <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">eight out of 10</ENAMEX> respondents felt that leaving the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> would have a negative impact on trusts&apos; ability to recruit health and social care staff.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P130E3"> In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">April 2016</ENAMEX>, a group of nearly <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">200</ENAMEX> health professionals and researchers warned that the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">NHS</ENAMEX> would be in jeopardy if <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> left the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P131">
				<sentence xml:id="P131E0"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> charities</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P132">
				<sentence xml:id="P132E0">Guidelines by the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Charity Commission for England and Wales</ENAMEX> that forbid political activity for registered charities have kept them silent on the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> poll.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P132E1"> According to <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Simon Wessely, head of psychological medicine at the Institute of Psychiatry, King&apos;s College London</ENAMEX> – neither a special revision of the guidelines from <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">7 March 2016</ENAMEX>, nor <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Cameron</ENAMEX>&apos;s encouragement have made health organisations, most of which support the remain campaign, willing to speak out.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P133">
				<sentence xml:id="P133E0">Fishing industry</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P134">
				<sentence xml:id="P134E0">A <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">June 2016</ENAMEX> survey of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> fishermen found that <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">92%</ENAMEX> intended to vote to leave the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P134E1"> The <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>&apos;s <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">Common Fisheries Policy</ENAMEX> was mentioned as a central reason for their near-unanimity.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P134E2"> More than <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">three-quarters</ENAMEX> believed that they would be able to land more fish, and <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">93%</ENAMEX> stated that leaving the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> would benefit the fishing industry.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P135">
				<sentence xml:id="P135E0">Historians</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P136">
				<sentence xml:id="P136E0">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">May 2016</ENAMEX>, more than <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">300</ENAMEX> historians wrote in a joint letter to <ENAMEX type="MEDIA">The Guardian</ENAMEX> that <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> could play a bigger role in the world as part of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P136E1">They said: &quot;As historians of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> and of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX>, we believe that <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> has had in the past, and will have in the future, an irreplaceable role to play in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Europe</ENAMEX>.&quot;</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P137">
				<sentence xml:id="P137E0">Exit plan competition</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P138">
				<sentence xml:id="P138E0">Following <ENAMEX type="PERSON">David Cameron</ENAMEX>&apos;s announcement of an <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> referendum, <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">British</ENAMEX> think tank the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Institute of Economic Affairs (IEA)</ENAMEX> announced in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">July 2013</ENAMEX> a competition to find the best plan for a <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> exit from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX>, declaring that a departure is a &quot;real possibility&quot; after the <ENAMEX type="EVENT">2015 general election</ENAMEX> .</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P138E1"> <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Iain Mansfield, a Cambridge graduate and UKTI diplomat</ENAMEX>, submitted the winning thesis: <ENAMEX type="CREATION">A Blueprint for Britain: Openness not Isolation</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P138E2"> <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Mansfield</ENAMEX>&apos;s submission focused on addressing both trade and regulatory issues with member states as well as other global trading partners.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P139">
				<sentence xml:id="P139E0">Opinion polling</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P140">
				<sentence xml:id="P140E0">Main article: Opinion polling for the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">United Kingdom European Union membership referendum</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P141">
				<sentence xml:id="P141E0">Opinion polling on the referendum</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P142">
				<sentence xml:id="P142E0">Polls from <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2010</ENAMEX> onwards suggested the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">British</ENAMEX> public were relatively evenly divided on the question, with opposition to <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> membership peaking in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">November 2012</ENAMEX> at <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">56%</ENAMEX> compared with <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">30%</ENAMEX> who prefer to remain in, while in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">June 2015</ENAMEX> those in favour of <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Britain</ENAMEX> remaining in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> reached <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">43%</ENAMEX> versus those opposed <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">36%</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P142E1"> The largest ever poll (of <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">20,000</ENAMEX> people, in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">March 2014</ENAMEX>) showed the public evenly split on the issue, with <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">41%</ENAMEX> in favour of withdrawal, <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">41%</ENAMEX> in favour of membership, and <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">18%</ENAMEX> undecided.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P142E2"> However, when asked how they would vote if <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> renegotiated the terms of its membership of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, and the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">UK Government</ENAMEX> stated that <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">British</ENAMEX> interests had been satisfactorily protected, more than <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">50%</ENAMEX> indicated that they would vote for <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> to stay in.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P143">
				<sentence xml:id="P143E0">Analysis of polling suggested that young voters tended to support remaining in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, whereas those older tend to support leaving, but there was no gender split in attitudes.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P143E1"> In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">February 2016</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">YouGov</ENAMEX> also found that <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">euroscepticism</ENAMEX> correlated with people of lower income and that &quot;higher social grades are more clearly in favour of remaining in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>&quot;, but noted that <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">euroscepticism</ENAMEX> also had strongholds in &quot;the more wealthy, Tory shires&quot;.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P143E2"> <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Scotland</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Wales</ENAMEX> and many <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">English urban areas</ENAMEX> with large student populations were more pro-<ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P143E3"> Big business was broadly behind remaining in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, though the situation among smaller companies was less clear cut.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P143E4"> In polls of economists, lawyers, and scientists, clear majorities saw the <ENAMEX type="CONCEPTUAL">UK</ENAMEX>&apos;s membership of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> as beneficial.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P144">
				<sentence xml:id="P144E0">Issues</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P145">
				<sentence xml:id="P145E0">Main article: Issues in the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL">United Kingdom European Union membership referendum, 2016</ENAMEX></sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P146">
				<sentence xml:id="P146E0">The number of jobs lost or gained by a withdrawal was a dominant issue; the <ENAMEX type="MEDIA">BBC</ENAMEX>&apos;s outline of issues warned that a precise figure was difficult to find.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P146E1">The <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Leave campaign</ENAMEX> argued that a reduction in red tape associated with <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> regulations would create more jobs and that small to medium-sized companies who trade domestically would be the biggest beneficiaries.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P146E2">Those arguing to remain in the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, claimed that <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">millions</ENAMEX> of jobs would be lost.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P146E3">The <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>&apos;s importance as a trading partner and the outcome of its trade status if it left was a disputed issue.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P146E4">Whilst those wanting to stay cited that most of the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>&apos;s trade was made with the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, those arguing to leave say that its trade was not as important as it used to be.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P146E5">Scenarios of the economic outlook for the country if it left the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> were generally negative.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P146E6">The <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">United Kingdom</ENAMEX> also paid more into the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> budget than it received.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P147">
				<sentence xml:id="P147E0">Citizens of <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> countries, including the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">United Kingdom</ENAMEX>, have the right to travel, live and work within other <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> countries, as free movement is one of the <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">four</ENAMEX> founding principles of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P147E1"> Campaigners for remaining said that <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> immigration had positive impacts on the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>&apos;s economy, citing that the country&apos;s growth forecasts were partly based upon continued high levels of net immigration.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P147E2"> The <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Office for Budget Responsibility</ENAMEX> also claimed that taxes from immigrants boost public funding.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P147E3"> The <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Leave campaign</ENAMEX>believed reduced immigration would ease pressure in public services such as schools and hospitals, as well as giving <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL">British</ENAMEX> workers more jobs and higher wages.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P147E4"> According to <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">official Office for National Statistics</ENAMEX> data, net migration in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">2015</ENAMEX> was <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">333,000</ENAMEX>, which was the <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">second</ENAMEX> highest level on record, far above <ENAMEX type="PERSON">David Cameron</ENAMEX>&apos;s target of <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">tens of thousands</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P147E5"> Net migration from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> was <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">184,000</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P147E6"> The figures also showed that <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">77,000</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX> migrants who came to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> were looking for work.</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P148">
				<sentence xml:id="P148E0">After the announcement had been made as to the outcome of the referendum, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Rowena Mason</ENAMEX>, political correspondent for <ENAMEX type="MEDIA">The Guardian</ENAMEX> offered the following assessment: &quot;Polling suggests discontent with the scale of migration to the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX> has been the biggest factor pushing <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE">Britons</ENAMEX> to vote out, with the contest turning into a referendum on whether people are happy to accept free movement in return for free trade.&quot;</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P148E1"> A columnist for <ENAMEX type="MEDIA">The Times</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Philip Collins</ENAMEX>, went a step further in his analysis: &quot;This was a referendum about immigration disguised as a referendum about the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">European Union</ENAMEX>.&quot;</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P149">
				<sentence xml:id="P149E0">The <ENAMEX type="TITLE">Conservative MEP (Member of the European Parliament)</ENAMEX> representing <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">South East England</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON">Daniel Hannan</ENAMEX>, predicted on the <ENAMEX type="CREATION">BBC program Newsnight</ENAMEX> that the level of immigration would remain high after <ENAMEX type="EVENT">Brexit</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P149E1"> &quot;Frankly, if people watching think that they have voted and there is now going to be <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">zero</ENAMEX> immigration from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">EU</ENAMEX>, they are going to be disappointed.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P149E2">...</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P149E3">you will look in vain for anything that the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Leave campaign</ENAMEX> said at any point that ever suggested there would ever be any kind of border closure or drawing up of the drawbridge.&quot;</sentence>
			</p>
			<p xml:lang="en" xml:id="P150">
