<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<corpus>
	<subcorpus>
		<document name="wikipedia.ner26.train">

			<paragraph xml:id="P0">
				<sentence xml:id="P0E1"><ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">World War I</ENAMEX> - <ENAMEX type="WEBSITE" subtype="information_web_site/N1">Wikipedia</ENAMEX>, the free encyclopedia</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E2"><ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">World War I</ENAMEX></sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E3">From <ENAMEX type="WEBSITE" subtype="information_web_site/N1">Wikipedia</ENAMEX>, the free encyclopedia</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E4"><ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">World War I ( WWI )</ENAMEX> was a global war centred in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="supernational_region/N1">Europe</ENAMEX> that began on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">28 July 1914</ENAMEX> and lasted <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">until 11 November 1918</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E5">It was predominantly called the World War or the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Great War</ENAMEX> from its occurrence until the start of <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">World War II</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1939</ENAMEX>, and the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">First World War</ENAMEX> or <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">World War I</ENAMEX> thereafter.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E6">It involved all the world ' s great powers, which were assembled in <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">two</ENAMEX> opposing alliances: the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="INSTITUTION">Allies</ENAMEX> ( based on the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL" subtype="O">Triple Entente of the United Kingdom, France and the Russian Empire</ENAMEX> ) and the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">Central Powers of Germany and Austria - Hungary</ENAMEX></sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E7">Although <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Italy</ENAMEX> had also been a member of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">Triple Alliance</ENAMEX> alongside <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany and Austria - Hungary</ENAMEX>, it did not join the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">Central Powers</ENAMEX>, as <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">Austria - Hungary</ENAMEX> had taken the offensive against the terms of the alliance.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E8">These alliances were both reorganised and expanded as more nations entered the war: <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Italy, Japan and the United States</ENAMEX> joined the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">Allies</ENAMEX>, and the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">Ottoman Empire and Bulgaria</ENAMEX> the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">Central Powers</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E9">Ultimately, more than <ENAMEX type="MEASURE" subtype="rational_number/N1">70 million</ENAMEX> military personnel, including <ENAMEX type="MEASURE" subtype="rational_number/N1">60 million</ENAMEX><ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1">Europeans</ENAMEX>, were mobilised in one of the largest wars in history.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E10">More than <ENAMEX type="MEASURE" subtype="rational_number/N1">9 million</ENAMEX> combatants were killed, largely because of technological advancements that led to enormous increases in the lethality of weapons without corresponding improvements in protection or mobility, causing both sides to resort to large - scale human wave attacks, which proved extremely costly in terms of casualties.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E11">It was the <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">fifth</ENAMEX> - deadliest conflict in world history, subsequently paving the way for various political changes, such as revolutions in many of the nations involved.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E12">One of the long - term causes of the war was the resurgence of <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">imperialism</ENAMEX> in the foreign policies of the great powers of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="supernational_region/N1">Europe</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E13">More immediately, the assassination of <ENAMEX type="PERSON" subtype="aristocratic_title/N1">Archduke Franz Ferdinand of Austria</ENAMEX>, the heir to the throne of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">Austria - Hungary</ENAMEX>, on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">28 June 1914</ENAMEX> by the <ENAMEX type="PERSON" subtype="criminal/N1">Yugoslav nationalist Gavrilo Princip</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="municipality/N1">Sarajevo</ENAMEX> triggered a diplomatic crisis when <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">Austria - Hungary</ENAMEX> subsequently delivered an ultimatum to the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">Kingdom of Serbia</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E14">Several alliances formed over the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">previous decades</ENAMEX> were invoked.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E15">Within <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">weeks</ENAMEX>, the major powers were at war and, via their colonies, the conflict soon spread around the world.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E16">On <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">28 July</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">Austro - Hungarians</ENAMEX> fired the first shots of the war as preparation for the invasion of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Serbia</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E17">While the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1">Russians</ENAMEX> mobilised, the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1">Germans</ENAMEX> invaded neutral <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Belgium and Luxembourg</ENAMEX> on the way to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">France</ENAMEX>, providing a casus belli for <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Britain</ENAMEX> ' s declaration of war against <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX></sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E18">After the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">German march on Paris</ENAMEX> was brought to a halt - - the so - called <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Miracle of the Marne</ENAMEX> - - the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="supernational_region/N1">Western Front</ENAMEX> settled into a static battle of attrition with a trench line that changed little until</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E19">On the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="supernational_region/N1">Eastern Front</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Russian army</ENAMEX> was successful against the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="historical_country/N1">Austro - Hungarians</ENAMEX>, but was stopped in its invasion of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">East Prussia</ENAMEX> by the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1">Germans</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E20">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">November</ENAMEX> the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">Ottoman Empire</ENAMEX> joined the war, opening up fronts in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="other_non-political_region/N1">Caucasus, Mesopotamia and the Sinai</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E21"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Italy and Bulgaria</ENAMEX> went to war in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1915</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Romania</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1916</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E22">In <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Russia</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">tsar's government</ENAMEX> collapsed in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">March 1917</ENAMEX> and a subsequent revolution in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="military_action/N1">November</ENAMEX> brought the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1">Russians</ENAMEX> to terms with the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">Central Powers</ENAMEX></sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E23">After a <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1918</ENAMEX><ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1">German</ENAMEX> offensive along the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">western front</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Allies</ENAMEX> drove back the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1">Germans</ENAMEX> in a series of successful offensives and <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">American forces</ENAMEX> began entering the trenches.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E24"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX>, which had its own trouble with revolutionaries, agreed to an armistice on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">11 November 1918</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E25">The war ended in victory for the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Allies</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E26">Events on the home fronts were as tumultuous as on the battle fronts, as the participants tried to mobilise their manpower and economic resources to fight a total war.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E27">By the end of the war, <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">four</ENAMEX> major imperial powers - - the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">German, Russian, Austro - Hungarian and Ottoman empires</ENAMEX> - - ceased to battle.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E28">The successor states of the former <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">two</ENAMEX> lost a great amount of territory, while the latter <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">two</ENAMEX> were dismantled entirely.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E29">The map of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="supernational_region/N1">central Europe</ENAMEX> was redrawn into several smaller states.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E30">The <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">League of Nations</ENAMEX> was formed in the hope of preventing another such conflict.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E31">The <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="regional_cultural_adjective/J1">European</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">nationalism</ENAMEX> spawned by the war, weak new nations, and the humiliation of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> ' s defeat were factors contributing to the rise of the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="member_of_a_political_group/N1">Nazis</ENAMEX> and the start of <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">World War II</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E32">In <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Canada</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="MEDIA" subtype="periodical/N1">Maclean ' s Magazine</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">October 1914</ENAMEX> said, " Some wars name themselves</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E33">This is the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Great War</ENAMEX>. "</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E34">A history of the origins and <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">early months</ENAMEX> of the war published in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="municipality/N1">New York</ENAMEX> in  <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">late 1914</ENAMEX> was titled <ENAMEX type="CREATION" subtype="O">The World War</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E35">During the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">Interwar period</ENAMEX>, the war was most often called the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">World War and the Great War</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">English</ENAMEX> - speaking countries.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E36">After the onset of the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Second World War</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1939</ENAMEX>, the terms <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">World War I</ENAMEX> or the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">First World War</ENAMEX> became standard, with <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">British and Canadian</ENAMEX> historians favouring the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">First World War</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1">Americans</ENAMEX><ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">World War I</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E37">The term " <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">First World War</ENAMEX> " was first used in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">September 1914</ENAMEX> by the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">German</ENAMEX> philosopher <ENAMEX type="PERSON" subtype="intellectual/N1">Ernst Haeckel</ENAMEX>, who claimed that " there is no doubt that the course and character of the feared ' <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="O">European War</ENAMEX> '... will become the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="O">first world war</ENAMEX> in the full sense of the word. " The <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">First World</ENAMEX> was also the title of a <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1920</ENAMEX> history by the <ENAMEX type="TITLE">officer</ENAMEX> and journalist <ENAMEX type="PERSON" subtype="writer/N1">Charles Court</ENAMEX></sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E38">Background</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E39">Main article:</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E40">Causes of <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">World War I</ENAMEX></sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E41">In the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="O">19th century</ENAMEX>, the major <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="regional_cultural_adjective/J1">European</ENAMEX> powers had gone to great lengths to maintain a balance of power throughout <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="supernational_region/N1">Europe</ENAMEX>, resulting in the existence of a complex network of political and military alliances throughout the continent by <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1900</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E42">These had started in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1815</ENAMEX>, with the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="interest_or_advocacy_group/N1">Holy Alliance</ENAMEX> between <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Prussia, Russia, and Austria</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E43">Then, in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">October 1873</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">German Chancellor Otto von Bismarck</ENAMEX> negotiated the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">League of the Three Emperors</ENAMEX> ( <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT" subtype="O">German</ENAMEX>: <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Dreikaiserbund</ENAMEX> ) between the monarchs of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">Austria - Hungary, Russia and Germany</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E44">This agreement failed because <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">Austria - Hungary and Russia</ENAMEX> could not agree over <ENAMEX type="LEGAL" subtype="regional_cultural_adjective/J1">Balkan policy</ENAMEX>, leaving <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany and Austria - Hungary</ENAMEX> in an alliance formed in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1879</ENAMEX>, called the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">Dual Alliance</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E45">This was seen as a method of countering <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Russian</ENAMEX> influence in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="peninsula/N1">Balkans</ENAMEX> as the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">Ottoman Empire</ENAMEX> continued to weaken.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E46">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1882</ENAMEX>, this alliance was expanded to include <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Italy</ENAMEX> in what became the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Triple Alliance</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E47"><ENAMEX type="PERSON" subtype="politician/N2">Bismarck</ENAMEX> had especially worked to hold <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Russia</ENAMEX> at <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> ' s side to avoid a <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">two</ENAMEX> - front war with <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">France and Russia</ENAMEX></sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E48">When <ENAMEX type="PERSON" subtype="aristocratic_ruler/N1">Wilhelm II</ENAMEX> ascended to the throne as <ENAMEX type="TITLE" subtype="O">German Emperor ( Kaiser )</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON" subtype="politician/N2">Bismarck</ENAMEX> was compelled to retire and his system of alliances was gradually de - emphasised.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E49">For example, the <ENAMEX type="TITLE" subtype="aristocratic_title/N1">Kaiser</ENAMEX> refused to renew the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL" subtype="O">Reinsurance Treaty</ENAMEX> with <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Russia</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1890</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E50"><ENAMEX type="PERIOD">Two years later</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL" subtype="O">Franco - Russian Alliance</ENAMEX> was signed to counteract the force of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Triple Alliance</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E51">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1904</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Britain</ENAMEX> signed a series of agreements with <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">France</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">Entente Cordiale</ENAMEX>, and in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1907</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Britain</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Russia</ENAMEX> signed the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL" subtype="O">Anglo - Russian Convention</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E52">While these agreements did not formally ally <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Britain with France or Russia</ENAMEX>, they made <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">British</ENAMEX> entry into any future conflict involving <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">France or Russia</ENAMEX> probable, and the system of interlocking bilateral agreements became known as the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">Triple Entente</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E53"><ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">German</ENAMEX> industrial and economic power had grown greatly after unification and the foundation of the Empire in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1871</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E54">From the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">mid - 1890s</ENAMEX> on, the government of <ENAMEX type="PERSON" subtype="O">Wilhelm II</ENAMEX> used this base to devote significant economic resources for building up the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Kaiserliche Marine ( Imperial German Navy )</ENAMEX>, established by <ENAMEX type="PERSON" subtype="O">Admiral Alfred von Tirpitz</ENAMEX>, in rivalry with the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">British Royal Navy</ENAMEX> for world naval supremacy.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E55">As a result, each nation strove to out - build the other in terms of capital ships.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E56">With the launch of <ENAMEX type="ARTIFACT" subtype="O">HMS Dreadnought</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1906</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">British Empire</ENAMEX> expanded on its significant advantage over its <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">German</ENAMEX> rival.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E57">The arms race between <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Britain and Germany</ENAMEX> eventually extended to the rest of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="supernational_region/N1">Europe</ENAMEX>, with all the major powers devoting their industrial base to producing the equipment and weapons necessary for a pan - <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="regional_cultural_adjective/J1">European</ENAMEX> conflict.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E58"><ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">Between 1908 and 1913</ENAMEX>, the military spending of the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="regional_cultural_adjective/J1">European</ENAMEX> powers increased by <ENAMEX type="MEASURE" subtype="percentage/N1">50%</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E59"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">Austria - Hungary</ENAMEX> precipitated the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="O">Bosnian crisis of 1908 - 1909</ENAMEX> by officially annexing the former <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="O">Ottoman</ENAMEX> territory of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Bosnia and Herzegovina</ENAMEX>, which it had occupied since <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1878</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E60">This angered the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">Kingdom of Serbia</ENAMEX> and its patron, the <ENAMEX type="CONCEPTUAL" subtype="O">Pan - Slavic</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Orthodox Russian Empire</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E61"><ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Russian</ENAMEX> political manoeuvring in the region destabilised peace accords, which were already fracturing in what was known as " the powder keg of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="supernational_region/N1">Europe</ENAMEX> ".</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E62">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1912 and 1913</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">First Balkan War</ENAMEX> was fought between the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">Balkan League</ENAMEX> and the fracturing <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">Ottoman Empire</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E63">The resulting <ENAMEX type="LEGAL" subtype="agreement/N1">Treaty of London</ENAMEX> further shrank the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">Ottoman Empire</ENAMEX>, creating an independent <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Albanian</ENAMEX> State while enlarging the territorial holdings of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Bulgaria, Serbia, Montenegro, and Greece</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E64">When <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Bulgaria</ENAMEX> attacked both <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Serbia and Greece</ENAMEX> on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">16 June 1913</ENAMEX>, it lost most of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Macedonia to Serbia and Greece and Southern Dobruja to Romania</ENAMEX> in the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="O">33 - day Second Balkan War</ENAMEX>, further destabilising the region.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E65"><ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="O">July 1914 crisis</ENAMEX></sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E66">Main article:</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E67"><ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="O">July Crisis</ENAMEX></sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E68">On <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">28 June 1914</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON" subtype="criminal/N1">Gavrilo Princip</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Bosnian Serb</ENAMEX> student and member of <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION">Young Bosnia</ENAMEX>, assassinated the heir to the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Austro - Hungarian</ENAMEX> throne, <ENAMEX type="PERSON" subtype="O">Archduke Franz Ferdinand of Austria</ENAMEX>, in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="O">Sarajevo, Bosnia</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E69">This began a month of diplomatic manoeuvring between <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">Austria - Hungary, Germany, Russia, France, and Britain</ENAMEX> called the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="O">July Crisis</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E70">Wanting to finally end <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Serbian</ENAMEX> interference in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Bosnia</ENAMEX> - the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION" subtype="non-political_criminal_organization/N1">Black Hand</ENAMEX> had provided <ENAMEX type="PERSON" subtype="criminal/N1">Princip</ENAMEX> and his group with their bombs and pistols, trained them, and helped them across the border, and the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1">Austrians</ENAMEX> were correct to believe that <ENAMEX type="TITLE" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Serbian officers</ENAMEX> and officials were involved - <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">Austria - Hungary</ENAMEX> delivered the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="O">July Ultimatum</ENAMEX> to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Serbia</ENAMEX>, a series of <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">ten</ENAMEX> demands intentionally made unacceptable, intending to provoke a war with <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Serbia</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E71">When <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Serbia</ENAMEX> agreed to only <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">eight of the ten</ENAMEX> demands, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">Austria - Hungary</ENAMEX> declared war on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">28 July 1914</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E72"><ENAMEX type="PERSON" subtype="intellectual/N1">Strachan</ENAMEX> argues, " Whether an equivocal and early response by <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Serbia</ENAMEX> would have made any difference to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">Austria - Hungary</ENAMEX> ' s behaviour must be doubtful</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E73"><ENAMEX type="PERSON" subtype="aristocratic_ruler/N1">Franz Ferdinand</ENAMEX> was not the sort of personality who commanded popularity, and his demise did not cast the empire into deepest mourning ".</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E74">The <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">Russian Empire</ENAMEX>, unwilling to allow <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">Austria - Hungary</ENAMEX> to eliminate its influence in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="supernational_region/N1">Balkans</ENAMEX>, and in support of its longtime <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="O">Serb</ENAMEX> proteges, ordered a partial mobilisation <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">one day later</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E75">The <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">German Empire</ENAMEX> mobilised on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">30 July 1914</ENAMEX>, ready to apply the " <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT" subtype="O">Schlieffen Plan</ENAMEX> ", which planned a quick, massive invasion of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">France</ENAMEX> to eliminate the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">French army</ENAMEX>, then to turn east against <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Russia</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E76">The <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION">French cabinet</ENAMEX> resisted military pressure to commence immediate mobilisation, and ordered its troops to withdraw <ENAMEX type="MEASURE" subtype="rational_number/N1">10 km</ENAMEX> from the border to avoid any incident.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E77"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">France</ENAMEX> only mobilised on the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">evening of 2 August</ENAMEX>, when <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> invaded <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Belgium</ENAMEX> and attacked <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">French</ENAMEX> troops.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E78"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> declared war on <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Russia</ENAMEX> on the same day.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E79"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Britain</ENAMEX> declared war on <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">4 August 1914</ENAMEX>, following an " unsatisfactory reply " to the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">British</ENAMEX> ultimatum that <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Belgium</ENAMEX> must be kept neutral.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E80">Progress of the war</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E81">Opening hostilities</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E82">Confusion among the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">Central Powers</ENAMEX></sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E83">The strategy of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">Central Powers</ENAMEX> suffered from miscommunication.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E84"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> had promised to support <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">Austria - Hungary</ENAMEX> ' s invasion of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Serbia</ENAMEX>, but interpretations of what this meant differed</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E85">Previously tested deployment plans had been replaced early in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1914</ENAMEX>, but the replacements had never been tested in exercises.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E86"><ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Austro - Hungarian</ENAMEX> leaders believed <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> would cover its northern flank against <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Russia</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E87"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX>, however, envisioned <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">Austria - Hungary</ENAMEX> directing most of its troops against <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Russia</ENAMEX>, while <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> dealt with <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">France</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E88">This confusion forced the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Austro - Hungarian Army</ENAMEX> to divide its forces between the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Russian and Serbian</ENAMEX> fronts.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E89">On <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">9 September 1914</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="UNKNOWN" subtype="O">Septemberprogramm</ENAMEX>, a possible plan that detailed <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> ' s specific war aims and the conditions that <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> sought to force on the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Allied</ENAMEX> Powers, was outlined by the <ENAMEX type="PERSON" subtype="O">German Chancellor, Theobald von Bethmann - Hollweg</ENAMEX></sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E90">It was never officially adopted.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E91"><ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Serbian</ENAMEX> campaign</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E92">Main article:</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E93"><ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Serbian</ENAMEX> Campaign ( <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">World War I</ENAMEX> )</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E94"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Austria</ENAMEX> invaded and fought the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Serbian army</ENAMEX> at the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Battle of Cer and Battle of Kolubara</ENAMEX> beginning on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">12 August</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E95">Over the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">next two weeks</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Austrian</ENAMEX> attacks were thrown back with heavy losses, which marked the first major <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="organization_adjective/J1">Allied</ENAMEX> victories of the war and dashed <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="O">Austro - Hungarian</ENAMEX> hopes of a swift victory.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E96">As a result, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Austria</ENAMEX> had to keep sizable forces on the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Serbian</ENAMEX> front, weakening its efforts against <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Russia</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E97"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Serbia</ENAMEX> ' s defeat of the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Austro - Hungarian</ENAMEX> invasion of <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1914</ENAMEX> counts among the major upset victories of the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">last century</ENAMEX></sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E98"><ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">German forces</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Belgium and France</ENAMEX></sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E99">Main article:</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E100"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="military_action/N1">Western Front</ENAMEX> ( <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">World War I</ENAMEX> )</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E101">At the outbreak of <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">World War I</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">German army</ENAMEX> ( consisting in the West of <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">seven</ENAMEX> field armies ) carried out a modified version of the <ENAMEX type="UNKNOWN" subtype="O">Schlieffen Plan</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E102">This marched <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">German</ENAMEX> armies through neutral <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Belgium</ENAMEX> and into <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">France</ENAMEX>, before turning southwards to encircle the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">French army</ENAMEX> on the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">German</ENAMEX> border.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E103">Since <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">France</ENAMEX> had declared that it would " keep full freedom of acting in case of a war between <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany and Russia</ENAMEX> ", <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> had to expect the possibility of an attack by <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">France</ENAMEX> on one front and by <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Russia</ENAMEX> on the other.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E104">To meet such a scenario, the <ENAMEX type="UNKNOWN" subtype="O">Schlieffen Plan</ENAMEX> stated that <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> must try to defeat <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">France</ENAMEX> quickly ( as had happened in the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Franco - Prussian War of 1870 - 71</ENAMEX> ).</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E105">It further suggested that to repeat a fast victory in the west, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> should not attack through the difficult terrain of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">Alsace - Lorraine</ENAMEX> ( which had a direct border west of the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="delimited_body_of_water/N1">river Rhine</ENAMEX> ), instead, the idea was to try to quickly cut <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="municipality/N1">Paris</ENAMEX> off from the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="delimited_body_of_water/N1">English Channel</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">British</ENAMEX> assistance, and take <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="municipality/N1">Paris</ENAMEX>, thus winning the war.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E106">Then the armies would be moved over to the east to meet <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Russia</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E107"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Russia</ENAMEX> was believed to need a long period of mobilisation before they could become a real threat to the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">Central Powers</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E108">The only existing <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">German</ENAMEX> plan for any war had <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">German</ENAMEX> armies marching through <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Belgium</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E109"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> wanted free escort through <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Belgium</ENAMEX> ( and originally the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Netherlands</ENAMEX> as well, which plan <ENAMEX type="TITLE" subtype="aristocratic_title/N1">Kaiser Wilhelm II</ENAMEX> rejected ) to invade <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">France</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E110">Neutral <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Belgium</ENAMEX> rejected this idea, so the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1">Germans</ENAMEX> decided to invade through <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Belgium</ENAMEX> instead.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E111"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">France</ENAMEX> also wanted to move their troops into <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Belgium</ENAMEX>, but <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Belgium</ENAMEX> originally rejected this " suggestion " as well, in the hope of avoiding any war on <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Belgian</ENAMEX> soil.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E112">In the end, after the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">German</ENAMEX> invasion, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Belgium</ENAMEX> did try to join their army with the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">French</ENAMEX> ( but a large part of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Belgian army</ENAMEX> retreated to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="municipality/N1">Antwerp</ENAMEX> where they were forced to surrender when all hope of help was gone ).</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E113">The plan called for the right flank of the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">German</ENAMEX> advance to bypass the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">French</ENAMEX> armies ( which were concentrated on the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Franco - German</ENAMEX> border, leaving the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Belgian</ENAMEX> border without significant <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">French</ENAMEX> forces ) and move south to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="municipality/N1">Paris</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E114">Initially the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1">Germans</ENAMEX> were successful, particularly in the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Battle of the Frontiers ( 14 - 24 August )</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E115">By <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">12 September</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">French</ENAMEX>, with assistance from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">British forces</ENAMEX>, halted the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">German</ENAMEX> advance east of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="municipality/N1">Paris</ENAMEX> at the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">First Battle of the Marne ( 5 - 12 September )</ENAMEX>, and pushed the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">German forces</ENAMEX> back some <ENAMEX type="MEASURE" subtype="rational_number/N1">50 km</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E116">The <ENAMEX type="PERIOD">last days</ENAMEX> of this battle signified the end of mobile warfare in the west.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E117">The <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">French</ENAMEX> offensive into <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="O">Southern Alsace</ENAMEX>, launched on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">20 August</ENAMEX> with the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Battle of Mulhouse</ENAMEX>, had limited success.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E118">In the east, the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1">Russians</ENAMEX> invaded with <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">two</ENAMEX> armies, surprising the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">German</ENAMEX> staff who had not expected the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1">Russians</ENAMEX> to move so early.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E119">A field army, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">8th</ENAMEX>, was rapidly moved from its previous role as reserve for the invasion of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">France, to East Prussia</ENAMEX> by rail across the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">German Empire</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E120">This army, led by general <ENAMEX type="PERSON" subtype="politician/N2">Paul von Hindenburg</ENAMEX> defeated <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Russia</ENAMEX> in a series of battles collectively known as the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">First Battle of Tannenberg ( 17 August - 2 September )</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E121">But the failed <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Russian</ENAMEX> invasion, causing the fresh <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">German</ENAMEX> troops to move to the east, allowed the tactical <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Allied</ENAMEX> victory at the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">First Battle of the Marne</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E122">The <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">Central Powers</ENAMEX> were denied a quick victory in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">France</ENAMEX> and forced to fight a war on <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">two</ENAMEX> fronts.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E123">The <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">German</ENAMEX> army had fought its way into a good defensive position inside <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">France</ENAMEX> and had permanently incapacitated <ENAMEX type="MEASURE" subtype="rational_number/N1">230, 000</ENAMEX> more <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">French</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">British</ENAMEX> troops than it had lost</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E124">Despite this, communications problems and questionable command decisions cost <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> the chance of early victory.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E125"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="supernational_region/N1">Asia and the Pacific</ENAMEX></sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E126">Main article:</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E127"><ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="regional_cultural_adjective/J1">Asian</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="O">Pacific</ENAMEX> theatre of <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">World War I</ENAMEX></sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E128"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">New Zealand occupied German Samoa</ENAMEX> ( later <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Western Samoa</ENAMEX> ) on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">30 August 1914</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E129">On <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="historical_event/N1">11 September</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Australian Naval and Military Expeditionary Force</ENAMEX> landed on the island of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="island/N1">Neu Pommern</ENAMEX> ( later <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="island/N1">New Britain</ENAMEX> ), which formed part of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">German New Guinea</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E130">On <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">28 October</ENAMEX>, the cruiser <ENAMEX type="ARTIFACT" subtype="vessel/N2">SMS Emden</ENAMEX> sank the <ENAMEX type="ARTIFACT" subtype="O">Russian cruiser Zhemchug</ENAMEX> in the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Battle of Penang</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E131"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Japan</ENAMEX> seized <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> ' s <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Micronesian</ENAMEX> colonies and, after the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Siege of Tsingtao</ENAMEX>, the coaling <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="O">port of Qingdao</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="O">Chinese Shandong peninsula</ENAMEX></sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E132">As <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="municipality/N1">Vienna</ENAMEX> refused to withdraw the <ENAMEX type="ARTIFACT" subtype="O">Austro - Hungarian cruiser " Kaiserin Elisabeth "</ENAMEX> from <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="O">Tsingtao</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Japan</ENAMEX> declared war not only on <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX>, but also on <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">Austria - Hungary</ENAMEX>; the ship participated in the defense of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="O">Tsingtao</ENAMEX> where it was sunk in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">November 1914</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E133">Within a few months, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Allied forces</ENAMEX> had seized all the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">German</ENAMEX> territories in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="O">Pacific</ENAMEX>; only isolated commerce raiders and a few holdouts in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="island/N1">New Guinea</ENAMEX> remained.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E134"><ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="regional_cultural_adjective/J1">African</ENAMEX> campaigns</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E135">Main article:</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E136"><ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="O">African</ENAMEX> theatre of <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">World War I</ENAMEX></sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E137">Some of the first clashes of the war involved <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">British, French, and German</ENAMEX> colonial forces in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="supernational_region/N1">Africa</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E138">On <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">7 August</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">French and British</ENAMEX> troops invaded the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">German protectorate of Togoland</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E139">On <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">10 August</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">German forces</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">South - West Africa</ENAMEX> attacked <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">South Africa</ENAMEX>; sporadic and fierce fighting continued for the rest of the war.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E140">The <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">German</ENAMEX> colonial forces in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="state/N2">German East Africa</ENAMEX>, led by <ENAMEX type="PERSON" subtype="O">Colonel Paul von Lettow - Vorbeck</ENAMEX>, fought a guerrilla warfare campaign during <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">World War I</ENAMEX> and only surrendered <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="O">two weeks after the armistice</ENAMEX> took effect in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="supernational_region/N1">Europe</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E141"><ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Indian</ENAMEX> support for the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Allies</ENAMEX></sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E142">Further information:</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E143"><ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Third Anglo - Afghan War</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX type="UNKNOWN" subtype="religious_adjective/J1">Hindu - German Conspiracy</ENAMEX></sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E144">Contrary to <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">British</ENAMEX> fears of a revolt in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">India</ENAMEX>, the outbreak of the war saw an unprecedented outpouring of loyalty and goodwill towards <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Britain</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E145"><ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Indian</ENAMEX> political leaders from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Indian National Congress</ENAMEX> and other groups were eager to support the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">British</ENAMEX> war effort, since they believed that strong support for the war effort would further the cause of <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION" subtype="O">Indian Home Rule</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E146">The <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Indian Army</ENAMEX> in fact outnumbered the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="military_organization/N1">British Army</ENAMEX> at the beginning of the war; about <ENAMEX type="MEASURE" subtype="rational_number/N1">1. 3 million</ENAMEX><ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Indian</ENAMEX> soldiers and labourers served in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="supernational_region/N1">Europe, Africa, and the Middle East</ENAMEX>, while both the central government and the princely states sent large supplies of food, money, and</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E147">In all, <ENAMEX type="MEASURE" subtype="rational_number/N1">140, 000</ENAMEX> men served on the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="O">Western Front</ENAMEX> and nearly <ENAMEX type="MEASURE" subtype="rational_number/N1">700, 000</ENAMEX> in</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E148">Casualties of <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Indian</ENAMEX> soldiers totalled <ENAMEX type="MEASURE" subtype="rational_number/N1">47, 746</ENAMEX> killed and <ENAMEX type="MEASURE" subtype="rational_number/N1">65, 126</ENAMEX> wounded</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E149">The suffering engendered by the war, as well as the failure of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">British government</ENAMEX> to grant self - government to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">India</ENAMEX> after the end of hostilities, bred disillusionment and fuelled the campaign for full independence that would be led by <ENAMEX type="PERSON" subtype="religious_figure/N1">Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi</ENAMEX> and others.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E150"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="O">Western Front</ENAMEX></sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E151">Main article:</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E152"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="O">Western Front</ENAMEX> ( <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">World War I</ENAMEX> )</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E153"><ENAMEX type="EVENT">Trench warfare</ENAMEX> begins ( <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1914 - 1915</ENAMEX> )</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E154">Military tactics before <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">World War I</ENAMEX> had failed to keep pace with advances in technology.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E155">These advances allowed for impressive defence systems, which out - of - date military tactics could not break through for most of the war.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E156">Barbed wire was a significant hindrance to massed infantry advances.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E157">Artillery, vastly more lethal than in the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1870s</ENAMEX>, coupled with machine guns, made crossing open ground extremely difficult.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E158"><ENAMEX type="TITLE">Commanders</ENAMEX> on both sides failed to develop tactics for breaching entrenched positions without heavy casualties.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E159">In time, however, technology began to produce new offensive weapons, such as gas warfare and the tank.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E160">After the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">First Battle of the Marne ( 5 - 12 September 1914 )</ENAMEX>, both <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">Entente and German forces</ENAMEX> began a series of outflanking manoeuvres, in the so - called " <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Race to the Sea</ENAMEX> ".</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E161"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Britain and France</ENAMEX> soon found themselves facing an uninterrupted line of entrenched <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">German forces</ENAMEX> from <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="O">Lorraine to Belgium ' s coast</ENAMEX></sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E162"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Britain and France</ENAMEX> sought to take the offensive, while <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> defended the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">occupied territories</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E163">Consequently, <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">German</ENAMEX> trenches were much better constructed than those of their enemy; <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="O">Anglo - French</ENAMEX> trenches were only intended to be " temporary " before their forces broke through <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">German</ENAMEX> defences.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E164">Both sides tried to break the stalemate using scientific and technological advances.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E165">On <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">22 April 1915</ENAMEX>, at the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Second Battle of Ypres</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1">Germans</ENAMEX> ( violating the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL" subtype="O">Hague Convention</ENAMEX> ) used chlorine gas for the <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">first</ENAMEX> time on the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="military_action/N1">Western Front</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E166">Several types of gas soon became widely used by both sides, and though it never proved a decisive, battle - winning weapon, poison gas became one of the most - feared and best - remembered horrors of the war.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E167">Tanks were first used in combat by the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">British</ENAMEX> during the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Battle of Flers - Courcelette</ENAMEX> ( part of the wider <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Somme offensive</ENAMEX> ) on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">15 September 1916</ENAMEX>, with only partial success.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E168">However, their effectiveness would grow as the war progressed; the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1">Germans</ENAMEX> employed only very small numbers of their own design, supplemented by captured <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Allied</ENAMEX> tanks.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E169">Trench warfare continues ( <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1916 - 1917</ENAMEX> )</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E170">Neither side proved able to deliver a decisive blow for the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="O">next two years</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E171">Throughout <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1915 - 17</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">British Empire and France</ENAMEX> suffered more casualties than <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX>, because of both the strategic and tactical stances chosen by the sides.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E172">Strategically, while the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1">Germans</ENAMEX> only mounted one major offensive, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Allies</ENAMEX> made several attempts to break through the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="O">German</ENAMEX> lines.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E173">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">February 1916</ENAMEX> the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1">Germans</ENAMEX> attacked the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">French</ENAMEX> defensive positions at <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="O">Verdun</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E174">Running <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">until December 1916</ENAMEX>, the battle saw initial <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">German</ENAMEX> gains, before <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">French</ENAMEX> counterattacks returned matters to near their starting point.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E175">Casualties were greater for the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">French</ENAMEX>, but the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1">Germans</ENAMEX> bled heavily as well, with anywhere from <ENAMEX type="MEASURE" subtype="rational_number/N1">700, 000 to 975, 000</ENAMEX> casualties suffered between</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E176"><ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Verdun</ENAMEX> became a symbol of <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">French</ENAMEX> determination and self - sacrifice.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E177">The <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Battle of the Somme</ENAMEX> was an <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="O">Anglo - French</ENAMEX> offensive that ran <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">from July to November 1916</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E178">The opening of this offensive ( <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1 July 1916</ENAMEX> ) saw the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">British Army</ENAMEX> endure the bloodiest day in its history, suffering <ENAMEX type="MEASURE" subtype="rational_number/N1">57, 470</ENAMEX> casualties, including <ENAMEX type="MEASURE" subtype="rational_number/N1">19, 240</ENAMEX> dead, on the</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E179">The entire <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Somme offensive</ENAMEX> cost the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="military_organization/N1">British Army</ENAMEX> some <ENAMEX type="MEASURE" subtype="rational_number/N1">420, 000</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E180">The <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1">French</ENAMEX> suffered another estimated <ENAMEX type="MEASURE" subtype="rational_number/N1">200, 000</ENAMEX> casualties, and the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1">Germans</ENAMEX> an estimated</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E181">Protracted action at <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Verdun</ENAMEX> throughout <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1916</ENAMEX>, combined with the bloodletting at the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="O">Somme</ENAMEX>, brought the exhausted <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">French army</ENAMEX> to the brink of collapse.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E182">Futile attempts at frontal assault came at a high price for both the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">British</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="O">French poilu</ENAMEX> and led to the widespread <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">French Army</ENAMEX> Mutinies, after the failure of the costly <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Nivelle Offensive of April - May 1917</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E183">The concurrent <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">British</ENAMEX><ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Battle of Arras</ENAMEX> was more limited in scope, and more successful, although ultimately of little strategic value.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E184">A smaller part of the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="municipality/N1">Arras</ENAMEX> offensive, the capture of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="other_geological_formation/N1">Vimy Ridge</ENAMEX> by the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Canadian Corps</ENAMEX>, became highly significant to that country: the idea that <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Canada</ENAMEX> ' s national identity was born out of the battle is an opinion widely held in military and general histories of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Canada</ENAMEX></sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E185">The last large - scale offensive of this period was a <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">British</ENAMEX> attack ( with <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">French</ENAMEX> support ) at <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Passchendaele ( July - November 1917 )</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E186">This offensive opened with great promise for the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Allies</ENAMEX>, before bogging down in the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">October</ENAMEX> mud.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E187">Casualties, though disputed, were roughly equal, at some <ENAMEX type="MEASURE" subtype="rational_number/N1">200, 000 - 400, 000</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E188">These <ENAMEX type="EVENT">years of trench warfare</ENAMEX> in the West saw no major exchanges of territory and, as a result, are often thought of as static and unchanging.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E189">However, throughout this period, <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">British, French, and German</ENAMEX> tactics constantly evolved to meet new battlefield challenges.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E190">Naval war</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E191">Main article:</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E192"><ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Naval warfare of World War I</ENAMEX></sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E193">At the start of the war, the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">German Empire</ENAMEX> had cruisers scattered across the globe, some of which were subsequently used to attack <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Allied</ENAMEX> merchant shipping.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E194">The <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">British Royal Navy</ENAMEX> systematically hunted them down, though not without some embarrassment from its inability to protect <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Allied</ENAMEX> shipping.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E195">For example, the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">German</ENAMEX> detached light cruiser <ENAMEX type="ARTIFACT" subtype="vessel/N2">SMS Emden</ENAMEX>, part of the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="supernational_region/N1">East - Asia</ENAMEX> squadron stationed at <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="municipality/N1">Qingdao</ENAMEX>, seized or destroyed <ENAMEX type="MEASURE" subtype="rational_number/N1">15</ENAMEX> merchantmen, as well as sinking a <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Russian</ENAMEX> cruiser and a <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">French</ENAMEX> destroyer.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E196">However, most of the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="O">German East - Asia</ENAMEX> squadron - - consisting of the armoured cruisers <ENAMEX type="ARTIFACT" subtype="vessel/N2">Scharnhorst and Gneisenau</ENAMEX>, light cruisers <ENAMEX type="ARTIFACT" subtype="vessel/N2">Nurnberg and Leipzig</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX type="MEASURE" subtype="O">two</ENAMEX> transport ships - - did not have orders to raid shipping and was instead underway to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> when it met <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">British</ENAMEX> ships.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E197">The <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">German</ENAMEX> flotilla and <ENAMEX type="ARTIFACT" subtype="vessel/N2">Dresden</ENAMEX> sank <ENAMEX type="MEASURE" subtype="O">two</ENAMEX> armoured cruisers at the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Battle of Coronel</ENAMEX>, but was almost destroyed at the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Battle of the Falkland Islands in December 1914</ENAMEX>, with only <ENAMEX type="ARTIFACT" subtype="vessel/N2">Dresden</ENAMEX> and a few auxiliaries escaping, but at the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Battle of Mas a Tierra</ENAMEX> these too were destroyed or interned.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E198">Soon after the outbreak of hostilities, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Britain</ENAMEX> began a <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">naval blockade of Germany</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E199">The strategy proved effective, cutting off vital military and civilian supplies, although this blockade violated accepted international law codified by several international agreements of the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="O">past two centuries</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E200"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Britain</ENAMEX> mined international waters to prevent any ships from entering entire sections of ocean, causing danger to even neutral ships.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E201">Since there was limited response to this tactic, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> expected a similar response to its unrestricted submarine warfare.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E202"><ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="date/N7">The 1916 Battle of Jutland</ENAMEX> ( <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT" subtype="O">German</ENAMEX>: <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Skagerrakschlacht</ENAMEX>, or " <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Battle of the Skagerrak</ENAMEX> " ) developed into the largest naval battle of the war, the only full - scale clash of battleships during the war, and one of the largest in history.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E203">It took place on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">31 May - 1 June 1916</ENAMEX>, in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="delimited_body_of_water/N1">North Sea of Jutland</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E204">The <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="military_organization/N1">Kaiserliche Marine ' s High Seas Fleet</ENAMEX>, commanded by <ENAMEX type="PERSON" subtype="O">Vice Admiral Reinhard Scheer</ENAMEX>, squared off against the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Royal Navy ' s Grand Fleet</ENAMEX>, led by <ENAMEX type="PERSON" subtype="O">Admiral Sir John Jellicoe</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E205">The engagement was a stand off, as the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1">Germans</ENAMEX>, outmanoeuvred by the larger <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">British</ENAMEX> fleet, managed to escape and inflicted more damage to the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">British</ENAMEX> fleet than they received.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E206">Strategically, however, the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1">British</ENAMEX> asserted their control of the sea, and the bulk of the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">German</ENAMEX> surface fleet remained confined to port for the duration of the war.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E207"><ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">German</ENAMEX><ENAMEX type="ARTIFACT" subtype="vessel/N2">U - boats</ENAMEX> attempted to cut the supply lines between <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="supernational_region/N1">North America and Britain</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E208">The nature of submarine warfare meant that attacks often came without warning, giving the crews of the merchant ships little hope of survival.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E209">The <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">United States</ENAMEX> launched a protest, and <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> changed its rules of engagement.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E210">After the sinking of the passenger ship <ENAMEX type="ARTIFACT" subtype="vessel/N2">RMS Lusitania</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1915</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> promised not to target passenger liners, while <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Britain</ENAMEX> armed its merchant ships, placing them beyond the protection of the " cruiser rules ", which demanded warning and placing crews in " a place of safety " ( a standard that lifeboats did not meet ).</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E211">.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E212"><ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">World War II</ENAMEX> - <ENAMEX type="WEBSITE" subtype="information_web_site/N1">Wikipedia</ENAMEX>, the free encyclopedia</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E213"><ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">World War II</ENAMEX></sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E214">From <ENAMEX type="WEBSITE" subtype="information_web_site/N1">Wikipedia</ENAMEX>, the free encyclopedia</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E215"><ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">World War II ( WWII or WW2 )</ENAMEX>, also known as the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Second World War</ENAMEX>, was a global war that lasted from <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1939</ENAMEX> to <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1945</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E216">It involved the vast majority of the world ' s nations - - including all of the great powers - - eventually forming <ENAMEX type="MEASURE" subtype="O">two</ENAMEX> opposing military alliances: the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Allies</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">Axis</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E217">It was the most widespread war in history, with more than <ENAMEX type="MEASURE" subtype="rational_number/N1">100 million</ENAMEX> people serving in military units from over <ENAMEX type="MEASURE" subtype="rational_number/N1">30</ENAMEX> different countries.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E218">In a state of " <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">total war</ENAMEX> ", the major participants placed their entire economic, industrial, and scientific capabilities at the service of the war effort, erasing the distinction between civilian and military resources.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E219">Marked by mass deaths of civilians, including the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="historical_event/N1">Holocaust</ENAMEX> and the only use of nuclear weapons in warfare, it resulted in an estimated <ENAMEX type="MEASURE" subtype="rational_number/N1">50 million</ENAMEX> to <ENAMEX type="MEASURE" subtype="rational_number/N1">85 million</ENAMEX> fatalities.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E220">These deaths make <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">World War II</ENAMEX> the deadliest conflict in human history.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E221">The <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Empire of Japan</ENAMEX> aimed to dominate <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="supernational_region/N1">East Asia</ENAMEX> and was already at war with the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Republic of China</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1937</ENAMEX>, but the world war is generally said to have begun on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1 September 1939</ENAMEX> with the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">invasion of Poland</ENAMEX> by <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> and subsequent declarations of war on <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> by <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">France</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">United Kingdom</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E222"><ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">From late 1939 to early 1941</ENAMEX>, in a series of campaigns and treaties, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> formed the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">Axis alliance</ENAMEX> with <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Italy</ENAMEX>, conquering or subduing much of continental <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="supernational_region/N1">Europe</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E223">Following the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL" subtype="O">Molotov - Ribbentrop Pact</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany and the Soviet Union</ENAMEX> partitioned and annexed territories between themselves of their <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="regional_cultural_adjective/J1">European</ENAMEX> neighbours, including <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Poland and the Baltic states</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E224">The <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">United Kingdom</ENAMEX> and the other members of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">British Commonwealth</ENAMEX> were the only major <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Allied forces</ENAMEX> continuing the fight against the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">Axis</ENAMEX>, with battles taking place in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="supernational_region/N1">North Africa</ENAMEX> as well as the long - running <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Battle of the Atlantic</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E225">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">June 1941</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">European Axis</ENAMEX> launched an <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">invasion of the Soviet Union</ENAMEX>, giving a start to the largest land theatre of war in history, which tied down the major part of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">Axis</ENAMEX> ' military forces for the rest of the war.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E226">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">December 1941</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Japan</ENAMEX> joined the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">Axis</ENAMEX>, attacked the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="O">United States and European territories</ENAMEX> in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="delimited_body_of_water/N1">Pacific Ocean</ENAMEX>, and quickly conquered much of the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="O">Western Pacific</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E227">The <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">Axis</ENAMEX> advance was stopped in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1942</ENAMEX><ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Japan</ENAMEX> lost a critical <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">battle at Midway</ENAMEX>, near <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="state/N2">Hawaii</ENAMEX>, and never regained its earlier momentum.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E228"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> was defeated in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="O">North Africa</ENAMEX> and, decisively, at <ENAMEX type="LOCATION">Stalingrad in Russia</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E229">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1943</ENAMEX>, with a series of <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="O">German</ENAMEX> defeats in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="other_non-political_region/N1">Eastern Europe</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Allied invasion of Italy</ENAMEX> which brought about that nation ' s surrender, and <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="O">American</ENAMEX> victories in the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="O">Pacific</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">Axis</ENAMEX> lost the initiative and undertook strategic retreat on all fronts</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E230">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1944</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Western Allies</ENAMEX> invaded <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="O">France</ENAMEX>, while the <ENAMEX type="UNKNOWN" subtype="O">Soviet Union</ENAMEX> regained all of its territorial losses and invaded <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> and its allies.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E231">During <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1944 and 1945</ENAMEX> the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">United States</ENAMEX> defeated the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Japanese Navy</ENAMEX> and captured key <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="O">Western Pacific islands</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E232">The war in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="supernational_region/N1">Europe</ENAMEX> ended with an invasion of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> by the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Western Allies</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Soviet Union</ENAMEX> culminating in the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">capture of Berlin</ENAMEX> by <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Soviet and Polish</ENAMEX> troops and the subsequent <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="legal_document/N1">German</ENAMEX> unconditional surrender on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="festival/N1">8 May 1945</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E233">Following the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="O">Potsdam Declaration</ENAMEX> by the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">Allies</ENAMEX> on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">26 July 1945</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">United States</ENAMEX> dropped atomic bombs on the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Japanese</ENAMEX> cities of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="municipality/N1">Hiroshima and Nagasaki</ENAMEX> on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">6 August and 9 August</ENAMEX> respectively.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E234">With an invasion of the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="O">Japanese archipelago</ENAMEX> imminent, and the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Soviet Union</ENAMEX> having declared war on <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Japan</ENAMEX> by invading <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="O">Manchuria</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Japan</ENAMEX> surrendered on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="festival/N1">15 August 1945</ENAMEX>, ending the war in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="supernational_region/N1">Asia</ENAMEX> and cementing the total victory of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Allies</ENAMEX> over the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">Axis</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E235"><ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">World War II</ENAMEX> altered the political alignment and social structure of the world.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E236">The <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">United Nations ( UN )</ENAMEX> was established to foster international co - operation and prevent future conflicts.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E237">The great powers that were the victors of the war - - the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">United States, the Soviet Union, China, the United Kingdom, and France</ENAMEX> - - became the permanent members of the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">United Nations Security Council</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E238">The <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Soviet Union</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">United States</ENAMEX> emerged as rival superpowers, setting the stage for the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="historical_period/N1">Cold War</ENAMEX>, which lasted for the <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="rational_number/N1">next 46 years</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E239">Meanwhile, the influence of <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="regional_cultural_adjective/J1">European</ENAMEX> great powers started to decline, while the decolonisation of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="supernational_region/N1">Asia and Africa</ENAMEX> began.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E240">Most countries whose industries had been damaged moved towards economic recovery.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E241">Political integration, especially in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="supernational_region/N1">Europe</ENAMEX>, emerged as an effort to stabilise postwar relations and fight more effectively in the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="historical_period/N1">Cold War</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E242">Chronology</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E243">The start of the war is generally held to be <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1 September 1939</ENAMEX>, beginning with the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">German invasion of Poland</ENAMEX>; <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Britain and France</ENAMEX> declared war on <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="O">two days later</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E244">Other dates for the beginning of war include the start of the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Second Sino - Japanese War on 7 July 1937</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E245">Others follow the <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">British</ENAMEX> historian <ENAMEX type="PERSON" subtype="intellectual/N1">A. J. P. Taylor</ENAMEX>, who held that the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Sino - Japanese War</ENAMEX> war in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="supernational_region/N1">Europe</ENAMEX> and its colonies occurred simultaneously and the <ENAMEX type="MEASURE" subtype="O">two</ENAMEX> wars merged.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E246">This article uses the conventional dating.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E247">Other starting dates sometimes used for <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">World War II</ENAMEX> include the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Italian invasion of Abyssinia on 3 October 1935</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E248">The <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">British</ENAMEX> historian <ENAMEX type="PERSON" subtype="intellectual/N1">Antony Beevor</ENAMEX> views the beginning of the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Second World War</ENAMEX> as the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Battles of Khalkhin Gol</ENAMEX> fought between <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Japan and the Soviet Union</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">from May to September 1939</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E249">The exact date of the war ' s end is also not universally agreed upon</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E250">It has been suggested that the war ended at <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="date/N7">the armistice of 14 August 1945 ( V - J Day )</ENAMEX>, rather than the formal <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="country/N1">surrender of Japan ( 2 September 1945 )</ENAMEX>; in some <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="regional_cultural_adjective/J1">European</ENAMEX> histories, it ended on <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="festival/N1">V - E Day ( 8 May 1945 )</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E251">However, the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL" subtype="O">Treaty of Peace</ENAMEX> with <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Japan</ENAMEX> was not signed until <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1951</ENAMEX>, and that with <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="O">Germany</ENAMEX> not until <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1990</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E252">Background</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E253">Main article:</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E254">Causes of <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">World War II</ENAMEX></sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E255"><ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">World War I</ENAMEX> radically altered the political map, with the defeat of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">Central Powers</ENAMEX> - - including <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">Austria - Hungary, Germany and the Ottoman Empire</ENAMEX> - - and the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="date/N7">1917 Bolshevik seizure of power in Russia</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E256">Meanwhile, existing victorious <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Allies</ENAMEX> such as <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">France, Belgium, Italy, Greece and Romania</ENAMEX> gained territories, while new states were created out of the collapse of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">Austria - Hungary and the Russian and Ottoman Empires</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E257">Despite the pacifist movement in the aftermath of the war, the losses still caused irredentist and revanchist <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">nationalism</ENAMEX> to become important in a number of <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="regional_cultural_adjective/J1">European</ENAMEX> states.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E258"><ENAMEX type="CONCEPT">Irredentism and revanchism</ENAMEX> were strong in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> because of the significant territorial, colonial, and financial losses incurred by the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL" subtype="O">Treaty of Versailles</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E259">Under the treaty, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> lost around <ENAMEX type="MEASURE" subtype="percentage/N1">13 percent</ENAMEX> of its home territory and all of its overseas colonies, while <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">German</ENAMEX> annexation of other states was prohibited, reparations were imposed, and limits were placed on the size and capability of the country ' s armed forces.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E260">Meanwhile, the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Russian Civil War</ENAMEX> had led to the creation of the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Soviet Union</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E261">The <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">German Empire</ENAMEX> was dissolved in the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">German Revolution of 1918 - 1919</ENAMEX>, and a democratic government, later known as the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">Weimar Republic</ENAMEX>, was created.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E262">The <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="O">interwar period</ENAMEX> saw strife between supporters of the new republic and hardline opponents on both the right and left.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E263">Although <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Italy</ENAMEX> as an Entente ally made some territorial gains, <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Italian</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="CONCEPTUAL">nationalists</ENAMEX> were angered that the promises made by <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Britain and France</ENAMEX> to secure <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Italian</ENAMEX> entrance into the war were not fulfilled with the peace settlement.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E264"><ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">From 1922 to 1925</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION" subtype="O">Fascist movement</ENAMEX> led by <ENAMEX type="PERSON" subtype="politician/N2">Benito Mussolini</ENAMEX> seized power in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Italy</ENAMEX> with a <ENAMEX type="CONCEPTUAL">nationalist, totalitarian, and class collaborationist</ENAMEX> agenda that abolished representative democracy, repressed <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="O">socialist, left - wing and liberal forces</ENAMEX>, and pursued an aggressive foreign policy aimed at forcefully forging <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Italy</ENAMEX> as a world power - - a " <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT" subtype="O">New Roman Empire</ENAMEX> "</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E265">In <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION" subtype="political_party/N1">Nazi Party</ENAMEX> led by <ENAMEX type="PERSON" subtype="politician/N2">Adolf Hitler</ENAMEX> sought to establish a <ENAMEX type="CONCEPT" subtype="political_ideology/N1">Nazi</ENAMEX> state in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E266">With the onset of the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="O">Great Depression</ENAMEX>, domestic support for the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="member_of_a_political_group/N1">Nazis</ENAMEX> rose and, in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1933</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON" subtype="politician/N2">Hitler</ENAMEX> was appointed <ENAMEX type="TITLE" subtype="political_title/N1">Chancellor of Germany</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E267">In the aftermath of the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Reichstag fire</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="PERSON" subtype="politician/N2">Hitler</ENAMEX> created a totalitarian single - party state led by the <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="member_of_a_political_group/N1">Nazis</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E268">The <ENAMEX type="ORGANISATION" subtype="political_party/N1">Kuomintang ( KMT )</ENAMEX> party in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">China</ENAMEX> launched a <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">unification campaign</ENAMEX> against regional warlords and nominally unified <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">China</ENAMEX> in the mid - <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1920s</ENAMEX>, but was soon embroiled in a civil war against its former <ENAMEX type="PERSON_TYPE" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Chinese communist allies</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E269">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1931</ENAMEX>, an increasingly militaristic <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Japanese Empire</ENAMEX>, which had long sought influence in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">China</ENAMEX> as the <ENAMEX type="MEASURE" subtype="O">first</ENAMEX> step of what its government saw as the country ' s right to rule <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="supernational_region/N1">Asia</ENAMEX>, used the <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="O">Mukden Incident</ENAMEX> as a pretext to launch an <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">invasion of Manchuria</ENAMEX> and establish the puppet state of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="O">Manchukuo</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E270">Too weak to resist <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Japan</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">China</ENAMEX> appealed to the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">League of Nations</ENAMEX> for help.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E271"><ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Japan</ENAMEX> withdrew from the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">League of Nations</ENAMEX> after being condemned for its incursion into <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="other_non-political_region/N1">Manchuria</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E272">The <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">two</ENAMEX> nations then fought several battles, in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="municipality/N1">Shanghai, Rehe and Hebei</ENAMEX>, until the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL" subtype="O">Tanggu Truce</ENAMEX> was signed in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1933</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E273">Thereafter, <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Chinese</ENAMEX> volunteer forces continued the resistance to <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1">Japanese</ENAMEX> aggression in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="other_non-political_region/N1">Manchuria</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="O">Chahar and Suiyuan</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E274"><ENAMEX type="PERSON" subtype="politician/N2">Adolf Hitler</ENAMEX>, after an unsuccessful attempt to overthrow the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">German government</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1923</ENAMEX>, became the <ENAMEX type="TITLE" subtype="political_title/N1">Chancellor of Germany</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1933</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E275">He abolished democracy, espousing a radical, racially motivated revision of the world order, and soon began a massive rearmament campaign.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E276">It was at this time that multiple political scientists began to predict that a <ENAMEX type="MEASURE">second</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX type="EVENT" subtype="military_action/N1">Great War</ENAMEX> might take place.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E277">Meanwhile, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">France</ENAMEX>, to secure its alliance, allowed <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Italy</ENAMEX> a free hand in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Ethiopia</ENAMEX>, which <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Italy</ENAMEX> desired as a colonial possession.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E278">The situation was aggravated in early <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">1935</ENAMEX> when the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="historical_country/N1">Territory of the Saar Basin</ENAMEX> was legally reunited with <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX type="PERSON" subtype="politician/N2">Hitler</ENAMEX> repudiated the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL" subtype="O">Treaty of Versailles</ENAMEX>, accelerated his rearmament programme and introduced conscription.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E279">Hoping to contain <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">United Kingdom, France and Italy</ENAMEX> formed the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="O">Stresa Front</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E280">The <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Soviet Union</ENAMEX>, concerned due to <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> ' s goals of capturing vast areas of <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="other_non-political_region/N1">eastern Europe</ENAMEX>, wrote a treaty of mutual assistance with <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">France</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E281">Before taking effect though, the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL" subtype="O">Franco - Soviet pact</ENAMEX> was required to go through the bureaucracy of the <ENAMEX type="INSTITUTION" subtype="supernational_organization/N1">League of Nations</ENAMEX>, which rendered it essentially toothless.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E282">However, in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="date/N7">June 1935</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">United Kingdom</ENAMEX> made an <ENAMEX type="LEGAL" subtype="O">independent naval agreement</ENAMEX> with <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX>, easing prior restrictions.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E283">The <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">United States</ENAMEX>, concerned with events in <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="supernational_region/N1">Europe</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="supernational_region/N1">Asia</ENAMEX>, passed the <ENAMEX type="LEGAL" subtype="O">Neutrality Act</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="O">August</ENAMEX>.</sentence>
				<sentence xml:id="P0E284">In <ENAMEX type="PERIOD" subtype="O">October</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Italy</ENAMEX> invaded <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Ethiopia</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX type="LOCATION" subtype="country/N1">Germany</ENAMEX> was the only major <ENAMEX type="NATIONAL" subtype="regional_cultural_adjective/J1">European</ENAMEX> nation to support the invasion.</sentence>
