-DOCSTART- -46/28/British_Hero_of_the_Holocaust.semdoc.xml-
British	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
Hero	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
of	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
the	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
Holocaust	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
-	O	O
Wikipedia	UNKNOWN	information_web_site/N1
,	UNKNOWN	information_web_site/N1
the	UNKNOWN	information_web_site/N1
free	UNKNOWN	information_web_site/N1
encyclopedia	UNKNOWN	information_web_site/N1

British	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
Hero	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
of	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
the	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
Holocaust	AWARD	civic_honor/N1

From	O	O
Wikipedia	UNKNOWN	information_web_site/N1
,	O	O
the	O	O
free	O	O
encyclopedia	O	O

The	O	O
British	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
Hero	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
of	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
the	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
Holocaust	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
award	O	O
is	O	O
a	O	O
special	O	O
national	O	O
award	O	O
given	O	O
by	O	O
the	O	O
UK	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
government	O	O
in	O	O
recognition	O	O
of	O	O
British	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
citizens	O	O
who	O	O
assisted	O	O
in	O	O
rescuing	O	O
victims	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
Holocaust	EVENT	historical_event/N1
.	O	O

On	O	O
9	PERIOD	date/N7
March	PERIOD	date/N7
2010	PERIOD	date/N7
it	O	O
was	O	O
awarded	O	O
to	O	O
25	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
individuals	O	O
posthumously	O	O
,	O	O
and	O	O
to	O	O
two	O	O
living	O	O
people	O	O
,	O	O
Sir	TITLE	O
Nicholas	PERSON	O
Winton	PERSON	O
aged	O	O
100	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
,	O	O
and	O	O
Denis	PERSON	military_person/N1
Avey	PERSON	military_person/N1
aged	O	O
91	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
.	O	O

The	O	O
award	O	O
is	O	O
a	O	O
solid	O	O
silver	O	O
medallion	O	O
,	O	O
and	O	O
bears	O	O
the	O	O
inscription	O	O
"	O	O
in	O	O
the	O	O
service	O	O
of	O	O
humanity	O	O
"	O	O
in	O	O
recognition	O	O
of	O	O
"	O	O
selfless	O	O
actions	O	O
"	O	O
which	O	O
"	O	O
preserved	O	O
life	O	O
in	O	O
the	O	O
face	O	O
of	O	O
persecution	O	O
"	O	O
.	O	O

Campaign	O	O
for	O	O
official	O	O
recognition	O	O

In	O	O
2008	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
a	O	O
campaign	O	O
to	O	O
gain	O	O
official	O	O
posthumous	O	O
recognition	O	O
of	O	O
British	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
Holocaust	EVENT	historical_event/N1
rescuers	O	O
was	O	O
initiated	O	O
by	O	O
the	O	O
Holocaust	ORGANISATION	charitable_organization/N1
Educational	ORGANISATION	charitable_organization/N1
Trust	ORGANISATION	charitable_organization/N1
,	O	O
a	O	O
British	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
charity	O	O
founded	O	O
in	O	O
1988	PERIOD	date/N7
.	O	O

The	O	O
campaign	O	O
cited	O	O
the	O	O
examples	O	O
of	O	O
British	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
citizens	O	O
such	O	O
as	O	O
Frank	PERSON	educator/N1
Foley	PERSON	educator/N1
,	O	O
Jane	PERSON	O
Haining	PERSON	O
and	O	O
June	PERSON	O
Ravenhall	PERSON	O
who	O	O
had	O	O
previously	O	O
been	O	O
honoured	O	O
by	O	O
Israel	LOCATION	country/N1
as	O	O
one	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
British	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
nominees	O	O
to	O	O
the	O	O
status	O	O
of	O	O
Righteous	ORGANISATION	O
among	O	O
the	O	O
Nations	O	O
,	O	O
but	O	O
had	O	O
received	O	O
no	O	O
British	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
honour	O	O
during	O	O
their	O	O
lifetime	O	O
.	O	O

Under	O	O
the	O	O
official	O	O
British	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
honours	O	O
system	O	O
honours	O	O
cannot	O	O
be	O	O
awarded	O	O
posthumously	O	O
,	O	O
so	O	O
the	O	O
Trust	BUSINESS	trade_name/N1
'	O	O
s	O	O
campaign	O	O
sought	O	O
to	O	O
have	O	O
the	O	O
honours	O	O
system	O	O
changed	O	O
,	O	O
to	O	O
allow	O	O
the	O	O
awarding	O	O
of	O	O
either	O	O
an	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
MBE	O	O
or	O	O
an	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
OBE	O	O
posthumously	O	O
to	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
British	O	O
rescuers	O	O
such	O	O
as	PERSON	O
Frank	PERSON	O
Foley	O	O

On	O	O
7	PERIOD	date/N7
May	PERIOD	date/N7
2008	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
the	O	O
50th	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
anniversary	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
of	O	O
the	O	O
death	O	O
of	O	O
Foley	O	O
,	PERSON	educator/N1
the	O	O
Trust	O	O
filed	O	O
an	O	O
internet	O	O
petition	O	O
titled	O	O
'	O	O
UK	O	O
-	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
Rescuers	O	O
'	O	O
on	O	O
the	O	O
10	O	O
Downing	INSTITUTION	residence/N2
Street	INSTITUTION	residence/N2
website	INSTITUTION	residence/N2
,	O	O
to	O	O
call	O	O
on	O	O
the	O	O
Prime	O	O
Minister	TITLE	political_title/N1
to	TITLE	political_title/N1
reconsider	O	O
the	O	O
laws	O	O
governing	O	O
the	O	O
posthumous	O	O
honours	O	O
system	O	O
.	O	O

With	O	O
a	O	O
deadline	O	O
for	O	O
signatories	O	O
of	O	O
7	PERIOD	date/N7
May	PERIOD	date/N7
2009	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
the	O	O
petition	O	O
ultimately	O	O
gathered	O	O
1	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
,	O	O
087	O	O

It	O	O
had	O	O
stated	O	O
:	O	O

.	O	O
.	O	O
.	PERSON	educator/N1
[	O	O
Foley	O	O
]	O	O
was	O	O
never	O	O
formally	O	O
honoured	O	O
by	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
the	O	O
British	O	O
nation	O	O
during	O	O
his	O	O
lifetime	O	O
for	O	O
his	O	O

We	O	O
therefore	O	O
call	O	O
on	O	O
the	O	O
Government	O	O
to	O	O
review	O	O
the	O	O
current	O	O
statutes	O	O
governing	O	O
the	O	O
honours	O	O
system	O	O
,	O	O
so	O	O
that	O	O
the	O	O
Honours	ORGANISATION	O
Committee	ORGANISATION	O
can	O	O
consider	O	O
awarding	O	O
a	O	O
posthumous	O	O
knighthood	O	O
to	O	O
Frank	PERSON	O
Foley	PERSON	O
.	O	O

We	O	O
hope	O	O
that	O	O
this	O	O
will	O	O
open	O	O
the	O	O
way	O	O
for	O	O
the	O	O
Honours	ORGANISATION	O
Committee	ORGANISATION	O
to	O	O
consider	O	O
recognition	O	O
for	O	O
other	O	O
British	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
heroes	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
Holocaust	EVENT	historical_event/N1
,	O	O
including	O	O
Randolph	PERSON	politician/N2
Churchill	PERSON	politician/N2
,	O	O
Sergeant	TITLE	military_title/N1
Charles	PERSON	military_person/N1
Coward	PERSON	military_person/N1
,	O	O
Jane	PERSON	O
Haining	PERSON	O
,	O	O
Tommy	PERSON	O
Noble	PERSON	O
and	O	O
Robert	PERSON	O
Smallbones	PERSON	O
,	O	O
who	O	O
risked	O	O
and	O	O
in	O	O
some	O	O
cases	O	O
gave	O	O
their	O	O
own	O	O
lives	O	O
to	O	O
save	O	O
others	O	O
.	O	O

Through	O	O
2008	PERIOD	date/N7
and	O	O
2009	PERIOD	date/N7
the	O	O
campaign	O	O
attracted	O	O
support	O	O
from	O	O
the	O	O
media	O	O
as	O	O
well	O	O
as	O	O
members	O	O
of	O	O
parliament	O	O
,	O	O
both	O	O
in	O	O
the	O	O
UK	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
parliament	O	O
and	O	O
in	O	O
the	O	O
Scottish	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
Parliament	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
,	O	O
citing	O	O
the	O	O
particular	O	O
examples	O	O
of	O	O
Foley	LOCATION	municipality/N1
,	O	O
Ravenhall	LOCATION	municipality/N1
and	O	O
Haining	PERSON	O
.	O	O

In	O	O
March	PERIOD	date/N7
2009	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
the	O	O
MP	TITLE	political_title/N1
Russell	PERSON	politician/N2
Brown	PERSON	politician/N2
tabled	O	O
the	O	O
early	O	O
day	O	O
motion	O	O
Recognition	O	O
for	O	O
British	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
Heroes	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
Holocaust	EVENT	historical_event/N1
in	O	O
Westminster	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
citing	O	O
the	O	O
examples	O	O
of	O	O
Foley	LOCATION	municipality/N1
,	O	O
Haining	PERSON	O
and	O	O
Ravenhall	LOCATION	municipality/N1
,	O	O
securing	O	O
135	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
signatories	O	O
.	O	O

Announcement	O	O
of	O	O
a	O	O
new	O	O
award	O	O

On	O	O
29	PERIOD	date/N7
April	PERIOD	date/N7
2009	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
as	O	O
the	O	O
early	O	O
day	O	O
motion	O	O
reached	O	O
Parliament	O	O
,	O	O
the	O	O
government	O	O
announced	O	O
that	O	O
a	O	O
new	O	O
award	O	O
would	O	O
be	O	O
specially	O	O
created	O	O
to	O	O
recognise	O	O
these	O	O
British	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
rescuers	O	O
.	O	O

Announced	O	O
just	O	O
after	O	O
Gordon	PERSON	politician/N2
Brown	PERSON	politician/N2
'	O	O
s	O	O
first	O	O
visit	O	O
to	O	O
the	INSTITUTION	correctional_facility/N1
Auschwitz	O	O
-	LOCATION	municipality/N1
Birkenau	O	O
concentration	O	O
camp	O	O
in	LOCATION	country/N1
Poland	O	O
,	O	O
the	TITLE	political_title/N1
Prime	TITLE	political_title/N1
Minister	O	O
said	O	O
"	O	O
We	O	O
will	O	O
create	O	O
national	O	O
awards	O	O
in	LOCATION	country/N1
Britain	O	O
for	O	O
those	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
British	O	O
citizens	O	O
who	O	O
helped	O	O
so	O	O
many	O	O
people	O	O
,	CONCEPTUAL	cultural_adjective/J1
Jewish	O	O
and	O	O
other	O	O
citizens	O	O
,	O	O
during	O	O
the	EVENT	historical_event/N1
Holocaust	O	O
period	O	O
"	O	O

The	O	O
recognition	O	O
was	O	O
to	O	O
take	O	O
the	O	O
form	O	O
of	O	O
some	O	O
type	O	O
of	O	O
a	O	O
new	O	O
national	O	O
award	O	O
,	O	O
outside	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
Honours	CONCEPT	O
System	CONCEPT	O
,	O	O
after	O	O
the	O	O
government	O	O
ruled	O	O
out	O	O
reforming	O	O
the	O	O
posthumous	O	O
honours	O	O
rules	O	O
,	O	O
with	O	O
the	O	O
Secretary	TITLE	political_title/N1
of	TITLE	political_title/N1
State	TITLE	political_title/N1
for	O	O
Communities	O	O
and	O	O
Local	O	O
Government	O	O
and	O	O
the	O	O
Minister	TITLE	political_title/N1
for	O	O
the	O	O
Cabinet	ORGANISATION	government_department/N1
Office	ORGANISATION	government_department/N1
going	O	O
on	O	O
to	O	O
discuss	O	O
the	O	O
exact	O	O
form	O	O
it	O	O
would	O	O
take	O	O
with	O	O
the	O	O
Trust	O	O
,	O	O
Russell	PERSON	politician/N2
Brown	PERSON	politician/N2
MP	TITLE	political_title/N1
and	O	O
the	O	O
families	O	O
of	O	O
potential	O	O
recipients	O	O
.	O	O

British	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
Hero	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
of	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
the	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
Holocaust	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
award	O	O

The	O	O
new	O	O
award	O	O
was	O	O
announced	O	O
as	O	O
the	O	O
British	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
Hero	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
of	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
the	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
Holocaust	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
award	O	O
,	O	O
a	O	O
state	O	O
recognition	O	O
similar	O	O
to	O	O
a	O	O
state	O	O
honour	O	O
.	O	O

It	O	O
was	O	O
presented	O	O
to	O	O
27	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
people	O	O
on	O	O
9	PERIOD	date/N7
March	PERIOD	date/N7
2010	PERIOD	date/N7
-	O	O
in	O	O
addition	O	O
to	O	O
being	O	O
awarded	O	O
posthumously	O	O
to	O	O
the	O	O
families	O	O
of	O	O
25	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
recipients	O	O
,	O	O
the	O	O
medal	O	O
was	O	O
also	O	O
awarded	O	O
to	O	O
two	O	O
living	O	O
people	O	O
,	O	O
Sir	TITLE	O
Nicholas	PERSON	O
Winton	PERSON	O
,	O	O
aged	O	O
100	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
,	O	O
and	O	O
Denis	PERSON	military_person/N1
Avey	PERSON	military_person/N1
,	O	O
aged	O	O
91	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
.	O	O

Both	O	O
Winton	PERSON	O
and	O	O
Avey	PERSON	military_person/N1
,	O	O
along	O	O
with	O	O
relatives	O	O
of	O	O
posthumous	O	O
recipients	O	O
,	O	O
received	O	O
the	O	O
award	O	O
at	O	O
a	O	O
reception	O	O
in	O	O
10	INSTITUTION	residence/N2
Downing	INSTITUTION	residence/N2
Street	INSTITUTION	residence/N2
.	O	O

The	O	O
award	O	O
itself	O	O
is	O	O
a	O	O
solid	O	O
silver	O	O
medallion	O	O
,	O	O
and	O	O
bears	O	O
the	O	O
inscription	O	O
"	O	O
in	O	O
the	O	O
service	O	O
of	O	O
humanity	O	O
"	O	O
on	O	O
the	O	O
front	O	O
,	O	O
and	O	O
on	O	O
the	O	O
reverse	O	O
,	O	O
a	O	O
recognition	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
recipient	O	O
'	O	O
s	O	O
"	O	O
selfless	O	O
actions	O	O
[	O	O
which	O	O
]	O	O
preserved	O	O
life	O	O
in	O	O
the	O	O
face	O	O
of	O	O
persecution	O	O
"	O	O

To	O	O
qualify	O	O
for	O	O
a	O	O
British	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
Hero	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
of	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
the	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
Holocaust	AWARD	civic_honor/N1
award	O	O
the	O	O
individual	O	O
had	O	O
to	O	O
be	O	O
a	O	O
British	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
citizen	O	O
who	O	O
helped	O	O
or	O	O
rescued	O	O
Jews	PERSON_TYPE	member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1
or	O	O
others	O	O
in	O	O
the	O	O
Holocaust	EVENT	historical_event/N1
;	O	O
either	O	O
through	O	O
extraordinary	O	O
acts	O	O
of	O	O
courage	O	O
-	O	O
this	O	O
essentially	O	O
captured	O	O
those	O	O
people	O	O
who	O	O
put	O	O
their	O	O
own	O	O
lives	O	O
at	O	O
risk	O	O
and	O	O
are	O	O
Righteous	O	O
Among	O	O
the	O	O
Nations	O	O
-	O	O
or	O	O
by	O	O
going	O	O
above	O	O
and	O	O
beyond	O	O
the	O	O
call	O	O
of	O	O
duty	O	O
in	O	O
the	O	O
most	O	O
difficult	O	O
circumstances	O	O
-	O	O
this	O	O
included	O	O
individuals	O	O
who	O	O
were	O	O
not	O	O
Righteous	O	O
Among	O	O
the	O	O
Nations	O	O
.	O	O

List	O	O
of	O	O
recipients	O	O

The	O	O
27	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
recipients	O	O
were	O	O
:	O	O

Princess	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
Alice	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
of	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
Greece	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1

Sir	TITLE	O
Nicholas	PERSON	O
Winton	PERSON	O

Major	O	O
Frank	PERSON	military_person/N1
Foley	PERSON	military_person/N1

Battery	O	O
Sergeant	O	O
Major	O	O
Charles	PERSON	military_person/N1
Coward	PERSON	military_person/N1

Sister	O	O
Agnes	PERSON	entertainer/N1
Walsh	PERSON	entertainer/N1

Denis	PERSON	military_person/N1
Avey	PERSON	military_person/N1

Albert	PERSON	health_professional/N1
Bedane	PERSON	health_professional/N1

Jane	PERSON	O
Haining	PERSON	O

June	PERSON	O
Ravenhall	PERSON	O

Sofka	PERSON	O
Skipwith	PERSON	O

Bertha	PERSON	O
Bracey	PERSON	O

Henk	PERSON	O
Huffener	PERSON	O

Two	O	O
sisters	O	O
from	O	O
London	LOCATION	municipality/N1

Ida	PERSON	O
Cook	PERSON	O
(	O	O
a	O	O
.	O	O
k	PERSON	writer/N1
.	PERSON	writer/N1
a	O	O

Louise	PERSON	O
Cook	PERSON	O

Three	O	O
siblings	O	O
from	O	O
Jersey	LOCATION	state/N2

Louisa	PERSON	O
Gould	PERSON	O

Ivy	PERSON	O
Forster	PERSON	O

Harold	PERSON	O
Le	PERSON	O
Druillenec	PERSON	O

The	O	O
10	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
recipients	O	O
in	O	O
2013	PERIOD	date/N7
were	O	O
:	O	O

Rabbi	TITLE	religious_title/N1
Dr	CONCEPT	academic_degree/N1
Solomon	PERSON	religious_figure/N1
Schonfeld	PERSON	religious_figure/N1
who	O	O
went	O	O
above	O	O
and	O	O
beyond	O	O
the	O	O
call	O	O
of	O	O
duty	O	O
to	O	O
personally	O	O
save	O	O
hundreds	O	O
of	O	O
Jews	PERSON_TYPE	member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1
from	O	O
the	O	O
Death	O	O
Camps	O	O
by	O	O
acquiring	O	O
visas	O	O
which	O	O
allowed	O	O
them	O	O
to	O	O
escape	O	O
the	O	O
Nazis	PERSON_TYPE	member_of_a_political_group/N1
.	O	O

Lena	PERSON	O
Lakomy	PERSON	O
who	O	O
risked	O	O
her	O	O
life	O	O
in	O	O
Auschwitz	INSTITUTION	correctional_facility/N1
to	O	O
save	O	O
the	O	O
life	O	O
of	O	O
Hela	PERSON	O
Frank	PERSON	O
.	O	O

Robert	PERSON	O
Smallbones	PERSON	O
Consul	O	O
General	O	O
in	O	O
Frankfurt	LOCATION	municipality/N1
who	O	O
went	O	O
far	O	O
beyond	O	O
the	O	O
call	O	O
of	O	O
duty	O	O
to	O	O
ensure	O	O
that	O	O
Jewish	CONCEPTUAL	cultural_adjective/J1
families	O	O
were	O	O
given	O	O
visas	O	O
in	O	O
order	O	O
to	O	O
save	O	O
their	O	O
lives	O	O
.	O	O

Arthur	PERSON	O
Dowden	PERSON	O
vice	O	O
-	O	O
Consul	O	O
General	O	O
in	O	O
Frankfurt	LOCATION	municipality/N1
who	O	O
went	O	O
far	O	O
beyond	O	O
the	O	O
call	O	O
of	O	O
duty	O	O
to	O	O
save	O	O
lives	O	O
by	O	O
issuing	O	O
visas	O	O
and	O	O
by	O	O
going	O	O
through	O	O
the	O	O
streets	O	O
distributing	O	O
food	O	O
in	O	O
the	O	O
days	O	O
when	O	O
Jews	PERSON_TYPE	member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1
were	O	O
not	O	O
allowed	O	O
to	O	O
receive	O	O
it	O	O
.	O	O

A	O	O
group	O	O
of	O	O
6	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
British	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
prisoners	O	O
of	O	O
war	O	O
who	O	O
risked	O	O
execution	O	O
to	O	O
save	O	O
the	O	O
life	O	O
of	O	O
Hannah	PERSON	O
Sara	PERSON	O
Rigler	PERSON	O
.	O	O

Alan	PERSON	O
Edwards	PERSON	O

Roger	PERSON	O
Letchford	PERSON	O

George	PERSON	O
Hammond	PERSON	O

Tommy	PERSON	O
Noble	PERSON	O

Harold	PERSON	O
'	PERSON	O
Bill	PERSON	O
'	PERSON	O
Scruton	PERSON	O

Stanley	PERSON	intellectual/N1
Wells	PERSON	intellectual/N1

(	O	O
There	O	O
are	O	O
another	O	O
4	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
in	O	O
this	O	O
group	O	O
of	O	O
POWs	O	O
to	O	O
whom	O	O
awards	O	O
are	O	O
not	O	O
yet	O	O
issued	O	O
,	O	O
because	O	O
they	O	O
and	O	O
their	O	O
relatives	O	O
remained	O	O
untraced	O	O
in	O	O
2013	PERIOD	date/N7
.	O	O
)	O	O

John	PERSON	O
Buckley	PERSON	O

Bert	PERSON	O
Hambling	PERSON	O

Bill	PERSON	O
Keeble	PERSON	O

Willy	PERSON	O
Fisher	PERSON	O

Fisher	PERSON	O

-DOCSTART- -95/11/Cambodian–Vietnamese_War.semdoc.xml-
Cambodian	EVENT	military_action/N1
-	EVENT	military_action/N1
Vietnamese	EVENT	military_action/N1
War	EVENT	military_action/N1
-	O	O
Wikipedia	UNKNOWN	information_web_site/N1
,	UNKNOWN	information_web_site/N1
the	UNKNOWN	information_web_site/N1
free	UNKNOWN	information_web_site/N1
encyclopedia	UNKNOWN	information_web_site/N1

Cambodian	EVENT	military_action/N1
-	EVENT	military_action/N1
Vietnamese	EVENT	military_action/N1
War	EVENT	military_action/N1

From	O	O
Wikipedia	UNKNOWN	information_web_site/N1
,	UNKNOWN	information_web_site/N1
the	UNKNOWN	information_web_site/N1
free	UNKNOWN	information_web_site/N1
encyclopedia	UNKNOWN	information_web_site/N1

The	O	O
Cambodian	EVENT	military_action/N1
-	EVENT	military_action/N1
Vietnamese	EVENT	military_action/N1
War	EVENT	military_action/N1
was	O	O
an	O	O
armed	O	O
conflict	O	O
between	O	O
the	O	O
Socialist	LOCATION	country/N1
Republic	LOCATION	country/N1
of	LOCATION	country/N1
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
and	O	O
Democratic	LOCATION	historical_country/N1
Kampuchea	LOCATION	historical_country/N1
.	O	O

The	O	O
war	O	O
began	O	O
with	O	O
isolated	O	O
clashes	O	O
along	O	O
the	O	O
land	O	O
and	O	O
maritime	O	O
boundaries	O	O
of	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
and	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
between	O	O
1975	PERIOD	date/N7
and	O	O
1977	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
occasionally	O	O
involving	O	O
division	O	O
-	O	O
sized	O	O
military	O	O
formations	O	O
.	O	O

On	O	O
25	PERIOD	date/N7
December	PERIOD	date/N7
1978	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
launched	O	O
a	O	O
full	O	O
-	O	O
scale	O	O
invasion	O	O
of	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
and	O	O
subsequently	O	O
occupied	O	O
the	O	O
country	O	O
and	O	O
removed	O	O
the	O	O
Khmer	PERSON_TYPE	member_of_a_military_group/N1
Rouge	PERSON_TYPE	member_of_a_military_group/N1
from	O	O
power	O	O
.	O	O

During	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnam	EVENT	military_action/N1
War	EVENT	military_action/N1
,	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
and	O	O
Khmer	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
Rouge	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
communists	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
had	O	O
formed	O	O
an	O	O
alliance	O	O
to	O	O
fight	O	O
U	LOCATION	country/N1
.	O	O
S	O	O
.	O	O
-	O	O
backed	O	O
regimes	O	O
in	O	O
their	O	O

Despite	O	O
their	O	O
open	O	O
display	O	O
of	O	O
cooperation	O	O
with	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	CONCEPT	language/N1
,	O	O
the	O	O
Khmer	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Rouge	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
leadership	O	O
feared	O	O
that	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
communists	O	O
were	O	O
scheming	O	O
to	O	O
form	O	O
an	O	O
Indochinese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
federation	O	O
with	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
as	O	O
the	O	O
dominant	O	O
force	O	O
in	O	O
the	O	O
region	O	O
.	O	O

In	O	O
order	O	O
to	O	O
preempt	O	O
an	O	O
attempt	O	O
by	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	CONCEPT	language/N1
to	O	O
dominate	O	O
them	O	O
,	O	O
the	O	O
Khmer	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Rouge	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
leadership	O	O
began	O	O
purging	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
-	O	O
trained	O	O
personnel	O	O
within	O	O
their	O	O
own	O	O
ranks	O	O
as	O	O
the	O	O
Lon	PERSON	politician/N2
Nol	PERSON	politician/N2
regime	O	O
capitulated	O	O
in	O	O
1975	PERIOD	date/N7
.	O	O

Then	O	O
,	O	O
in	O	O
May	PERIOD	date/N7
1975	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
the	O	O
newly	O	O
formed	O	O
Democratic	LOCATION	historical_country/N1
Kampuchea	LOCATION	historical_country/N1
,	O	O
dominated	O	O
by	O	O
the	O	O
Khmer	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Rouge	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
,	O	O
began	O	O
waging	O	O
a	O	O
war	O	O
against	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
,	O	O
which	O	O
was	O	O
marked	O	O
by	O	O
an	O	O
attack	O	O
on	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
island	O	O
of	O	O
Phu	LOCATION	island/N1
Quoc	LOCATION	island/N1
.	O	O

However	O	O
,	O	O
behind	O	O
the	O	O
scenes	O	O
,	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
leaders	O	O
continued	O	O
to	O	O
fear	O	O
what	O	O
they	O	O
perceived	O	O
as	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
expansionism	O	O
.	O	O

As	O	O
such	O	O
,	O	O
on	O	O
30	PERIOD	date/N7
April	PERIOD	date/N7
1977	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
they	O	O
launched	O	O
another	O	O
major	O	O
military	O	O
attack	O	O
on	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
.	O	O

Shocked	O	O
by	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
assault	O	O
,	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
launched	O	O
a	O	O
retaliatory	O	O
strike	O	O
at	O	O
the	O	O
end	O	O
of	O	O
1977	PERIOD	date/N7
in	O	O
an	O	O
attempt	O	O
to	O	O
force	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
Government	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
to	O	O
negotiate	O	O
.	O	O

In	O	O
January	PERIOD	date/N7
1978	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
military	O	O
withdrew	O	O
because	O	O
their	O	O
political	O	O
objectives	O	O
had	O	O
not	O	O
been	O	O
achieved	O	O
.	O	O

Small	O	O
-	O	O
scale	O	O
fighting	O	O
continued	O	O
between	O	O
the	O	O
two	O	O
countries	O	O
throughout	O	O
1978	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
as	O	O
China	LOCATION	country/N1
tried	O	O
to	O	O
mediate	O	O
peace	O	O
talks	O	O
between	O	O
the	O	O
two	O	O
sides	O	O
.	O	O

However	O	O
,	O	O
neither	O	O
country	O	O
could	O	O
reach	O	O
an	O	O
acceptable	O	O
compromise	O	O
at	O	O
the	O	O
negotiation	O	O
table	O	O
.	O	O

By	O	O
the	O	O
end	O	O
of	O	O
1978	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
leaders	O	O
decided	O	O
to	O	O
remove	O	O
the	O	O
Khmer	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Rouge	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
-	O	O
dominated	O	O
regime	O	O
of	O	O
Democratic	LOCATION	historical_country/N1
Kampuchea	LOCATION	historical_country/N1
,	O	O
perceiving	O	O
it	O	O
as	O	O
being	O	O
pro	O	O
-	O	O
Chinese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
and	O	O
too	O	O
hostile	O	O
towards	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
.	O	O

On	O	O
25	PERIOD	date/N7
December	PERIOD	date/N7
1978	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
150	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
,	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
000	O	O
Vietnamese	O	O
troops	LOCATION	historical_country/N1
invaded	LOCATION	historical_country/N1
Democratic	O	O
Kampuchea	O	O
and	O	O
overran	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
the	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
Kampuchean	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
Revolutionary	O	O
Army	O	O
in	O	O
just	O	O
two	O	O

On	O	O
8	PERIOD	date/N7
January	PERIOD	date/N7
1979	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
a	O	O
pro	O	O
-	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
People	LOCATION	country/N1
'	LOCATION	country/N1
s	LOCATION	country/N1
Republic	LOCATION	country/N1
of	LOCATION	country/N1
Kampuchea	O	O
(	LOCATION	country/N1
PRK	O	O
)	O	O
was	O	O
established	O	O
in	LOCATION	municipality/N1
Phnom	LOCATION	municipality/N1
Penh	O	O
,	O	O
marking	O	O
the	O	O
beginning	O	O
of	O	O
a	O	O
ten	O	O
-	O	O
year	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
Vietnamese	O	O
occupation	O	O

During	O	O
that	O	O
period	O	O
,	O	O
the	O	O
Khmer	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Rouge	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
'	O	O
s	LOCATION	historical_country/N1
Democratic	LOCATION	historical_country/N1
Kampuchea	O	O
continued	O	O
to	O	O
be	O	O
recognised	O	O
by	O	O
the	ORGANISATION	supernational_organization/N1
United	ORGANISATION	supernational_organization/N1
Nations	O	O
as	O	O
the	O	O
legitimate	O	O
government	O	O
of	LOCATION	country/N1
Kampuchea	O	O
,	O	O
as	O	O
several	O	O
armed	O	O
resistance	O	O
groups	O	O
were	O	O
formed	O	O
to	O	O
fight	O	O
the	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
Vietnamese	O	O
occupation	O	O

Behind	O	O
the	O	O
scenes	O	O
,	O	O
Prime	TITLE	political_title/N1
Minister	TITLE	political_title/N1
Hun	PERSON	politician/N2
Sen	PERSON	politician/N2
of	O	O
the	O	O
PRK	LOCATION	country/N1
regime	O	O
approached	O	O
factions	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
Coalition	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
Government	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
of	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
Democratic	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
Kampuchea	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
(	O	O
CGDK	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
)	O	O
to	O	O
begin	O	O
peace	O	O
talks	O	O
.	O	O

Under	O	O
heavy	O	O
diplomatic	O	O
and	O	O
economic	O	O
pressure	O	O
from	O	O
the	O	O
international	O	O
community	O	O
,	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
Government	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
implemented	O	O
a	O	O
series	O	O
of	O	O
economic	O	O
and	O	O
foreign	O	O
policy	O	O
reforms	O	O
,	O	O
which	O	O
led	O	O
to	O	O
their	O	O
withdrawal	O	O
from	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
in	O	O
September	PERIOD	date/N7
1989	PERIOD	date/N7
.	O	O

At	O	O
the	O	O
Third	O	O
Jakarta	LOCATION	municipality/N1
Informal	O	O
Meeting	O	O
in	O	O
1990	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
under	O	O
the	O	O
Australian	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
-	O	O
sponsored	O	O
Cambodian	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
Peace	O	O
Plan	O	O
,	O	O
representatives	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
CGDK	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
and	O	O
the	O	O
PRK	LOCATION	country/N1
agreed	O	O
to	O	O
a	O	O
power	O	O
-	O	O
sharing	O	O
arrangement	O	O
by	O	O
forming	O	O
a	O	O
unity	O	O
government	O	O
known	O	O
as	O	O
the	O	O
Supreme	ORGANISATION	O
National	ORGANISATION	O
Council	ORGANISATION	O
(	O	O
SNC	ORGANISATION	O
)	O	O
.	O	O

The	O	O
SNC	ORGANISATION	O
'	O	O
s	O	O
role	O	O
was	O	O
to	O	O
represent	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
Cambodian	O	O
sovereignty	O	O
on	O	O
the	O	O
international	O	O
stage	O	O
,	O	O
while	O	O
the	EVENT	military_action/N1
United	EVENT	military_action/N1
Nations	EVENT	military_action/N1
Transitional	EVENT	military_action/N1
Authority	EVENT	military_action/N1
in	EVENT	military_action/N1
Cambodia	O	O
(	EVENT	military_action/N1
UNTAC	O	O
)	O	O
was	O	O
tasked	O	O
with	O	O
supervising	O	O
the	O	O
country	O	O
'	O	O
s	O	O
domestic	O	O
policies	O	O
until	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
a	O	O
Cambodian	O	O
government	O	O
was	O	O
elected	O	O
by	O	O
the	O	O
people	O	O
through	O	O
a	O	O
peaceful	O	O
,	O	O
democratic	O	O

Cambodia	LOCATION	country/N1
'	O	O
s	O	O
pathway	O	O
to	O	O
peace	O	O
proved	O	O
to	O	O
be	O	O
difficult	O	O
,	O	O
as	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Khmer	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Rouge	O	O
leaders	O	O
decided	O	O
not	O	O
to	O	O
participate	O	O
in	O	O
the	O	O
general	O	O
elections	O	O
,	O	O
but	O	O
instead	O	O
they	O	O
chose	O	O
to	O	O
disrupt	O	O
the	O	O
electoral	O	O
process	O	O
by	O	O
launching	O	O
military	O	O
attacks	O	O
on	ORGANISATION	supernational_organization/N1
UN	O	O
peacekeepers	O	O
and	O	O
killing	O	O
ethnic	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
Vietnamese	O	O
migrants	O	O

In	O	O
May	PERIOD	date/N7
1993	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
Sihanouk	PERSON	O
'	O	O
s	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
FUNCINPEC	O	O
movement	O	O
defeated	O	O
the	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
Cambodian	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
People	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
'	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
s	O	O
Party	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
(	O	O
CPP	O	O
)	O	O
,	O	O
formerly	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
the	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
Kampuchean	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
People	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
'	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
s	O	O
Revolutionary	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
Party	O	O
(	O	O
KPRP	O	O
)	O	O
,	O	O
to	O	O
win	O	O
the	O	O

However	O	O
,	O	O
the	O	O
CPP	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
leadership	O	O
refused	O	O
to	O	O
accept	O	O
defeat	O	O
and	O	O
they	O	O
announced	O	O
that	O	O
the	O	O
eastern	O	O
provinces	O	O
of	O	O
Cambodia	LOCATION	country/N1
,	O	O
where	O	O
most	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
CPP	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
'	O	O
s	O	O
votes	O	O
were	O	O
drawn	O	O
from	O	O
,	O	O
would	O	O
secede	O	O
from	LOCATION	country/N1
Cambodia	O	O

To	O	O
avoid	O	O
such	O	O
an	O	O
outcome	O	O
,	O	O
Norodom	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
Ranariddh	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
,	O	O
the	O	O
leader	O	O
of	O	O
FUNCINPEC	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
agreed	O	O
to	O	O
form	O	O
a	O	O
coalition	O	O
government	O	O
with	O	O
the	O	O
CPP	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
.	O	O

Shortly	O	O
afterwards	O	O
,	O	O
the	O	O
constitutional	O	O
monarchy	O	O
was	O	O
restored	O	O
and	O	O
the	O	O
Khmer	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Rouge	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
was	O	O
outlawed	O	O
by	O	O
the	O	O
newly	O	O
formed	O	O
Cambodian	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
Government	O	O
.	O	O

Background	O	O

Cambodian	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
-	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
history	O	O

Angkor	LOCATION	municipality/N1
,	O	O
the	O	O
seat	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
Khmer	LOCATION	country/N1
Empire	LOCATION	country/N1
was	O	O
subjected	O	O
to	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
influence	O	O
as	O	O
early	O	O
as	O	O
the	O	O
13th	O	O
century	O	O
.	O	O

Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
influence	O	O
spread	O	O
gradually	O	O
and	O	O
indirectly	O	O
,	O	O
and	O	O
it	O	O
was	O	O
not	O	O
until	O	O
the	O	O
early	O	O
19th	O	O
century	O	O
that	O	O
Vietnam	O	O
exercised	LOCATION	country/N1
direct	O	O
control	O	O
.	O	O

In	O	O
1813	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
Nak	PERSON	O
Ong	PERSON	O
Chan	PERSON	O
gained	O	O
the	O	O
Cambodian	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
throne	O	O
with	O	O
the	O	O
help	O	O
of	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
,	O	O
and	O	O
under	O	O
his	O	O
rule	O	O
Cambodia	LOCATION	country/N1
became	O	O
a	O	O
protectorate	O	O
.	O	O

Following	O	O
his	O	O
death	O	O
in	O	O
1834	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
colonised	O	O
Cambodia	LOCATION	country/N1
;	O	O
it	O	O
was	O	O
governed	O	O
under	O	O
a	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
administration	O	O
and	O	O
termed	O	O
a	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
'	O	O
province	O	O
'	O	O
.	O	O

Throughout	O	O
the	O	O
1830s	PERIOD	date/N7
,	PERIOD	date/N7
Vietnam	O	O
attempted	LOCATION	country/N1
to	O	O
erase	O	O
Khmer	O	O
culture	PERSON_TYPE	member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1
,	O	O
which	O	O
had	O	O
derived	O	O
the	O	O
basis	O	O
of	O	O
Cambodian	O	O
society	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
,	O	O
dress	O	O
and	O	O
religion	O	O
from	O	O
India	O	O
rather	LOCATION	country/N1
than	O	O
China	O	O
.	LOCATION	country/N1

The	O	O
trend	O	O
of	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
dominance	O	O
continued	O	O
during	O	O
French	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
colonization	O	O
,	O	O
under	O	O
which	O	O
Cambodia	LOCATION	country/N1
was	O	O
forced	O	O
to	O	O
cede	O	O
much	O	O
of	O	O
its	O	O
southern	O	O
cone	O	O
(	O	O
would	O	O
later	O	O
be	O	O
Saigon	LOCATION	municipality/N1
,	O	O
the	O	O
Mekong	LOCATION	other_non-political_region/N1
Delta	LOCATION	other_non-political_region/N1
and	O	O
Tay	LOCATION	municipality/N1
Ninh	LOCATION	municipality/N1
)	O	O
to	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
.	O	O

The	O	O
Khmer	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Rouge	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
later	O	O
justified	O	O
their	O	O
incursions	O	O
into	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
as	O	O
an	O	O
attempt	O	O
to	O	O
regain	O	O
the	O	O
territories	O	O
which	O	O
Cambodia	LOCATION	country/N1
lost	O	O
during	O	O
the	O	O
previous	O	O
centuries	O	O
.	O	O

Rise	O	O
of	O	O
communism	O	O

The	O	O
communist	O	O
movement	O	O
in	O	O
Cambodia	LOCATION	country/N1
and	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
began	O	O
before	O	O
World	EVENT	military_action/N1
War	EVENT	military_action/N1
II	EVENT	military_action/N1
with	O	O
the	O	O
founding	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
Indochinese	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
Communist	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
Party	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
(	O	O
ICP	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
)	O	O
,	O	O
almost	O	O
exclusively	O	O
dominated	O	O
by	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	CONCEPT	language/N1
,	O	O
originally	O	O
meant	O	O
to	O	O
fight	O	O
French	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
colonial	O	O
rule	O	O
in	O	O
Indochina	LOCATION	other_non-political_region/N1
.	O	O

In	O	O
1941	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
Nguyen	PERSON	O
Ai	PERSON	O
Quoc	PERSON	O
(	O	O
commonly	O	O
known	O	O
by	O	O
his	O	O
alias	O	O
Ho	PERSON	politician/N2
Chi	PERSON	politician/N2
Minh	PERSON	politician/N2
)	O	O
founded	O	O
the	O	O
Viet	LOCATION	O
Nam	LOCATION	O
Doc	LOCATION	O
Lap	LOCATION	O
Dong	LOCATION	O
Minh	LOCATION	O
Hoi	LOCATION	O
,	O	O
or	O	O
the	O	O
Viet	ORGANISATION	interest_or_advocacy_group/N1
Minh	ORGANISATION	interest_or_advocacy_group/N1
.	O	O

When	O	O
the	O	O
Japanese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
were	O	O
defeated	O	O
at	O	O
the	O	O
end	O	O
of	O	O
World	EVENT	military_action/N1
War	EVENT	military_action/N1
II	EVENT	military_action/N1
,	O	O
he	O	O
initiated	O	O
the	O	O
first	EVENT	military_action/N1
Indochinese	EVENT	military_action/N1
war	EVENT	military_action/N1
of	EVENT	military_action/N1
independence	EVENT	military_action/N1
against	O	O
the	O	O
French	PERSON_TYPE	member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1
.	O	O

During	O	O
this	O	O
time	O	O
,	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
forces	O	O
made	O	O
extensive	O	O
use	O	O
of	O	O
Cambodian	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
territory	O	O
to	O	O
transport	O	O
weapons	O	O
,	O	O
supplies	O	O
,	O	O
and	O	O
troops	O	O
.	O	O

This	O	O
relationship	O	O
lasted	O	O
throughout	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnam	EVENT	military_action/N1
War	EVENT	military_action/N1
,	O	O
when	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
communists	O	O
used	O	O
Cambodia	LOCATION	country/N1
as	O	O
a	O	O
transport	O	O
route	O	O
and	O	O
staging	O	O
area	O	O
for	O	O
attacks	O	O
on	O	O
South	LOCATION	country/N1
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
.	O	O

In	O	O
1951	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
guided	O	O
the	O	O
establishment	O	O
of	O	O
a	O	O
separate	O	O
Cambodian	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
communist	O	O
party	O	O
,	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
People	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
'	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
s	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
Revolutionary	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
Party	O	O
(	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
KPRP	O	O
)	O	O
,	O	O
which	O	O
allied	O	O
with	O	O
a	O	O
nationalist	O	O
separatist	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
Cambodian	O	O
movement	O	O
,	O	O
the	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
Khmer	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
Serei	O	O
(	O	O
Free	PERSON_TYPE	member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1
Khmers	O	O
)	O	O
,	O	O
in	O	O
order	O	O
to	O	O
pursue	O	O
independence	O	O

In	O	O
accordance	O	O
with	O	O
the	O	O
1954	CONCEPT	O
Geneva	CONCEPT	O
Accords	CONCEPT	O
negotiating	O	O
the	O	O
end	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
French	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
domination	O	O
,	O	O
newly	O	O
created	O	O
communist	O	O
North	LOCATION	country/N1
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
pulled	O	O
all	O	O
of	O	O
its	O	O
Viet	ORGANISATION	interest_or_advocacy_group/N1
Minh	ORGANISATION	interest_or_advocacy_group/N1
soldiers	O	O
and	O	O
cadres	O	O
out	O	O
of	O	O
Cambodia	LOCATION	country/N1
;	O	O
however	O	O
,	O	O
since	O	O
the	O	O
KPRP	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
was	O	O
staffed	O	O
primarily	O	O
by	O	O
ethnic	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
or	O	O
Cambodians	PERSON_TYPE	member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1
under	O	O
its	O	O
tutelage	O	O
,	O	O
approximately	O	O
5	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
,	CONCEPTUAL	political_adjective/J1
000	O	O
Communist	O	O
cadres	O	O
went	O	O
with	O	O

The	O	O
power	O	O
vacuum	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
communists	O	O
left	O	O
in	O	O
its	O	O
wake	O	O
in	O	O
Cambodia	LOCATION	country/N1
was	O	O
soon	O	O
filled	O	O
by	O	O
the	O	O
return	O	O
of	O	O
a	O	O
young	O	O
group	O	O
of	O	O
Cambodian	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
communist	O	O
revolutionaries	O	O
,	O	O
many	O	O
of	O	O
whom	O	O
received	O	O
their	O	O
communist	O	O
education	O	O
in	O	O
France	LOCATION	country/N1
.	O	O

In	O	O
1960	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
the	O	O
KPRP	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
changed	O	O
its	O	O
name	O	O
to	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
Communist	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
Party	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
(	O	O
KCP	ORGANISATION	O
)	O	O
,	O	O
and	O	O
the	O	O
name	O	O
was	O	O
later	O	O
adopted	O	O
by	O	O
the	O	O
majority	O	O
coalition	O	O
that	O	O
formed	O	O
around	O	O
Saloth	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
Sar	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
(	O	O
Pol	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
Pot	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
)	O	O
,	O	O
Ieng	PERSON	politician/N2
Sary	PERSON	politician/N2
and	O	O
Khieu	PERSON	politician/N2
Samphan	PERSON	politician/N2
as	O	O
the	O	O
'	O	O
true	O	O
'	O	O
political	O	O
institution	O	O
memorialising	O	O
the	O	O
KCP	ORGANISATION	O
.	O	O

This	O	O
clique	O	O
became	O	O
the	O	O
genesis	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
Khmer	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Rouge	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
,	O	O
and	O	O
its	O	O
doctrine	O	O
was	O	O
heavily	O	O
influenced	O	O
by	O	O
the	O	O
Maoist	CONCEPTUAL	political_adjective/J1
ideology	O	O
.	O	O

Democratic	LOCATION	historical_country/N1
Kampuchea	LOCATION	historical_country/N1
and	O	O
the	O	O
Khmer	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Rouge	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1

The	O	O
Khmer	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Rouge	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
government	O	O
adopted	O	O
the	O	O
mysterious	O	O
term	O	O
Angkar	PERSON	O
,	O	O
or	O	O
"	O	O
the	O	O
organisation	O	O
"	O	O
and	O	O
,	O	O
until	O	O
1977	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
the	O	O
identities	O	O
of	O	O
its	O	O
leaders	O	O
remained	O	O
confidential	O	O
.	O	O

The	O	O
official	O	O
head	O	O
of	O	O
state	O	O
was	O	O
Khieu	PERSON	politician/N2
Samphan	PERSON	politician/N2
,	O	O
but	O	O
the	O	O
two	O	O
men	O	O
in	O	O
control	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
Party	O	O
were	O	O
Pol	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
Pot	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
and	O	O
Ieng	PERSON	politician/N2
Sary	PERSON	politician/N2
.	O	O

The	O	O
ultimate	O	O
objective	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
Khmer	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Rouge	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
was	O	O
to	O	O
erase	O	O
the	O	O
structure	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
Cambodian	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
state	O	O
,	O	O
which	O	O
they	O	O
viewed	O	O
as	O	O
feudal	O	O
,	O	O
capitalist	O	O
,	O	O
and	O	O
oriented	O	O
around	O	O
the	O	O
agendas	O	O
of	O	O
both	O	O
the	O	O
landholding	O	O
elite	O	O
and	O	O
imperialists	O	O
.	O	O

In	O	O
its	O	O
place	O	O
,	O	O
they	O	O
hoped	O	O
to	O	O
create	O	O
a	O	O
classless	O	O
society	O	O
based	O	O
entirely	O	O
on	O	O
worker	O	O
-	O	O
peasants	O	O
.	O	O

The	O	O
radical	O	O
ideologies	O	O
and	O	O
goals	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
Khmer	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Rouge	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
were	O	O
alien	O	O
concepts	O	O
to	O	O
the	O	O
masses	O	O
.	O	O

In	O	O
fact	O	O
,	O	O
the	O	O
socialist	O	O
revolution	O	O
held	O	O
very	O	O
little	O	O
popular	O	O
appeal	O	O
,	O	O
which	O	O
led	O	O
Pol	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
Pot	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
and	O	O
his	O	O
cadres	O	O
to	O	O
use	O	O
ultra	O	O
-	O	O
nationalist	O	O
sentiment	O	O
,	O	O
repressive	O	O
and	O	O
murderous	O	O
rule	O	O
,	O	O
and	O	O
propaganda	O	O
aimed	O	O
at	O	O
demonising	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
to	O	O
maintain	O	O
their	O	O
tenuous	O	O
control	O	O
.	O	O

During	O	O
the	O	O
five	O	O
years	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
Khmer	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Rouge	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
rebellion	O	O
from	O	O
1970	PERIOD	date/N7
to	O	O
1975	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
the	O	O
support	O	O
of	O	O
North	LOCATION	country/N1
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
,	O	O
in	O	O
conjunction	O	O
with	O	O
China	LOCATION	country/N1
,	O	O
was	O	O
essential	O	O
to	O	O
its	O	O
eventual	O	O
triumph	O	O
.	O	O

However	O	O
,	O	O
even	O	O
before	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnam	EVENT	military_action/N1
War	EVENT	military_action/N1
ended	O	O
,	O	O
the	O	O
relationship	O	O
between	O	O
the	O	O
Khmer	PERSON_TYPE	member_of_a_military_group/N1
Rouge	PERSON_TYPE	member_of_a_military_group/N1
-	O	O
-	O	O
which	O	O
was	O	O
in	O	O
the	O	O
process	O	O
of	O	O
seizing	O	O
power	O	O
from	O	O
a	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
US	O	O
-	O	O
backed	O	O
regime	O	O
headed	O	O
by	PERSON	politician/N2
Lon	PERSON	politician/N2
Nol	O	O
-	O	O
-	LOCATION	country/N1
and	O	O
Vietnam	O	O
was	O	O

Clashes	O	O
between	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
communists	O	O
and	O	O
Khmer	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Rouge	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
forces	O	O
began	O	O
as	O	O
early	O	O
as	O	O
1974	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
and	O	O
the	O	O
following	O	O
year	O	O
Pol	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
Pot	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
signed	O	O
a	O	O
treaty	O	O
codifying	O	O
the	O	O
'	O	O
friendship	O	O
'	O	O
between	O	O
the	O	O
Khmer	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Rouge	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
and	O	O
China	LOCATION	country/N1
.	O	O

Diplomacy	O	O
and	O	O
military	O	O
action	O	O

1975	PERIOD	date/N7
-	PERIOD	date/N7
76	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
from	O	O
fighting	O	O
to	O	O
building	O	O
friendly	O	O
relations	O	O

The	O	O
conclusion	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
Indochina	LOCATION	other_non-political_region/N1
conflict	O	O
in	O	O
April	PERIOD	date/N7
1975	PERIOD	date/N7
immediately	O	O
brought	O	O
a	O	O
new	O	O
conflict	O	O
between	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
and	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
.	O	O

Although	O	O
both	O	O
the	O	O
North	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
and	O	O
the	O	O
Khmer	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Rouge	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
had	O	O
previously	O	O
fought	O	O
side	O	O
by	O	O
side	O	O
,	O	O
the	O	O
leaders	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
newly	O	O
created	O	O
Democratic	LOCATION	historical_country/N1
Kampuchea	LOCATION	historical_country/N1
continued	O	O
to	O	O
view	O	O
North	LOCATION	country/N1
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
with	O	O
great	O	O
suspicion	O	O
,	O	O
because	O	O
they	O	O
believed	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
Communists	PERSON_TYPE	member_of_a_political_group/N1
had	O	O
never	O	O
given	O	O
up	O	O
their	O	O
dream	O	O
of	O	O
creating	O	O
an	O	O
Indochinese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
federation	O	O
with	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
as	O	O
the	O	O
leader	O	O
.	O	O

For	O	O
that	O	O
reason	O	O
,	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
Government	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
decided	O	O
to	O	O
remove	O	O
all	O	O
North	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
military	O	O
forces	O	O
from	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
territory	O	O
shortly	O	O
after	O	O
their	O	O
capture	O	O
of	O	O
Phnom	LOCATION	municipality/N1
Penh	LOCATION	municipality/N1
in	O	O
1975	PERIOD	date/N7
.	O	O

In	O	O
the	O	O
first	O	O
major	O	O
clash	O	O
between	O	O
the	O	O
two	O	O
former	O	O
allies	O	O
,	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
Revolutionary	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
Army	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
invaded	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
island	O	O
of	O	O
Phu	LOCATION	island/N1
Quoc	LOCATION	island/N1
on	O	O
1	PERIOD	date/N7
May	PERIOD	date/N7
1975	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
which	O	O
they	O	O
claimed	O	O
was	O	O
part	O	O
of	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
'	O	O
s	O	O
territory	O	O

Nine	O	O
days	O	O
later	O	O
,	O	O
on	O	O
10	PERIOD	date/N7
May	PERIOD	date/N7
1975	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
military	O	O
continued	O	O
its	O	O
incursion	O	O
by	O	O
capturing	O	O
Tho	LOCATION	island/N1
Chu	LOCATION	island/N1
,	O	O
where	O	O
it	O	O
executed	O	O
500	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
civilians	O	O
.	O	O

The	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
military	O	O
immediately	O	O
responded	O	O
to	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
actions	O	O
by	O	O
launching	O	O
a	O	O
counter	O	O
-	O	O
attack	O	O
and	O	O
removing	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
forces	O	O
from	O	O
Phu	LOCATION	island/N1
Quoc	LOCATION	island/N1
and	O	O
Tho	LOCATION	island/N1
Chu	LOCATION	island/N1
,	O	O
and	O	O
then	O	O
invading	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
island	O	O
of	O	O
Koh	LOCATION	island/N1
Wai	LOCATION	island/N1
.	O	O

In	O	O
June	PERIOD	date/N7
1975	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
while	O	O
on	O	O
a	O	O
visit	O	O
to	O	O
Hanoi	LOCATION	municipality/N1
,	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
leader	O	O
Pol	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
Pot	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
proposed	O	O
that	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
and	O	O
his	O	O
country	O	O
should	O	O
sign	O	O
a	O	O
treaty	O	O
of	O	O
friendship	O	O
and	O	O
begin	O	O
discussions	O	O
on	O	O
border	O	O
disputes	O	O
.	O	O

However	O	O
,	O	O
those	O	O
discussions	O	O
never	O	O
materialised	O	O
,	O	O
and	O	O
the	O	O
Kampucheans	PERSON_TYPE	member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1
claimed	O	O
that	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
turned	O	O
down	O	O
both	O	O
offers	O	O
.	O	O

In	O	O
August	PERIOD	date/N7
1975	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
returned	O	O
the	O	O
island	O	O
of	O	O
Koh	LOCATION	island/N1
Wai	LOCATION	island/N1
to	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
and	O	O
formally	O	O
recognised	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
sovereignty	O	O
over	O	O
the	O	O
island	O	O
.	O	O

Following	O	O
those	O	O
incidents	O	O
,	O	O
both	O	O
countries	O	O
attempted	O	O
to	O	O
improve	O	O
their	O	O
diplomatic	O	O
relations	O	O
with	O	O
a	O	O
series	O	O
of	O	O
congratulatory	O	O
messages	O	O
and	O	O
exchange	O	O
visits	O	O
.	O	O

On	O	O
17	PERIOD	date/N7
April	PERIOD	date/N7
1976	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
leaders	O	O
sent	O	O
a	O	O
message	O	O
to	O	O
congratulate	O	O
Khieu	PERSON	politician/N2
Samphan	PERSON	politician/N2
,	O	O
Nuon	PERSON	politician/N2
Chea	PERSON	politician/N2
and	O	O
Pol	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
Pot	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
on	O	O
their	O	O
"	O	O
elections	O	O
"	O	O
as	O	O
President	TITLE	political_title/N1
,	O	O
President	TITLE	political_title/N1
of	O	O
the	O	O
People	O	O
'	O	O
s	O	O
Representatives	O	O
and	TITLE	political_title/N1
Premier	O	O
of	LOCATION	country/N1
Kampuchea	O	O
,	O	O
respectively	O	O

Furthermore	O	O
,	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
even	O	O
denounced	O	O
the	O	O
alleged	O	O
"	O	O
U	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
.	O	O
S	O	O
.	O	O
bombing	LOCATION	municipality/N1
"	LOCATION	municipality/N1
of	O	O
Siem	PERIOD	date/N7
Reap	PERIOD	date/N7
in	O	O
February	O	O
1976	O	O
,	O	O
thereby	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
reinforcing	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	O	O
'	O	O
s	O	O
fictitious	O	O
claim	O	O

In	O	O
response	O	O
,	O	O
in	O	O
June	PERIOD	date/N7
1976	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
leadership	O	O
sent	O	O
a	O	O
message	O	O
to	O	O
the	O	O
Provisional	LOCATION	country/N1
Revolutionary	LOCATION	country/N1
Government	LOCATION	country/N1
of	LOCATION	country/N1
the	LOCATION	country/N1
Republic	LOCATION	country/N1
of	LOCATION	country/N1
South	LOCATION	country/N1
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
,	O	O
which	O	O
had	O	O
governed	O	O
South	LOCATION	country/N1
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
since	O	O
the	O	O
fall	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
U	LOCATION	country/N1
.	O	O
S	O	O
.	O	O
-	O	O
backed	O	O
regime	O	O
,	O	O
congratulating	O	O
them	O	O
on	O	O
the	O	O
seventh	O	O
anniversary	O	O
of	O	O

In	O	O
July	PERIOD	date/N7
1976	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
following	O	O
the	O	O
establishment	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
Socialist	LOCATION	country/N1
Republic	LOCATION	country/N1
of	LOCATION	country/N1
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
as	O	O
a	O	O
reunified	O	O
country	O	O
,	O	O
Phnom	LOCATION	municipality/N1
Penh	LOCATION	municipality/N1
Radio	O	O
broadcast	O	O
a	O	O
commentary	O	O
which	O	O
proclaimed	O	O
the	O	O
"	O	O
militant	O	O
solidarity	O	O
and	O	O
friendship	O	O
between	O	O
peoples	O	O
of	O	O
Democratic	LOCATION	historical_country/N1
Kampuchea	LOCATION	historical_country/N1
and	O	O
the	O	O
Socialist	LOCATION	country/N1
Republic	LOCATION	country/N1
of	LOCATION	country/N1
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
grow	O	O
constantly	O	O
greener	O	O
and	O	O
sturdier	O	O
"	O	O
.	O	O

However	O	O
,	O	O
during	O	O
that	O	O
same	O	O
month	O	O
,	O	O
Premier	TITLE	political_title/N1
Pol	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
Pot	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
publicly	O	O
hinted	O	O
at	O	O
tensions	O	O
between	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
and	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
when	O	O
he	O	O
told	O	O
a	O	O
visiting	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
media	O	O
delegation	O	O
that	O	O
there	O	O
were	O	O
"	O	O
obstacles	O	O
and	O	O
difficulties	O	O
"	O	O
in	O	O
the	O	O
relationship	O	O
between	O	O
the	O	O
two	O	O
countries	O	O
.	O	O

Nonetheless	O	O
,	O	O
on	O	O
21	PERIOD	date/N7
September	PERIOD	date/N7
1976	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
the	O	O
first	O	O
air	O	O
service	O	O
connecting	O	O
Hanoi	LOCATION	municipality/N1
and	O	O
Ho	LOCATION	municipality/N1
Chi	LOCATION	municipality/N1
Minh	LOCATION	municipality/N1
City	LOCATION	municipality/N1
with	O	O
Phnom	LOCATION	municipality/N1
Penh	LOCATION	municipality/N1
was	O	O
established	O	O
.	O	O

Then	O	O
in	O	O
December	PERIOD	date/N7
1976	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	ORGANISATION	O
Revolutionary	ORGANISATION	O
Organisation	ORGANISATION	O
sent	O	O
greetings	O	O
to	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
Communist	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
Party	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
during	O	O
their	O	O
Fourth	O	O
Congress	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
.	O	O

1977	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
build	O	O
-	O	O
up	O	O
to	O	O
war	O	O

Towards	O	O
the	O	O
end	O	O
of	O	O
1976	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
while	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
and	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
publicly	O	O
appeared	O	O
to	O	O
be	O	O
improving	O	O
their	O	O
relationships	O	O
,	O	O
the	O	O
private	O	O
suspicions	O	O
of	O	O
both	O	O
countries	O	O
'	O	O
leadership	O	O
grew	O	O
.	O	O

From	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
perspective	O	O
,	O	O
they	O	O
were	O	O
the	O	O
patron	O	O
of	O	O
genuine	O	O
Marxist	CONCEPTUAL	political_adjective/J1
-	CONCEPTUAL	political_adjective/J1
Leninist	CONCEPTUAL	political_adjective/J1
revolutions	O	O
in	O	O
South	LOCATION	supernational_region/N1
East	LOCATION	supernational_region/N1
Asia	LOCATION	supernational_region/N1
,	O	O
so	O	O
it	O	O
was	O	O
vital	O	O
for	O	O
them	O	O
to	O	O
exercise	O	O
control	O	O
over	O	O
the	O	O
Kampucheans	PERSON_TYPE	member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1
and	O	O
the	O	O
Laotians	PERSON_TYPE	member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1
.	O	O

Indeed	O	O
,	O	O
that	O	O
was	O	O
the	O	O
reason	O	O
North	LOCATION	country/N1
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
supported	O	O
the	O	O
Khmer	PERSON_TYPE	member_of_a_military_group/N1
Rouge	PERSON_TYPE	member_of_a_military_group/N1
during	O	O
their	O	O
fight	O	O
against	O	O
the	O	O
Lon	PERSON	politician/N2
Nol	PERSON	politician/N2
regime	O	O
,	O	O
in	O	O
the	O	O
hope	O	O
that	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
communists	O	O
would	O	O
adopt	O	O
a	O	O
pro	O	O
-	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
line	O	O
upon	O	O
their	O	O
victory	O	O
in	O	O
the	O	O
same	O	O
way	O	O
the	O	O
Pathet	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
Lao	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
had	O	O
done	O	O
.	O	O

However	O	O
,	O	O
their	O	O
hopes	O	O
were	O	O
dashed	O	O
as	O	O
early	O	O
as	O	O
1973	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
because	O	O
North	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
military	O	O
formations	O	O
operating	O	O
in	O	O
Khmer	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Rouge	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
-	O	O
occupied	O	O
territories	O	O
were	O	O
occasionally	O	O
subjected	O	O
to	O	O
armed	O	O
attacks	O	O
by	O	O
their	O	O
own	O	O
allies	O	O
.	O	O

The	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
position	O	O
inside	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
was	O	O
further	O	O
weakened	O	O
after	O	O
the	O	O
end	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
war	O	O
,	O	O
as	O	O
there	O	O
were	O	O
no	O	O
pro	O	O
-	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
elements	O	O
left	O	O
within	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
Communist	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
Party	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
.	O	O

Thus	O	O
,	O	O
when	O	O
the	O	O
pro	O	O
-	O	O
Chinese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
Pol	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
Pot	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
and	O	O
his	O	O
brother	O	O
-	O	O
in	O	O
-	O	O
law	O	O
Ieng	PERSON	politician/N2
Sary	PERSON	politician/N2
resigned	O	O
from	O	O
their	O	O
respective	O	O
positions	O	O
as	O	O
Premier	TITLE	political_title/N1
and	O	O
Foreign	TITLE	political_title/N1
Minister	TITLE	political_title/N1
in	O	O
September	PERIOD	date/N7
1976	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
Prime	TITLE	political_title/N1
Minister	TITLE	political_title/N1
Pham	PERSON	politician/N2
Van	PERSON	politician/N2
Djong	PERSON	politician/N2
and	O	O
General	TITLE	military_title/N1
Secretary	TITLE	political_title/N1
of	O	O
the	O	O
Communist	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
Party	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
Le	PERSON	politician/N2
Duan	PERSON	politician/N2
were	O	O
optimistic	O	O
that	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
could	O	O
exercise	O	O
greater	O	O
influence	O	O
on	O	O
the	O	O
Kampucheans	PERSON_TYPE	member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1
.	O	O

In	O	O
a	O	O
private	O	O
meeting	O	O
with	O	O
the	O	O
Soviet	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
ambassador	O	O
to	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
on	O	O
16	PERIOD	date/N7
November	PERIOD	date/N7
1976	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
Le	PERSON	politician/N2
Duan	PERSON	politician/N2
dismissed	O	O
both	O	O
Ieng	PERSON	politician/N2
Sary	PERSON	politician/N2
and	O	O
Pol	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
Pot	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
as	O	O
"	O	O
bad	O	O
people	O	O
"	O	O
for	O	O
their	O	O
pro	O	O
-	O	O
Chinese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
policies	O	O
.	O	O

Le	PERSON	politician/N2
Duan	PERSON	politician/N2
then	O	O
asserted	O	O
that	O	O
Nuon	PERSON	politician/N2
Chea	PERSON	politician/N2
,	O	O
who	O	O
had	O	O
ascended	O	O
to	O	O
the	O	O
position	O	O
of	O	O
Premier	TITLE	political_title/N1
of	O	O
Democratic	LOCATION	historical_country/N1
Kampuchea	LOCATION	historical_country/N1
as	O	O
Pol	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
Pot	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
'	O	O
s	O	O
replacement	O	O
,	O	O
was	O	O
a	O	O
person	O	O
of	O	O
pro	O	O
-	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
Vietnamese	O	O
orientation	O	O
,	O	O
so	LOCATION	country/N1
Vietnam	O	O
could	O	O
exercise	O	O
its	O	O
influence	O	O
through	O	O
him	O	O

However	O	O
,	O	O
the	O	O
events	O	O
which	O	O
developed	O	O
over	O	O
the	O	O
next	O	O
few	O	O
months	O	O
would	O	O
prove	O	O
Le	PERSON	politician/N2
Duan	PERSON	politician/N2
had	O	O
been	O	O
mistaken	O	O
in	O	O
his	O	O
assessment	O	O
of	O	O
Nuon	PERSON	politician/N2
Chea	PERSON	politician/N2
.	O	O

Meanwhile	O	O
,	O	O
in	O	O
Phnom	LOCATION	municipality/N1
Penh	LOCATION	municipality/N1
,	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
leadership	O	O
had	O	O
developed	O	O
a	O	O
seething	O	O
fear	O	O
and	O	O
hatred	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
leadership	O	O
as	O	O
a	O	O
result	O	O
of	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
'	O	O
s	O	O
historical	O	O
dominance	O	O
over	O	O
their	O	O
country	O	O

From	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
perspective	O	O
,	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
strategy	O	O
to	O	O
dominate	O	O
Indochina	LOCATION	supernational_region/N1
involved	O	O
infiltrating	O	O
the	O	O
communist	O	O
parties	O	O
of	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
and	O	O
Laos	LOCATION	country/N1
with	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
-	O	O
trained	O	O
cadres	O	O
.	O	O

For	O	O
that	O	O
reason	O	O
,	O	O
when	O	O
the	O	O
first	O	O
group	O	O
of	O	O
North	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
-	O	O
trained	O	O
Khmer	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Rouge	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
personnel	O	O
returned	O	O
to	O	O
the	O	O
country	O	O
,	O	O
they	O	O
were	O	O
immediately	O	O
purged	O	O
from	O	O
the	O	O
Party	O	O
.	O	O

During	O	O
the	O	O
months	O	O
following	O	O
the	O	O
defeat	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
Lon	PERSON	politician/N2
Nol	PERSON	politician/N2
regime	O	O
,	O	O
Pol	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
Pot	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
continued	O	O
to	O	O
purge	O	O
his	O	O
own	O	O
party	O	O
and	O	O
the	O	O
Government	O	O
of	O	O
Democratic	LOCATION	historical_country/N1
Kampuchea	LOCATION	historical_country/N1
of	O	O
those	O	O
who	O	O
he	O	O
believed	O	O
to	O	O
be	O	O
Soviet	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
and	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
agents	O	O
.	O	O

Then	O	O
,	O	O
in	O	O
the	O	O
context	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
triumphalism	O	O
,	O	O
which	O	O
prevailed	O	O
over	O	O
the	O	O
Khmer	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Rouge	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
leadership	O	O
in	O	O
a	O	O
war	O	O
that	O	O
they	O	O
claimed	O	O
they	O	O
had	O	O
single	O	O
-	O	O
handedly	O	O
defeated	O	O
the	O	O
"	O	O
American	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
imperialist	O	O
"	O	O
,	O	O
Democratic	LOCATION	historical_country/N1
Kampuchea	LOCATION	historical_country/N1
began	O	O
to	O	O
embark	O	O
on	O	O
a	O	O
war	O	O
against	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
.	O	O

As	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
Revolutionary	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
Army	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
made	O	O
preparations	O	O
for	O	O
its	O	O
war	O	O
against	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
,	O	O
state	O	O
-	O	O
controlled	O	O
media	O	O
in	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
sent	O	O
congratulatory	O	O
messages	O	O
to	O	O
the	O	O
Government	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
Democratic	LOCATION	historical_country/N1
Kampuchea	LOCATION	historical_country/N1
on	O	O
the	O	O
second	O	O
anniversary	O	O
of	O	O
its	O	O
establishment	O	O
,	O	O
on	O	O
17	PERIOD	date/N7
April	PERIOD	date/N7
1977	PERIOD	date/N7
.	O	O

On	O	O
30	PERIOD	date/N7
April	PERIOD	date/N7
1977	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
the	O	O
second	O	O
anniversary	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
fall	EVENT	military_action/N1
of	EVENT	military_action/N1
Saigon	EVENT	military_action/N1
,	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
reply	O	O
came	O	O
in	O	O
the	O	O
form	O	O
of	O	O
a	O	O
military	O	O
attack	O	O
against	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
provinces	O	O
of	O	O
An	LOCATION	state/N2
Giang	LOCATION	state/N2
and	O	O
Chau	LOCATION	delimited_body_of_water/N1
Djoc	LOCATION	delimited_body_of_water/N1
,	O	O
killing	O	O
hundreds	O	O
of	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
civilians	O	O
.	O	O

The	O	O
Vietnam	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
People	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
'	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
s	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
Army	O	O
responded	O	O
by	O	O
moving	O	O
its	O	O
troops	O	O
to	O	O
areas	O	O
attacked	O	O
by	LOCATION	country/N1
Kampuchea	O	O
and	O	O
,	O	O
on	PERIOD	date/N7
7	PERIOD	date/N7
June	PERIOD	date/N7
1977	O	O
,	LOCATION	country/N1
Vietnam	O	O
proposed	O	O
high	O	O
-	O	O
level	O	O
talks	O	O
to	O	O
discuss	O	O
outstanding	O	O
issues	O	O

On	O	O
18	PERIOD	date/N7
June	PERIOD	date/N7
1977	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
Government	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
replied	O	O
by	O	O
demanding	O	O
that	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
remove	O	O
all	O	O
of	O	O
its	O	O
military	O	O
units	O	O
from	O	O
the	O	O
disputed	O	O
areas	O	O
,	O	O
and	O	O
create	O	O
a	O	O
demilitarised	O	O
zone	O	O
between	O	O
the	O	O
opposing	O	O
forces	O	O
.	O	O

Both	O	O
sides	O	O
ignored	O	O
each	O	O
other	O	O
'	O	O
s	O	O
proposals	O	O
,	O	O
and	O	O
the	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
Kampuchean	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
Revolutionary	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
Army	O	O
continued	O	O
sending	O	O
soldiers	O	O
across	O	O
the	O	O
border	O	O
to	O	O
attack	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
Vietnamese	O	O
towns	O	O
and	O	O
villages	O	O

In	O	O
September	PERIOD	date/N7
1977	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
artillery	O	O
struck	O	O
several	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
villages	O	O
along	O	O
the	O	O
border	O	O
,	O	O
and	O	O
six	O	O
villages	O	O
in	O	O
Djong	LOCATION	state/N2
Thap	LOCATION	state/N2
Province	LOCATION	state/N2
were	O	O
overrun	O	O
by	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
infantry	O	O
.	O	O

Shortly	O	O
afterwards	O	O
,	O	O
six	O	O
divisions	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchea	ORGANISATION	O
Revolutionary	ORGANISATION	O
Army	ORGANISATION	O
advanced	O	O
about	O	O
10	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
kilometers	O	O
(	O	O
6	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
.	O	O
2	O	O
mi	O	O
)	LOCATION	state/N2
into	LOCATION	state/N2
Tay	LOCATION	state/N2
Ninh	O	O
Province	O	O
,	O	O
where	O	O
they	O	O
killed	O	O
more	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
than	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
1	O	O
,	O	O

Angered	O	O
by	O	O
the	O	O
scale	O	O
of	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
assaults	O	O
,	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnam	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
People	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
'	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
s	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
Army	O	O
assembled	O	O
eight	O	O
divisions	O	O
,	O	O
estimated	O	O
at	O	O
around	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
60	O	O
,	O	O
000	O	O
soldiers	O	O
,	O	O
to	O	O
launch	O	O
a	O	O
retaliatory	LOCATION	country/N1
strike	O	O

On	O	O
16	PERIOD	date/N7
December	PERIOD	date/N7
1977	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
divisions	O	O
,	O	O
with	O	O
support	O	O
from	O	O
elements	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnam	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
People	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
'	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
s	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
Air	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
Force	O	O
,	O	O
crossed	O	O
the	O	O
border	O	O
along	O	O
several	O	O
axes	O	O
with	O	O
the	O	O
objective	O	O
of	O	O
forcing	O	O
the	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
Kampuchean	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
Government	O	O
to	O	O
negotiate	O	O

On	O	O
the	O	O
battlefield	O	O
,	O	O
the	O	O
Kampucheans	PERSON_TYPE	member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1
quickly	O	O
lost	O	O
ground	O	O
as	O	O
their	O	O
combat	O	O
units	O	O
were	O	O
pushed	O	O
back	O	O
by	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
.	O	O

By	O	O
the	O	O
end	O	O
of	O	O
December	PERIOD	date/N7
1977	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
had	O	O
won	O	O
a	O	O
clear	O	O
military	O	O
victory	O	O
over	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
,	O	O
as	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
formations	O	O
marched	O	O
through	O	O
Svay	LOCATION	state/N2
Rieng	LOCATION	state/N2
Province	LOCATION	state/N2
and	O	O
only	O	O
stopped	O	O
short	O	O
of	O	O
entering	O	O
the	O	O
provincial	O	O
capital	O	O
.	O	O

Despite	O	O
the	O	O
ferocity	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
retaliation	O	O
,	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
Government	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
remained	O	O
defiant	O	O
.	O	O

On	O	O
31	PERIOD	date/N7
December	PERIOD	date/N7
1977	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
Khieu	PERSON	O
Sampham	PERSON	O
declared	O	O
that	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
Government	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
would	O	O
"	O	O
temporarily	O	O
"	O	O
sever	O	O
diplomatic	O	O
relations	O	O
with	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
until	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
military	O	O
withdraw	O	O
from	O	O
the	O	O
"	O	O
sacred	O	O
territory	O	O
of	O	O
Democratic	LOCATION	historical_country/N1
Kampuchea	LOCATION	historical_country/N1
"	O	O
.	O	O

On	O	O
6	PERIOD	date/N7
January	PERIOD	date/N7
1978	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
divisions	O	O
were	O	O
only	O	O
38	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
kilometers	O	O
(	O	O
24	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
mi	O	O
)	O	O
from	O	O
Phnom	LOCATION	municipality/N1
Penh	LOCATION	municipality/N1
,	O	O
but	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
Government	O	O
decided	O	O
to	O	O
withdraw	O	O
its	O	O
forces	O	O
from	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
because	O	O
they	O	O
had	O	O
failed	O	O
to	O	O
achieve	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
'	O	O
s	O	O
political	O	O
objective	O	O

During	O	O
the	O	O
withdrawal	O	O
,	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
military	O	O
also	O	O
evacuated	O	O
thousands	O	O
of	O	O
prisoners	O	O
and	O	O
civilian	O	O
refugees	O	O
,	O	O
including	O	O
future	O	O
leader	O	O
Hun	PERSON	politician/N2
Sen	PERSON	politician/N2

1978	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
preparations	O	O
for	O	O
regime	O	O
change	O	O

Instead	O	O
of	O	O
being	O	O
sobered	O	O
by	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
show	O	O
of	O	O
force	O	O
,	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
Government	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
boasted	O	O
that	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
withdrawal	O	O
was	O	O
a	O	O
major	O	O
victory	O	O
for	O	O
Democratic	LOCATION	historical_country/N1
Kampuchea	LOCATION	historical_country/N1
,	O	O
comparing	O	O
it	O	O
to	O	O
the	O	O
"	O	O
defeat	O	O
of	O	O
U	LOCATION	country/N1
.	O	O
S	O	O
.	O	O
imperialism	PERIOD	date/N7
"	PERIOD	date/N7
on	PERIOD	date/N7
17	O	O

The	O	O
Kampucheans	PERSON_TYPE	member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1
went	O	O
on	O	O
further	O	O
to	O	O
proclaim	O	O
that	O	O
"	O	O
our	O	O
6	PERIOD	date/N7
January	PERIOD	date/N7
victory	O	O
over	O	O
the	O	O
annexationist	O	O
,	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
aggressor	O	O
enemy	O	O
has	O	O
given	O	O
all	O	O
of	O	O
us	O	O
greater	O	O
confidence	O	O
in	O	O
the	O	O
forces	O	O
of	O	O
our	O	O
people	O	O
and	O	O
nation	O	O
,	O	O
in	O	O
our	O	O
Kampuchean	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
Communist	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
Party	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
and	O	O
our	O	O
Kampuchean	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
Revolutionary	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
Army	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
,	O	O
and	O	O
in	O	O
our	O	O
Party	O	O
'	O	O
s	O	O
line	O	O
of	O	O
people	O	O
'	O	O
s	O	O
war	O	O

The	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
leadership	O	O
claimed	O	O
that	O	O
one	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
soldier	O	O
was	O	O
equal	O	O
to	O	O
30	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
soldiers	O	O
,	O	O
so	O	O
if	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
could	O	O
raise	O	O
two	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
million	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
soldiers	O	O
from	O	O
a	O	O
population	O	O
of	O	O
eight	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
million	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
,	O	O
it	O	O
could	O	O
wipe	O	O
out	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
'	O	O
s	O	O
population	O	O
of	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
50	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
million	O	O
and	O	O
still	O	O
have	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
six	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
million	O	O
people	O	O
left	O	O

In	O	O
reality	O	O
,	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
leaders	O	O
simply	O	O
ignored	O	O
the	O	O
condition	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
population	O	O
in	O	O
their	O	O
own	O	O
country	O	O
and	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
;	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
,	O	O
though	O	O
poor	O	O
,	O	O
were	O	O
in	O	O
good	O	O
physical	O	O
condition	O	O
,	O	O
while	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
'	O	O
s	O	O
population	O	O
was	O	O
physically	O	O
and	O	O
mentally	O	O
exhausted	O	O
from	O	O
years	O	O
of	O	O
hard	O	O
labour	O	O
,	O	O
starvation	O	O
and	O	O
disease	O	O

In	O	O
addition	O	O
to	O	O
the	O	O
disparity	O	O
in	O	O
population	O	O
,	O	O
there	O	O
was	O	O
also	O	O
a	O	O
great	O	O
disparity	O	O
between	O	O
the	O	O
fighting	O	O
capabilities	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
armed	O	O
forces	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
two	O	O
countries	O	O
.	O	O

In	O	O
1977	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
Vietnam	EVENT	military_action/N1
was	O	O
estimated	O	O
to	O	O
have	O	O
615	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
,	O	O
000	O	O
soldiers	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
and	O	O
900	O	O
tanks	O	O
,	O	O
supported	O	O
by	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
a	O	O
12	O	O
,	O	O
000	O	O
-	O	O
member	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
air	O	O
force	O	O
with	O	O
300	O	O
combat	O	O
aircraft	O	O
,	O	O
including	O	O
one	O	O
squadron	O	O

In	O	O
comparison	O	O
,	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
had	O	O
an	O	O
army	O	O
of	O	O
70	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
,	O	O
000	O	O
,	O	O
only	O	O
a	O	O
few	O	O
heavy	O	O
tanks	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
,	O	O
200	O	O
armoured	O	O
vehicles	O	O
,	O	O
and	O	O
limited	O	O
air	O	O

Despite	O	O
facing	O	O
such	O	O
heavy	O	O
odds	O	O
,	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
showed	O	O
no	O	O
signs	O	O
of	O	O
hesitation	O	O
as	O	O
its	O	O
military	O	O
continued	O	O
to	O	O
assault	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
'	O	O
s	O	O
border	O	O
regions	O	O

In	O	O
January	PERIOD	date/N7
1978	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
forces	O	O
still	O	O
held	O	O
portions	O	O
of	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
territory	O	O
and	O	O
began	O	O
overrunning	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
outposts	O	O
in	O	O
Ha	LOCATION	state/N2
Tien	LOCATION	state/N2
Province	LOCATION	state/N2
.	O	O

On	O	O
27	PERIOD	date/N7
January	PERIOD	date/N7
1978	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
started	O	O
calling	O	O
on	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
military	O	O
along	O	O
the	O	O
border	O	O
regions	O	O
to	O	O
overthrow	O	O
the	O	O
Khmer	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Rouge	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
regime	O	O
.	O	O

Against	O	O
the	O	O
backdrop	O	O
of	O	O
military	O	O
clashes	O	O
,	O	O
between	O	O
9	PERIOD	date/N7
January	PERIOD	date/N7
and	O	O
20	PERIOD	date/N7
February	PERIOD	date/N7
1978	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
Deputy	TITLE	political_title/N1
Foreign	TITLE	political_title/N1
Minister	TITLE	political_title/N1
Phan	PERSON	politician/N2
Hien	PERSON	politician/N2
made	O	O
several	O	O
trips	O	O
to	O	O
Beijing	LOCATION	municipality/N1
to	O	O
hold	O	O
discussions	O	O
with	O	O
representatives	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
Government	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
,	O	O
which	O	O
ultimately	O	O
proved	O	O
to	O	O
be	O	O
fruitless	O	O
.	O	O

On	O	O
18	PERIOD	date/N7
January	PERIOD	date/N7
1978	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
China	LOCATION	country/N1
attempted	O	O
to	O	O
mediate	O	O
further	O	O
negotiations	O	O
between	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
and	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
when	O	O
Vice	TITLE	political_title/N1
Premier	TITLE	political_title/N1
Deng	PERSON	politician/N2
Yingchao	PERSON	politician/N2
travelled	O	O
to	O	O
Phnom	LOCATION	municipality/N1
Penh	LOCATION	municipality/N1
,	O	O
where	O	O
she	O	O
was	O	O
met	O	O
with	O	O
strong	O	O
resistance	O	O
by	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
leaders	O	O
.	O	O

Meanwhile	O	O
,	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
government	O	O
officials	O	O
began	O	O
conducting	O	O
secret	O	O
meetings	O	O
with	O	O
So	O	O
Phim	PERSON	O
,	O	O
the	O	O
Khmer	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Rouge	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
leader	O	O
in	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
'	O	O
s	LOCATION	O
Eastern	LOCATION	O
Military	LOCATION	O
Zone	O	O
,	O	O
to	O	O
plan	O	O
a	O	O
military	O	O
uprising	O	O
backed	O	O
by	LOCATION	country/N1
Vietnam	O	O

During	O	O
that	O	O
same	O	O
period	O	O
,	O	O
military	O	O
setbacks	O	O
experienced	O	O
by	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
Revolutionary	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
Army	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
in	O	O
the	O	O
Eastern	LOCATION	O
Military	LOCATION	O
Zone	LOCATION	O
prompted	O	O
Pol	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
Pot	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
to	O	O
label	O	O
the	O	O
region	O	O
as	O	O
a	O	O
"	O	O
nest	O	O
of	O	O
traitors	O	O
"	O	O
.	O	O

In	O	O
order	O	O
to	O	O
purge	O	O
the	O	O
Eastern	LOCATION	O
Military	LOCATION	O
Zone	LOCATION	O
of	O	O
those	O	O
he	O	O
perceived	O	O
to	O	O
have	O	O
been	O	O
contaminated	O	O
by	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
,	O	O
Pol	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
Pot	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
ordered	O	O
military	O	O
units	O	O
from	O	O
the	O	O
Southwest	LOCATION	O
Zone	LOCATION	O
to	O	O
move	O	O
into	O	O
eastern	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
and	O	O
eliminate	O	O
the	O	O
"	O	O
hidden	O	O
traitors	O	O
"	O	O
.	O	O

Unable	O	O
to	O	O
withstand	O	O
an	O	O
attack	O	O
from	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
Government	O	O
,	O	O
So	O	O
Phim	PERSON	O
committed	O	O
suicide	O	O
while	O	O
his	O	O
deputy	O	O
Heng	PERSON	politician/N2
Samrin	PERSON	politician/N2
defected	O	O
to	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
.	O	O

On	O	O
12	PERIOD	date/N7
April	PERIOD	date/N7
1978	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
Government	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
declared	O	O
they	O	O
and	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
could	O	O
negotiate	O	O
again	O	O
if	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
gave	O	O
up	O	O
their	O	O
expansionist	O	O
ambitions	O	O
and	O	O
recognised	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
'	O	O
s	O	O
sovereignty	O	O

However	O	O
,	O	O
there	O	O
was	O	O
also	O	O
a	O	O
pre	O	O
-	O	O
condition	O	O
requiring	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
to	O	O
meet	O	O
several	O	O
obligations	O	O
through	O	O
a	O	O
seven	O	O
-	O	O
month	O	O
trial	O	O
ceasefire	O	O
.	O	O

The	O	O
Vietnamese	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
Government	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
immediately	O	O
rejected	O	O
the	O	O
demand	O	O
and	O	O
,	O	O
in	O	O
response	O	O
,	O	O
two	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
divisions	O	O
penetrated	O	O
up	O	O
to	O	O
2	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
kilometers	O	O
(	O	O
1	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
.	O	O
2	O	O
mi	O	O
)	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
into	O	O
Vietnamese	O	O
territory	O	O
,	O	O
and	O	O
massacred	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
over	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
3	O	O
,	O	O
000	O	O
Vietnamese	O	O
civilians	O	O
in	LOCATION	municipality/N1
the	LOCATION	municipality/N1
village	O	O
of	LOCATION	state/N2
Ba	LOCATION	state/N2
Chuc	LOCATION	state/N2
in	O	O

In	O	O
June	PERIOD	date/N7
1978	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
Air	O	O
Force	O	O
started	O	O
bombing	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
positions	O	O
along	O	O
the	O	O
border	O	O
regions	O	O
,	O	O
flying	O	O
about	O	O
30	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
bombing	O	O
sorties	O	O
per	O	O
day	O	O
and	O	O
inflicting	O	O
heavy	O	O
casualties	O	O
on	O	O
the	O	O
Kampucheans	PERSON_TYPE	member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1
.	O	O

By	O	O
that	O	O
stage	O	O
in	O	O
the	O	O
conflict	O	O
,	O	O
most	O	O
surviving	O	O
leaders	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
Eastern	LOCATION	O
Military	LOCATION	O
Zone	LOCATION	O
had	O	O
escaped	O	O
into	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
,	O	O
where	O	O
they	O	O
assembled	O	O
at	O	O
various	O	O
secret	O	O
camps	O	O
with	O	O
the	O	O
purpose	O	O
of	O	O
forming	O	O
a	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
-	O	O
backed	O	O
"	O	O
liberation	O	O
army	O	O
"	O	O
to	O	O
fight	O	O
against	O	O
Pol	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
Pot	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
'	O	O
s	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Khmer	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Rouge	O	O
regime	O	O

Meanwhile	O	O
,	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	ORGANISATION	government_department/N1
Communist	ORGANISATION	government_department/N1
Party	ORGANISATION	government_department/N1
Politburo	ORGANISATION	government_department/N1
was	O	O
meeting	O	O
in	O	O
Hanoi	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
to	O	O
discuss	O	O
its	O	O
strategy	O	O
for	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
.	O	O

It	O	O
concluded	O	O
that	O	O
the	O	O
Khmer	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Rouge	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
regime	O	O
was	O	O
a	O	O
proxy	O	O
of	O	O
China	LOCATION	country/N1
,	O	O
which	O	O
had	O	O
been	O	O
trying	O	O
to	O	O
fill	O	O
the	O	O
power	O	O
vacuum	O	O
following	O	O
the	O	O
withdrawal	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
United	LOCATION	country/N1
States	LOCATION	country/N1
.	O	O

As	O	O
such	O	O
,	O	O
China	LOCATION	country/N1
was	O	O
identified	O	O
as	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
'	O	O
s	O	O
main	O	O
enemy	O	O
,	O	O
and	O	O
its	O	O
client	O	O
regime	O	O
in	LOCATION	municipality/N1
Phnom	LOCATION	municipality/N1
Penh	O	O
had	O	O
to	O	O
be	O	O
removed	O	O
by	O	O
conventional	O	O
military	O	O
force	O	O
,	O	O
because	O	O
the	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
Vietnamese	O	O
adaptation	O	O
of	O	O
the	CONCEPTUAL	political_adjective/J1
Maoist	O	O
"	O	O
people	O	O
'	O	O
s	O	O
war	O	O
"	O	O
doctrine	O	O
had	O	O
not	O	O
been	O	O
a	O	O
success	O	O
against	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
the	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Khmer	O	O
Rouge	O	O
'	O	O
s	O	O

To	O	O
reflect	O	O
the	O	O
attitude	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
country	O	O
'	O	O
s	O	O
leaders	O	O
,	LOCATION	country/N1
Vietnam	O	O
'	O	O
s	O	O
state	O	O
-	O	O
controlled	O	O
media	O	O
stepped	O	O
up	O	O
its	O	O
propaganda	O	O
war	O	O
against	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
the	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Khmer	O	O
Rouge	O	O
,	O	O
with	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
the	CONCEPTUAL	political_adjective/J1
Vietnamese	MEDIA	periodical/N1
Communist	MEDIA	periodical/N1
Nhan	O	O
Dan	O	O
newspaper	O	O
regularly	O	O
calling	O	O
for	O	O
international	O	O
intervention	O	O
to	O	O
save	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
the	O	O
Kampuchean	O	O
people	O	O
from	O	O
domestic	O	O
terror	O	O
initiated	O	O
by	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
the	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Khmer	O	O
Rouge	O	O

Furthermore	O	O
,	O	O
instead	O	O
of	O	O
sending	O	O
congratulatory	O	O
messages	O	O
like	O	O
they	O	O
had	O	O
done	O	O
in	O	O
the	O	O
previous	O	O
years	O	O
,	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
media	O	O
changed	O	O
their	O	O
tone	O	O
and	O	O
began	O	O
referring	O	O
to	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
Government	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
as	O	O
the	O	O
"	O	O
Pol	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
Pot	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
-	O	O
Ieng	PERSON	politician/N2
Sary	PERSON	politician/N2
clique	O	O
"	O	O
as	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
military	O	O
continued	O	O
their	O	O
campaign	O	O
in	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
.	O	O

By	O	O
the	O	O
end	O	O
of	O	O
June	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
military	O	O
assembled	O	O
a	O	O
multi	O	O
-	O	O
division	O	O
task	O	O
force	O	O
to	O	O
launch	O	O
another	O	O
limited	O	O
-	O	O
objective	O	O
campaign	O	O
against	O	O
the	O	O
Kampucheans	PERSON_TYPE	member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1
.	O	O

Again	O	O
,	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	CONCEPT	language/N1
pushed	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
forces	O	O
back	O	O
into	O	O
the	O	O
provincial	O	O
cities	O	O
of	O	O
Suong	LOCATION	municipality/N1
and	O	O
Prey	LOCATION	state/N2
Veng	LOCATION	state/N2
and	O	O
then	O	O
pulled	O	O
out	O	O
.	O	O

However	O	O
,	O	O
as	O	O
they	O	O
had	O	O
done	O	O
before	O	O
,	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
Army	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
moved	O	O
its	O	O
artillery	O	O
towards	O	O
the	O	O
border	O	O
and	O	O
continued	O	O
shelling	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
villages	O	O
as	O	O
though	O	O
nothing	O	O
had	O	O
happened	O	O
.	O	O

During	O	O
the	O	O
second	O	O
half	O	O
of	O	O
1978	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
leaders	O	O
devoted	O	O
much	O	O
of	O	O
their	O	O
energy	O	O
towards	O	O
the	O	O
military	O	O
campaign	O	O
against	O	O
the	O	O
Khmer	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Rouge	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
regime	O	O
,	O	O
by	O	O
seeking	O	O
political	O	O
support	O	O
from	O	O
the	O	O
Soviet	LOCATION	country/N1
Union	LOCATION	country/N1
.	O	O

In	O	O
a	O	O
briefing	O	O
with	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
Foreign	ORGANISATION	government_department/N1
Ministry	ORGANISATION	government_department/N1
officials	O	O
on	O	O
25	PERIOD	date/N7
July	PERIOD	date/N7
1978	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
the	O	O
Soviet	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
charge	O	O
d	O	O
'	O	O
affaires	LOCATION	municipality/N1
in	O	O
Hanoi	O	O
was	O	O
told	O	O
that	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
the	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
Kampuchean	O	O
Government	O	O
had	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
deployed	O	O
14	O	O
of	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
its	O	O
17	O	O
regular	O	O
army	O	O
divisions	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
and	O	O
16	O	O
local	O	O
regiments	O	O
along	O	O
the	O	O
border	LOCATION	country/N1
with	O	O

Then	O	O
,	O	O
in	O	O
early	O	O
September	PERIOD	date/N7
1978	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
Le	PERSON	politician/N2
Duan	PERSON	politician/N2
informed	O	O
the	O	O
Soviet	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
ambassador	O	O
that	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
aimed	O	O
to	O	O
"	O	O
solve	O	O
fully	O	O
this	O	O
question	O	O
of	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
by	O	O
the	O	O
beginning	O	O
of	O	O
1979	PERIOD	date/N7
"	O	O
.	O	O

While	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
was	O	O
laying	O	O
the	O	O
political	O	O
foundation	O	O
for	O	O
the	O	O
military	O	O
campaign	O	O
against	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
,	O	O
Soviet	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
ships	O	O
were	O	O
reported	O	O
to	O	O
be	O	O
unloading	O	O
military	O	O
hardware	O	O
and	O	O
ammunition	O	O
in	O	O
Cam	LOCATION	delimited_body_of_water/N1
Ranh	LOCATION	delimited_body_of_water/N1
Bay	LOCATION	delimited_body_of_water/N1
.	O	O

In	O	O
October	PERIOD	date/N7
1978	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
radio	O	O
broadcast	O	O
what	O	O
they	O	O
claimed	O	O
were	O	O
accounts	O	O
of	O	O
uprisings	O	O
against	O	O
the	O	O
Khmer	PERSON_TYPE	member_of_a_military_group/N1
Rouge	PERSON_TYPE	member_of_a_military_group/N1
regime	O	O
,	O	O
urging	O	O
members	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
military	O	O
either	O	O
to	O	O
overthrow	O	O
the	O	O
"	O	O
Pol	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
Pot	PERSON	aristocratic_ruler/N1
-	O	O
Ieng	PERSON	politician/N2
Sary	PERSON	politician/N2
clique	O	O
"	O	O
or	O	O
defect	O	O
to	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
.	O	O

In	O	O
a	O	O
major	O	O
turning	O	O
point	O	O
in	O	O
the	O	O
course	O	O
of	O	O
Soviet	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
-	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
and	O	O
Sino	PERSON_TYPE	member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1
-	PERSON_TYPE	member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1
Vietnamese	PERSON_TYPE	member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1
diplomatic	O	O
relations	O	O
,	O	O
and	O	O
ultimately	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
invasion	O	O
of	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
,	O	O
a	O	O
Treaty	CONCEPT	agreement/N1
of	CONCEPT	agreement/N1
Friendship	CONCEPT	agreement/N1
and	CONCEPT	agreement/N1
Cooperation	CONCEPT	agreement/N1
was	O	O
signed	O	O
between	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
and	O	O
the	O	O
Soviet	LOCATION	country/N1
Union	LOCATION	country/N1
on	O	O
3	PERIOD	date/N7
November	PERIOD	date/N7
1978	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
which	O	O
guaranteed	O	O
the	O	O
former	O	O
of	O	O
vital	O	O
Soviet	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
military	O	O
aid	O	O
in	O	O
the	O	O
scenario	O	O
that	O	O
China	LOCATION	country/N1
intervened	O	O
in	O	O
the	O	O
conflict	O	O
.	O	O

Later	O	O
,	O	O
in	O	O
November	PERIOD	date/N7
1978	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
a	O	O
command	O	O
and	O	O
control	O	O
headquarters	O	O
was	O	O
established	O	O
for	O	O
the	O	O
planned	O	O
invasion	O	O
of	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
,	O	O
with	O	O
Senior	TITLE	O
General	TITLE	O
Le	PERSON	military_person/N1
Djuc	PERSON	military_person/N1
Anh	PERSON	military_person/N1
taking	O	O
full	O	O
control	O	O
of	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
military	O	O
units	O	O
along	O	O
the	O	O
border	O	O
areas	O	O
.	O	O

The	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
government	O	O
drafted	O	O
350	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
,	O	O
000	O	O
men	O	O
into	O	O
the	O	O
military	O	O
to	O	O
replace	O	O
earlier	O	O
losses	O	O
and	O	O
augment	O	O
its	O	O
units	O	O
along	O	O
the	O	O

While	O	O
the	O	O
new	O	O
recruits	O	O
were	O	O
completing	O	O
training	O	O
,	O	O
ten	O	O
divisions	O	O
were	O	O
deployed	O	O
to	O	O
the	O	O
border	O	O
regions	O	O
of	O	O
Long	LOCATION	state/N2
An	LOCATION	state/N2
,	O	O
Djong	LOCATION	state/N2
Thap	LOCATION	state/N2
and	O	O
Tay	LOCATION	municipality/N1
Ninh	LOCATION	municipality/N1
provinces	O	O
.	O	O

Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
also	O	O
shifted	O	O
three	O	O
divisions	O	O
based	O	O
in	O	O
Laos	LOCATION	country/N1
south	O	O
towards	O	O
the	O	O
Laos	LOCATION	country/N1
-	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
border	O	O
.	O	O

On	O	O
13	PERIOD	date/N7
December	PERIOD	date/N7
1978	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
the	O	O
Chinese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
Government	O	O
warned	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
that	O	O
its	O	O
patience	O	O
was	O	O
limited	O	O
,	O	O
and	O	O
that	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
would	O	O
be	O	O
punished	O	O
if	O	O
it	O	O
behaved	O	O
in	O	O
an	O	O
"	O	O
unbridled	O	O
fashion	O	O
"	O	O
.	O	O

Hanoi	ORGANISATION	political_body/N1
claimed	O	O
that	O	O
KUFNS	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
was	O	O
an	O	O
independent	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
communist	O	O
movement	O	O
,	O	O
with	O	O
members	O	O
drawn	O	O
from	O	O
all	O	O
walks	O	O
of	O	O
life	O	O
.	O	O

Heng	PERSON	politician/N2
Samrin	PERSON	politician/N2
,	O	O
formerly	O	O
a	O	O
member	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
Khmer	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Rouge	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
and	O	O
commander	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
4th	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
Division	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
,	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
was	O	O
the	O	O
chairman	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
KUFNS	O	O
Central	ORGANISATION	O
Committee	ORGANISATION	O
.	ORGANISATION	O

Previously	O	O
,	O	O
the	O	O
KUFNS	ORGANISATION	political_party/N1
was	O	O
known	O	O
as	O	O
the	O	O
Provisional	LOCATION	country/N1
Revolutionary	LOCATION	country/N1
Government	LOCATION	country/N1
of	LOCATION	country/N1
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
(	O	O
PRGK	ORGANISATION	O
)	O	O
,	O	O
which	O	O
consisted	O	O
of	O	O
300	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
former	O	O
Khmer	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
Rouge	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
cadres	O	O
who	O	O
defected	O	O
to	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
.	O	O

The	O	O
PRGK	ORGANISATION	O
regularly	O	O
sent	O	O
representatives	O	O
abroad	O	O
in	O	O
search	O	O
of	O	O
support	O	O
,	O	O
before	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
abandoned	O	O
the	O	O
'	O	O
people	O	O
'	O	O
s	O	O
war	O	O
'	O	O
concept	O	O
in	O	O
favour	O	O
of	O	O
a	O	O
conventional	O	O
military	O	O
campaign	O	O
,	O	O
similar	O	O
to	O	O
the	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
Soviet	O	O
invasion	O	O
of	LOCATION	historical_country/N1
Czechoslovakia	O	O
in	PERIOD	date/N7
1968	O	O

Not	O	O
to	O	O
be	O	O
outdone	O	O
by	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
military	O	O
build	O	O
-	O	O
up	O	O
,	O	O
the	O	O
Government	ORGANISATION	O
of	ORGANISATION	O
Democratic	ORGANISATION	O
Kampuchea	ORGANISATION	O
was	O	O
busy	O	O
strengthening	O	O
its	O	O
armed	O	O
forces	O	O
with	O	O
Chinese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
support	O	O
.	O	O

In	O	O
previous	O	O
years	O	O
,	O	O
China	LOCATION	country/N1
had	O	O
only	O	O
provided	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
Revolutionary	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
Army	ORGANISATION	military_organization/N1
with	O	O
a	O	O
limited	O	O
amount	O	O
of	O	O
arms	O	O
and	O	O
ammunition	O	O
,	O	O
but	O	O
as	O	O
relations	O	O
with	O	O
Vietnam	LOCATION	country/N1
worsened	O	O
in	O	O
1978	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
Beijing	LOCATION	municipality/N1
established	O	O
additional	O	O
supply	O	O
routes	O	O
through	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
and	O	O
increased	O	O
the	O	O
volume	O	O
of	O	O
military	O	O
hardware	O	O
which	O	O
travelled	O	O
down	O	O
each	O	O
route	O	O
.	O	O

On	O	O
the	O	O
eve	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnamese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
invasion	O	O
,	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
had	O	O
an	O	O
estimated	O	O
73	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
,	O	O
000	O	O
soldiers	O	O
in	LOCATION	O
the	LOCATION	O
Eastern	LOCATION	O
Military	O	O
Zone	LOCATION	country/N1
bordering	O	O

At	O	O
that	O	O
time	O	O
,	O	O
all	O	O
branches	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
Kampuchean	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
armed	O	O
forces	O	O
were	O	O
significantly	O	O
strengthened	O	O
by	O	O
large	O	O
quantities	O	O
of	O	O
Chinese	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
-	O	O
made	O	O
military	O	O
equipment	O	O
,	O	O
which	O	O
included	O	O
fighter	O	O
aircraft	O	O
,	O	O
patrol	O	O
boats	O	O
,	O	O
heavy	O	O
artillery	O	O
,	O	O
anti	O	O
-	O	O
aircraft	O	O
guns	O	O
,	O	O
trucks	O	O
and	O	O
tanks	O	O
.	O	O

Additionally	O	O
,	O	O
there	O	O
were	O	O
between	O	O
10	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
,	O	O
000	MEASURE	rational_number/N1
and	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
20	O	O
,	O	O
000	O	O
Chinese	O	O
advisers	O	O
in	O	O
both	O	O
military	O	O
and	O	O
civilian	O	O
capacities	O	O
,	O	O
providing	O	O
their	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
support	ORGANISATION	terrorist_organization/N1
to	O	O
the	O	O

Invasion	O	O
of	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1

Early	O	O
in	O	O
December	PERIOD	date/N7
1978	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
Kampuchea	LOCATION	country/N1
'	O	O
s	O	O
new	O	O
found	O	O
strength	O	O
was	O	O
tested	O	O
when	O	O
a	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
Vietnamese	O	O
offensive	O	O
,	O	O
consisting	O	O
of	O	O
two	O	O
divisions	O	O
,	O	O
crossed	O	O
the	O	O
border	O	O
and	O	O
moved	O	O
towards	O	O
the	O	O
town	O	O
of	LOCATION	municipality/N1
Kratie	O	O
,	O	O
while	O	O
other	O	O
support	O	O
divisions	O	O
were	O	O
deployed	O	O
along	O	O
local	O	O
routes	O	O
to	O	O
cut	O	O
off	O	O
the	O	O
logistical	O	O
tail	O	O
of	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
Kampuchean	O	O
units	O	O

units	O	O

-DOCSTART- -54/71/America_in_Vietnam.semdoc.xml-
America	CREATION	written_composition/N1
in	CREATION	written_composition/N1
Vietnam	CREATION	written_composition/N1
-	O	O
Wikipedia	UNKNOWN	information_web_site/N1
,	UNKNOWN	information_web_site/N1
the	UNKNOWN	information_web_site/N1
free	UNKNOWN	information_web_site/N1
encyclopedia	UNKNOWN	information_web_site/N1

America	CREATION	written_composition/N1
in	CREATION	written_composition/N1
Vietnam	CREATION	written_composition/N1

America	CREATION	written_composition/N1
in	CREATION	written_composition/N1
Vietnam	CREATION	written_composition/N1
is	O	O
a	O	O
book	O	O
by	O	O
Guenter	PERSON	writer/N1
Lewy	PERSON	writer/N1
about	O	O
America	LOCATION	country/N1
'	O	O
s	O	O
role	O	O
in	O	O
the	EVENT	military_action/N1
Vietnam	EVENT	military_action/N1
War	O	O

The	O	O
book	O	O
is	O	O
highly	O	O
influential	O	O
,	O	O
although	O	O
it	O	O
has	O	O
remained	O	O
controversial	O	O
even	O	O
decades	O	O
after	O	O
its	O	O
publication	O	O
.	O	O

Lewy	PERSON	writer/N1
contends	O	O
that	O	O
the	O	O
United	LOCATION	country/N1
States	LOCATION	country/N1
'	O	O
actions	O	O
in	O	O
Vietnam	EVENT	military_action/N1
were	O	O
neither	O	O
illegal	O	O
nor	O	O
immoral	O	O
,	O	O
and	O	O
that	O	O
tales	O	O
of	O	O
American	NATIONAL	jurisdictional_cultural_adjective/J1
atrocities	O	O
were	O	O
greatly	O	O
exaggerated	O	O
in	O	O
what	O	O
he	O	O
understands	O	O
as	O	O
a	O	O
"	O	O
veritable	O	O
industry	O	O
"	O	O
of	O	O
war	O	O
crimes	O	O
allegations	O	O
.	O	O

The	O	O
text	O	O
returned	O	O
to	O	O
the	O	O
limelight	O	O
during	O	O
the	O	O
2004	PERIOD	date/N7
US	LOCATION	country/N1
Presidential	O	O
Election	O	O
,	O	O
when	O	O
it	O	O
was	O	O
cited	O	O
by	O	O
several	O	O
groups	O	O
supporting	O	O
the	O	O
reelection	O	O
of	O	O
George	PERSON	politician/N2
W	PERSON	politician/N2
.	PERSON	politician/N2
Bush	O	O
,	O	O
in	O	O
contending	O	O
that	CONCEPTUAL	political_adjective/J1
Democratic	O	O
presidential	O	O
contender	PERSON	politician/N2
John	PERSON	politician/N2
Kerry	O	O
had	O	O
betrayed	O	O
his	O	O
country	O	O
for	O	O
his	O	O
participation	O	O
in	O	O
anti	O	O
-	O	O
war	O	O
activities	O	O
upon	O	O
his	O	O
return	O	O
from	O	O
service	O	O
in	EVENT	military_action/N1
Vietnam	O	O

Overview	O	O

Published	O	O
in	O	O
1978	PERIOD	date/N7
,	O	O
America	CREATION	written_composition/N1
in	CREATION	written_composition/N1
Vietnam	CREATION	written_composition/N1
argues	O	O
against	O	O
traditional	O	O
or	O	O
"	O	O
orthodox	O	O
"	O	O
interpretations	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
war	O	O
as	O	O
unnecessary	O	O
,	O	O
unjust	O	O
,	O	O
or	O	O
unwinnable	O	O
.	O	O

The	O	O
book	O	O
has	O	O
proven	O	O
highly	O	O
controversial	O	O
.	O	O

Historians	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
"	O	O
orthodox	O	O
"	O	O
school	O	O
have	O	O
singled	O	O
it	O	O
out	O	O
for	O	O
harsh	O	O
criticism	O	O
,	O	O
while	O	O
the	O	O
"	O	O
revisionist	O	O
school	O	O
"	O	O
of	O	O
Vietnam	EVENT	military_action/N1
historiography	O	O
holds	O	O
it	O	O
to	O	O
be	O	O
a	O	O
watershed	O	O
in	O	O
the	O	O
literature	O	O
on	O	O
the	O	O
war	O	O
.	O	O

An	O	O
infamous	O	O
text	O	O
among	O	O
critics	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnam	EVENT	military_action/N1
War	EVENT	military_action/N1
,	O	O
the	O	O
text	O	O
has	O	O
found	O	O
ardent	O	O
support	O	O
among	O	O
the	O	O
revisionist	O	O
minority	O	O
of	O	O
academics	O	O
,	O	O
such	O	O
as	O	O
Norman	PERSON	journalist/N1
Podhoretz	PERSON	journalist/N1
,	O	O
Mark	PERSON	intellectual/N1
Moyar	PERSON	intellectual/N1
,	O	O
and	O	O
Michael	PERSON	journalist/N1
Lind	PERSON	journalist/N1
.	O	O

America	CREATION	written_composition/N1
in	CREATION	written_composition/N1
Vietnam	CREATION	written_composition/N1
is	O	O
frequently	O	O
characterized	O	O
as	O	O
a	O	O
"	O	O
revisionist	O	O
"	O	O
history	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnam	EVENT	military_action/N1
War	EVENT	military_action/N1
.	O	O

Lewy	PERSON	writer/N1
argues	O	O
,	O	O

It	O	O
is	O	O
the	O	O
reasoned	O	O
conclusion	O	O
of	O	O
this	O	O
study	O	O
.	O	O
.	O	O
.	O	O
that	O	O
the	O	O
sense	O	O
of	O	O
guilt	O	O
created	O	O
by	EVENT	military_action/N1
the	EVENT	military_action/N1
Vietnam	O	O
war	O	O
in	O	O
the	O	O
minds	O	O
of	PERSON_TYPE	member_of_an_ethnic_group/N1
many	O	O
Americans	O	O
is	O	O
not	O	O
warranted	O	O
and	O	O
that	O	O
the	O	O
charges	O	O
of	O	O
officially	O	O
,	O	O
condoned	O	O
illegal	O	O
and	O	O
grossly	O	O
immoral	O	O
conduct	O	O
are	O	O
without	O	O

Indeed	O	O
,	O	O
detailed	O	O
examination	O	O
of	O	O
battlefield	O	O
practices	O	O
reveals	O	O
that	O	O
the	O	O
loss	O	O
civilian	O	O
life	O	O
in	O	O
Vietnam	EVENT	military_action/N1
was	O	O
less	O	O
great	O	O
than	O	O
in	O	O
World	EVENT	military_action/N1
War	EVENT	military_action/N1
II	EVENT	military_action/N1
and	O	O
Korea	LOCATION	peninsula/N1
and	O	O
that	O	O
concern	O	O
with	O	O
minimizing	O	O
the	O	O
ravages	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
war	O	O
was	O	O
strong	O	O
.	O	O

To	O	O
measure	O	O
and	O	O
compare	O	O
the	O	O
devastation	O	O
and	O	O
loss	O	O
of	O	O
human	O	O
life	O	O
caused	O	O
by	O	O
different	O	O
war	O	O
will	O	O
be	O	O
objectionable	O	O
to	O	O
those	O	O
who	O	O
repudiate	O	O
all	O	O
resort	O	O
to	O	O
military	O	O
force	O	O
as	O	O
an	O	O
instrument	O	O
of	O	O
foreign	O	O
policy	O	O
and	O	O
may	O	O
be	O	O
construed	O	O
as	O	O
callousness	O	O
.	O	O

Yet	O	O
as	O	O
long	O	O
as	O	O
wars	O	O
do	O	O
take	O	O
place	O	O
at	O	O
all	O	O
it	O	O
remains	O	O
a	O	O
moral	O	O
duty	O	O
to	O	O
seek	O	O
to	O	O
reduce	O	O
the	O	O
agony	O	O
caused	O	O
by	O	O
war	O	O
,	O	O
and	O	O
the	O	O
fulfillment	O	O
of	O	O
this	O	O
obligation	O	O
should	O	O
not	O	O
be	O	O
disdained	O	O
.	O	O

I	O	O
hope	O	O
that	O	O
this	O	O
book	O	O
may	O	O
help	O	O
demonstrate	O	O
that	O	O
moral	O	O
convictions	O	O
are	O	O
not	O	O
the	O	O
exclusive	O	O
possession	O	O
of	O	O
persons	O	O
in	O	O
conscience	O	O
opposed	O	O
to	O	O
war	O	O
,	O	O
and	O	O
that	O	O
those	O	O
who	O	O
in	O	O
certain	O	O
circumstances	O	O
accept	O	O
the	O	O
necessity	O	O
and	O	O
ethical	O	O
justification	O	O
of	O	O
armed	O	O
conflict	O	O
also	O	O
do	O	O
care	O	O
about	O	O
human	O	O
suffering	O	O
.	O	O

The	O	O
text	O	O
was	O	O
praised	O	O
by	O	O
US	LOCATION	country/N1
Senator	TITLE	political_title/N1
Jim	PERSON	politician/N2
Webb	PERSON	politician/N2
,	O	O
a	O	O
Vietnam	O	O
veteran	O	O
then	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
House	ORGANISATION	government_department/N1
Committee	ORGANISATION	government_department/N1
on	ORGANISATION	government_department/N1
Veteran	ORGANISATION	government_department/N1
'	ORGANISATION	government_department/N1
s	ORGANISATION	government_department/N1
Affairs	O	O
staff	O	O
,	O	O
and	O	O
by	O	O
several	O	O
newspapers	O	O
,	O	O
including	MEDIA	periodical/N1
The	MEDIA	periodical/N1
Economist	O	O
,	O	O
which	O	O
described	O	O
it	O	O
as	O	O
"	O	O
in	O	O
many	O	O
way	O	O
the	O	O
best	O	O
history	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
war	O	O
yet	O	O
to	O	O
appear	O	O
"	O	O

Critics	O	O
have	O	O
included	O	O
historians	O	O
of	O	O
the	O	O
"	O	O
orthodox	O	O
"	O	O
school	O	O
,	O	O
as	O	O
well	O	O
as	O	O
various	O	O
anti	O	O
-	O	O
war	O	O
activists	O	O
.	O	O

Bertrand	PERSON	intellectual/N1
Russell	PERSON	intellectual/N1
and	O	O
Noam	PERSON	intellectual/N1
Chomsky	PERSON	intellectual/N1
were	O	O
singled	O	O
out	O	O
for	O	O
criticism	O	O
by	O	O
Lewy	PERSON	writer/N1
in	O	O
the	O	O
book	O	O
;	O	O
Chomsky	PERSON	intellectual/N1
would	O	O
later	O	O
respond	O	O
that	O	O
"	O	O
every	O	O
state	O	O
has	O	O
its	O	O
Guenter	PERSON	O
Lewys	PERSON	O
"	O	O
.	O	O

Lewy	PERSON	writer/N1
contends	O	O
that	O	O
the	O	O
Vietnam	EVENT	military_action/N1
War	EVENT	military_action/N1
was	O	O
legal	O	O
and	O	O
not	O	O
immoral	O	O
.	O	O
