<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="100100" id="root" date="1996-10-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Sept U.S. layoffs up from Aug but still low - report.</title>
<headline>Sept U.S. layoffs up from Aug but still low - report.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1996-10-07</dateline>
<text> 
<p>U.S. layoffs rose last month, but spot labor shortages and fewer merger-related layoffs helped make September the second-lowest job-cuts month so far in 1996, said a report by Challenger, Gray &amp; Christmas Inc.</p>
<p>Announced layoffs in September totaled 29,632, up 46 percent from August's 20,309 but down 10.7 percent from 33,173 in September 1995, the report said.</p>
<p>The August total was the lowest for any month since April 1995, it said.  </p>
<p>&quot;For the past two months, spot labor shortages in some industries have helped to suppress the number of job cuts overall,&quot; said John Challenger, executive vice president at the international outplacement firm.</p>
<p>A decline in merger-related job cuts helped contain the overall number of layoffs as well, the report said.</p>
<p>In May through September 1996, six percent of total employee discharges were attributed to mergers, compared with 22 percent during the same period of 1995, it said.</p>
<p>Companies continue to trim their payrolls in order to keep wages under control, Challenger said.  </p>
<p>&quot;Management views downsizing as a valve,&quot; he said. &quot;When the number of employees reaches a level that pushes against the wage ceiling, management turns the valve, discharging employees and relieving wage pressure.&quot;  </p>
<p>The report said that for the first nine months of 1996, 8.3 percent of job cuts were merger-driven, compared with 13.6 percent a year earlier.</p>
<p>In the first nine months of 1996, 362,297 layoffs were announced, against 302,017 in the first nine months of 1995, the report said.</p>
<p>-- N.A. Treasury 212-859-1660</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1996</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-10-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-10-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-10-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-10-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-10-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-10-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1996-10-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-10-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1996-10-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
